[
{
    "title": "Iloilo sounds alarm over rising dengue cases",
    "timestamp": "August 3, 2016",
    "content": "THE death toll due to dengue hemorrhagic fever has doubled and the cases continue to increase significantly causing alarming remark from health officials that the trend might reach epidemic threshold if left unresolved.   Provincial Health Officer Dr. Patricia Grace Trabado revealed that the recorded dengue cases from January 1 to July 23, 2016 have reached the alert threshold. Alert threshold refers to the level of occurrence of disease that serves as an early warning for epidemics. “There is an impending dengue outbreak that we must prevent from happening again,” stressed Trabado during the Dengue Summit held in Casa Real de Iloilo on August 2. The first dengue outbreak in Iloilo was in 1998. The second occurred 12 years after wherein cases rose by 512% from 1,061 with 18 deaths in 2009 to 6,500 with 32 deaths in 2010. Five years have passed and another spike in the recorded dengue cases was detected as of the 29th morbidity week, according to the Provincial Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit (PESU). As of July 23, the sum of the cases recorded in 43 local government units increased by 196 percent (2,179 cases with eight deaths) compared to cases on the same period in 2015 (737 cases with four deaths). The figure was also 159 percent higher compared to cases recorded on the same period in 2014 (842 cases with seven deaths). “I am alarmed by the rising cases of dengue. We should address this public health problem immediately,” Governor Arthur Defensor Sr. urged the municipal mayors present during the Dengue Summit. All is at risk “The incidence of dengue has grown dramatically and people of all ages, regardless of status in life, are at risk,” stressed Trabado. Based on the recorded dengue cases this year, the median age bracket affected by dengue was from one to ten years old (883 cases; 449 of which were female). It was then followed by people aging from 11 to 20 years old (849 cases; 476 of which were male) and 21 to 30 years old (223 cases; 121 of which were male). An eight-year-old Grade 3 pupil in Anilao was the first patient who died of dengue in Iloilo on January 7. Grade 1 (six-year-old) and Grade 2 (seven-year-old) pupils from Igbaras and Sta. Barbara added to the list of fatalities on March 23 and 28, respectively. So far, a 30-year-old male from Concepcion was the oldest patient to die of dengue on May 14, while the youngest was a four-year-old girl in Alimodian on June 27. On June 9, Calinog, he town with the most number of dengue cases at 191, registered its first fatality – a ten-year-old Grade 5 pupil. The other two fatalities, who were both six years old females, were recorded in Maasin on July 22 and Sta. Barbara on July 18. Defensor appealed to the public that if they have high fever (40°Celsius) they must not hesitate to bring themselves to the nearest district hospitals where suspected dengue cases were treated for free. “If any of the 12 district hospitals will demand for payment during your confinement, report it to me immediately. If you don’t have any medical insurance and you are an indigent, we will enroll you to PhilHealth’s Point of Care Program,” he said. Early detection and treatment of suspected dengue cases will help prevent the rising death toll, according to Dr. Glenn Alonsabe, chief epidemiologist of the Department of Health Regional Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit in Western Visayas. Instead of spreading their selves too thin, Alonsabe advised that the strategies on search and destroy of mosquito breeding grounds must be targeted first in barangays with clustering of cases and in schools where the affected population could be found most of the time. The top ten towns with the most number of dengue cases were Calinog (192 with 1 death), Sta. Barbara (152 with 2 deaths), Sara (131 cases), Passi City (109 cases), Pototan (101 cases), Estancia (92 cases), Oton (92 cases), Miagao (91 cases), Pavia (84 cases), Cabatuan (79 cases). Meanwhile, Trabado also recommended that the Action Barangay Kontra Dengue (ABKD) has to be reorganized, reactivate or organized in every barangay to plan, implement, monitor and evaluate the status of dengue transmission in their locality. She also encouraged the mayors to dedicate one day in a week for the municipal-wide search and destroy activity known as “People Power: Do Day Kontra Dengue”, especially in schools.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/iloilo/local-news/2016/08/03/iloilo-sounds-alarm-over-rising-dengue-cases-489198",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(22, 46, 'DISEASE'), (51, 58, 'CHANGE'), (67, 72, 'CASE'), (309, 314, 'CASE'), (747, 752, 'CASE'), (897, 902, 'CASE'), (1048, 1053, 'CASE'), (1124, 1129, 'CASE'), (1161, 1166, 'CASE'), (1199, 1204, 'CASE'), (1275, 1280, 'CASE'), (1322, 1327, 'CASE'), (1376, 1381, 'CASE'), (1720, 1725, 'CASE'), (1814, 1819, 'CASE'), (1914, 1919, 'CASE'), (1973, 1978, 'CASE'), (2489, 2494, 'CASE'), (2866, 2871, 'CASE'), (3193, 3198, 'CASE'), (3573, 3578, 'CASE'), (3706, 3711, 'CASE'), (3789, 3794, 'CASE'), (3813, 3818, 'CASE'), (3834, 3839, 'CASE'), (3855, 3860, 'CASE'), (3872, 3877, 'CASE'), (3891, 3896, 'CASE'), (3909, 3914, 'CASE'), (3930, 3935, 'CASE'), (85, 93, 'CHANGE'), (181, 189, 'STATE'), (302, 308, 'DISEASE'), (512, 518, 'DISEASE'), (600, 606, 'DISEASE'), (665, 671, 'DISEASE'), (890, 896, 'DISEASE'), (1385, 1391, 'DISEASE'), (1527, 1533, 'DISEASE'), (1575, 1581, 'DISEASE'), (1713, 1719, 'DISEASE'), (1772, 1778, 'DISEASE'), (2081, 2087, 'DISEASE'), (2343, 2349, 'DISEASE'), (2482, 2488, 'DISEASE'), (2859, 2865, 'DISEASE'), (3186, 3192, 'DISEASE'), (3699, 3705, 'DISEASE'), (4006, 4012, 'DISEASE'), (4140, 4146, 'DISEASE'), (4329, 4335, 'DISEASE'), (320, 346, 'DATE'), (478, 487, 'STATE'), (519, 527, 'STATE'), (672, 680, 'STATE'), (622, 641, 'GPE'), (645, 653, 'DATE'), (635, 641, 'GPE'), (684, 690, 'GPE'), (2091, 2097, 'GPE'), (698, 702, 'DATE'), (724, 726, 'CARDINAL'), (2910, 2912, 'CARDINAL'), (753, 757, 'CHANGE'), (761, 765, 'PERCENT'), (771, 776, 'CARDINAL'), (782, 784, 'CARDINAL'), (2688, 2690, 'CARDINAL'), (795, 799, 'DATE'), (803, 808, 'CARDINAL'), (814, 816, 'CARDINAL'), (827, 831, 'DATE'), (833, 837, 'CARDINAL'), (964, 1009, 'ORG'), (1011, 1015, 'ORG'), (333, 340, 'DATE'), (1024, 1031, 'DATE'), (1066, 1068, 'CARDINAL'), (1092, 1101, 'CHANGE'), (1105, 1116, 'PERCENT'), (1118, 1123, 'CARDINAL'),(1135, 1140), (2008, 2013), (1189, 1193, 'DATE'), (1195, 1198, 'CARDINAL'), (1210, 1214, 'CARDINAL'), (2386, 2390, 'CARDINAL'), (1244, 1255, 'PERCENT'), (1256, 1262, 'CHANGE'), (1312, 1316, 'DATE'), (1318, 1321, 'CARDINAL'), (1333, 1338, 'CARDINAL'), (1369, 1375, 'CHANGE'), (3221, 3227, 'CHANGE'), (1586, 1591, 'CHANGE'), (1788, 1791, 'CARDINAL'), (4222, 4225, 'CARDINAL'), (1795, 1798, 'CARDINAL'), (2537, 2540, 'CARDINAL'), (3665, 3668, 'CARDINAL'), (1810, 1813, 'CARDINAL'), (1821, 1824, 'CARDINAL'), (1949, 1951, 'CARDINAL'), (1955, 1957, 'CARDINAL'), (2277, 2279, 'CARDINAL'), (1969, 1972, 'CARDINAL'), (1980, 1983, 'CARDINAL'), (2040, 2046, 'GPE'), (2101, 2110, 'DATE'), (2176, 2183, 'GPE'), (2188, 2200, 'GPE'), (2667, 2679, 'GPE'), (3745, 3757, 'GPE'), (2236, 2251, 'DATE'), (2299, 2309, 'GPE'), (2353, 2359, 'DATE'), (2408, 2417, 'GPE'), (2421, 2428, 'DATE'), (2433, 2439, 'DATE'), (2441, 2448, 'GPE'), (3717, 3724, 'GPE'), (2453, 2457, 'LOC_TYPE'), (3669, 3673, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2498, 2501, 'CARDINAL'), (2575, 2578, 'CARDINAL'), (2645, 2651, 'GPE'), (2655, 2662, 'DATE'), (2683, 2690, 'DATE'), (2824, 2842, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2913, 2931, 'LOC_TYPE'), (3097, 3107, 'ORG'), (3301, 3365, 'ORG'), (3369, 3384, 'GPE'), (3544, 3553, 'LOC_TYPE'), (3586, 3593, 'LOC_TYPE'), (4352, 4359, 'LOC_TYPE'), (3726, 3729, 'CARDINAL'), (3735, 3736, 'CARDINAL'), (3759, 3762, 'CARDINAL'), (815, 816, 'CARDINAL'), (3768, 3769, 'CARDINAL'), (3785, 3788, 'CARDINAL'), (3809, 3812, 'CARDINAL'), (3830, 3833, 'CARDINAL'), (3852, 3854, 'CARDINAL'), (3869, 3871, 'CARDINAL'), (2499, 2501, 'CARDINAL'), (1318, 1320, 'CARDINAL'), (1121, 1123, 'CARDINAL'), (3990, 3998, 'LOC_TYPE'), (4076, 4084, 'LOC_TYPE') ]"
},
{
    "title": "1,121 dengue cases in January 2017",
    "timestamp": "February3, 2017",
    "content": "THE Department of Health (DOH) 7 reported 1,121 dengue cases for January 2017, or 38 percent lower compared to the 1,815 dengue cases for the same period in 2016. Rennan Cimafranca, of the DOH’s Regional Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit (Resu) said Resu recorded 12 deaths from dengue in January 2017, which is lesser to the 14 deaths recorded in the same period last year. Cimafranca said the figures on dengue cases covers Region 7, which is composed of Cebu, Bohol and Siquijor. Cimafranca said the top five areas are Cebu City, with 156 cases including two deaths; Mandaue City, with 126 including one death; Lapu-Lapu City, with 104 cases including two deaths; Consolacion, with 64 cases including four deaths; and Toledo City, with 47 cases. Cimafranca said that both sexes were almost equally represented in dengue cases, with 50.3 percent male and 49.7 percent female. Most of those affected were within the 6-10 age bracket. On the other hand, Cyril Pangatungan of the Provincial Health Office (PHO) Provincial Epidemology Surveillance Unit (Pesu) reported 451 dengue cases in January 2017, which is lower than the 722 cases of the same period in 2016. Pangatungan reported to Gov. Hilario Davide III that there were five deaths caused by dengue in January 2017. Pangatungan said the top five areas with dengue cases are Consolacion town, with 60 cases; Toledo City, with 47 cases; Moalboal, with 34 cases; Carcar City, with 33 cases; and Liloan, with 31 cases.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/cebu/local-news/2017/02/03/1121-dengue-cases-january-2017-523625",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(4, 24, 'ORG'), (26, 29, 'ORG'), (189, 192, 'ORG'), (31, 32, 'CARDINAL'), (434, 435, 'CARDINAL'), (1126, 1127, 'CARDINAL'), (42, 47, 'CARDINAL'), (48, 54, 'DISEASE'), (121, 127, 'DISEASE'), (280, 286, 'DISEASE'), (407, 413, 'DISEASE'), (817, 823, 'DISEASE'), (1072, 1078, 'DISEASE'), (1250, 1256, 'DISEASE'), (1315, 1321, 'DISEASE'), (55, 60, 'CASE'), (128, 133, 'CASE'), (414, 419, 'CASE'), (543, 548, 'CASE'), (640, 645, 'CASE'), (689, 694, 'CASE'), (743, 748, 'CASE'), (824, 829, 'CASE'), (1079, 1084, 'CASE'), (1130, 1135, 'CASE'), (1322, 1327, 'CASE'), (1358, 1363, 'CASE'), (1386, 1391, 'CASE'), (1411, 1416, 'CASE'), (1439, 1444, 'CASE'), (1466, 1471, 'CASE'), (65, 77, 'DATE'), (290, 302, 'DATE'), (1088, 1100, 'DATE'), (1260, 1272, 'DATE'), (82, 92, 'PERCENT'), (93, 98, 'CHANGE'), (1111, 1116, 'CHANGE'), (115, 120, 'CARDINAL'), (157, 161, 'DATE'), (1158, 1162, 'DATE'), (195, 238, 'ORG'), (240, 244, 'ORG'), (251, 255, 'ORG'), (265, 267, 'CARDINAL'), (327, 329, 'CARDINAL'), (427, 435, 'GPE'), (458, 462, 'GPE'), (464, 469, 'GPE'), (474, 482, 'GPE'), (523, 532, 'GPE'), (539, 542, 'CARDINAL'), (559, 562, 'CARDINAL'), (656, 659, 'CARDINAL'), (571, 583, 'GPE'), (590, 593, 'CARDINAL'), (604, 607, 'CARDINAL'), (615, 629), (636, 639, 'CARDINAL'), (668, 679, 'GPE'), (1332, 1343, 'GPE'), (686, 688, 'CARDINAL'), (705, 709, 'CARDINAL'), (722, 733, 'GPE'), (1365, 1376, 'GPE'), (740, 742, 'CARDINAL'), (1383, 1385, 'CARDINAL'), (836, 848, 'PERCENT'), (858, 870, 'PERCENT'), (980, 1004, 'ORG'), (1006, 1009, 'ORG'), (1011, 1051, 'ORG'), (1053, 1057, 'ORG'), (1068, 1071, 'CARDINAL'), (1126, 1129, 'CARDINAL'), (508, 512, 'CARDINAL'), (1228, 1232, 'CARDINAL'), (1299, 1303, 'CARDINAL'), (1355, 1357, 'CARDINAL'), (1393, 1401, 'GPE'), (1408, 1410, 'CARDINAL'), (1418, 1429, 'GPE'), (1436, 1438, 'CARDINAL'), (1450, 1456, 'GPE'), (1463, 1465, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "Measles cases in Davao City increase",
    "timestamp": "January 17, 2018",
    "content": "THE Davao City Health Office (CHO) has recorded 16 confirmed cases of measles and 222 suspected cases in 36 barangays in the city. “We have 222 suspected cases. They have fever, maculopapular rashes, cough, cold, eye redness (conjunctivitis), and other viral symptoms,“ said Assistant City Health Officer Dr. Marjorie Culas through a text message to Sun.Star Davao yesterday. The 16 cases were confirmed after the Research Institute for Tropical Medicine (RITM) in Manila processed their laboratory exams. The CHO has also informed that only districts of Paquibato and Baguio have not reported any cases of measles. Culas, on the other hand, explained that some of the people infected with measles may not be from the city. “There are some of them who are only included in our records because they lived together with their relatives who are residents of the city. But they are actually from neighboring cities or provinces who only went to Davao to be admitted to big hospitals here like in SPMC where they can enjoy free medication,” she said. The official also said that the first report of measles was recorded on November 2017, and then it started to increase in December 2017. She said these are from areas where evacuees from war-torn cities stayed. However, she said that it’s hard to speculate that they brought the virus here. There were also received reports from Mini-forest Health Center near Magsaysay Park. “They don't have immunization cards to show or some has no history of immunization,“ she added. An Outbreak Immunization Response (ORI) last November and December was made to prevent an outbreak or epidemic. They managed to immunize 15 thousand children but 600 refused immunization. “Maybe they fear vaccination, or maybe it’s the Dengvaxia controversy getting their way. Some parents are not there during the house-to-house round-up,“ she said. She added that they will continue their ORI until the end of the month. She added that they still have stocks of measles vaccine (MMR Vaccine). Unlike Dengvaxia, the country has been using MMR Vaccine for decades. It’s a guarantee that the vaccine is effective and has no side effects like that of Dengvaxia.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/davao/local-news/2018/01/17/measles-cases-davao-city-increase-584428",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(4, 28, 'ORG'), (30, 33, 'ORG'), (510, 513, 'ORG'), (48, 50, 'CARDINAL'), (380, 382, 'CARDINAL'), (61, 66, 'CASE'), (96, 101, 'CASE'), (154, 159, 'CASE'), (383, 388, 'CASE'), (598, 603, 'CASE'), (70, 77, 'DISEASE'), (607, 614, 'DISEASE'), (690, 697, 'DISEASE'), (1094, 1101, 'DISEASE'), (1982, 1989, 'DISEASE'), (82, 85, 'CARDINAL'), (140, 143, 'CARDINAL'), (105, 107, 'CARDINAL'), (108, 117, 'LOC_TYPE'), (125, 129, 'LOC_TYPE'), (285, 289, 'LOC_TYPE'), (718, 722, 'LOC_TYPE'), (859, 863, 'LOC_TYPE'), (414, 454, 'ORG'), (359, 364, 'GPE'), (941, 946, 'GPE'), (456, 460, 'ORG'), (465, 471, 'GPE'), (542, 551, 'LOC_TYPE'), (555, 564, 'GPE'), (569, 575, 'GPE'), (904, 910, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1242, 1248, 'LOC_TYPE'), (914, 923, 'LOC_TYPE'), (969, 978, 'LOC_TYPE'), (992, 996, 'ORG'), (1118, 1131, 'DATE'), (1168, 1181, 'DATE'), (1207, 1212, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1375, 1400, 'ORG'), (1406, 1420, 'GPE'), (1563, 1571, 'DATE'), (1576, 1584, 'DATE'), (1521, 1529, 'STATE'), (1608, 1616, 'STATE'), (1620, 1628, 'STATE'), (1655, 1666, 'CARDINAL'), (1680, 1683, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "Rise in measles cases seen in NegOcc",
    "timestamp": "May 11, 2015",
    "content": "THE Department of Health Region- Western Visayas (DOH-6) reported 64 cases of measles in Negros Occidental in 2014, from only nine cases in 2013, following an outbreak in 2014. The DOH-6 said the cases in Negros Occidental were part of the 399 laboratory confirmed measles cases in the region in 2014, up by 141 from the previous year’s figure. Dr. Renilyn Reyes, DOH-6 medical specialist II, said that the measles outbreaks in the provinces of Iloilo, Capiz and Negros Occidental last year contributed to the sudden increase of measles cases from 2013. Of the 399 cases, Iloilo had the most number of cases with 145, followed by Capiz with 81, and Negros Occidental with 64. Antique and Guimaras have 29 cases each; Iloilo City, 23; Aklan, 18; and Bacolod, nine. The lone fatality in 2014 was a two-year-old from Antique. “People in Western Visayas are susceptible to measles because the immunization coverage is low,” Reyes said. The main reason why people are infected with measles is because they are not vaccinated, she added. Reyes urged the public to be vaccinated against measles because the vaccines are free. “These vaccines are free and they can combat measles safely and effectively,” she said. The DOH seeks to immunize 95 percent of the children in public schools to lower the chances of measles outbreaks. This coming August, the DOH will also conduct school-based immunization in all government schools and select private schools. Some of the vaccines that will be given are pneumococcal conjugate vaccines, inactivated polio vaccines, tetanus diphtheria vaccines, and human papilloma virus vaccines. Around two million school children in Western Visayas will be given free vaccines. Barredo said the latest patient is a 10-year-old girl from Lipayo, Dauin who was confined at a private hospital in Dumaguete City since January 1. Clinical records show that the patient received vaccine on anti-measles in April 2004. Barredo said that a person who received anti-measles vaccine does not necessary mean he or she will not be infected with measles; however, if a person received anti-measles vaccine, infection will not prolong. Barredo said that 17 to 20 percent of the total population of children in the province failed to avail of the immunization program of the Health department. He said a total of 89,683 children were vaccinated in 2012 and 89,426 children in 2013 or 83 percent of children in the province were fully immunized.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/bacolod/local-news/2015/05/11/rise-measles-cases-seen-negocc-406825",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(4, 24, 'ORG'), (33, 48, 'GPE'), (834, 849, 'GPE'), (1655, 1670, 'GPE'), (50, 55, 'ORG'), (181, 186, 'ORG'), (364, 369, 'ORG'), (66, 68, 'CARDINAL'), (672, 674, 'CARDINAL'), (69, 74, 'CASE'), (131, 136, 'CASE'), (196, 201, 'CASE'), (273, 278, 'CASE'), (537, 542, 'CASE'), (565, 570, 'CASE'), (602, 607, 'CASE'), (705, 710, 'CASE'), (78, 85, 'DISEASE'), (265, 272, 'DISEASE'), (407, 414, 'DISEASE'), (529, 536, 'DISEASE'), (869, 876, 'DISEASE'), (977, 984, 'DISEASE'), (1080, 1087, 'DISEASE'), (1164, 1171, 'DISEASE'), (1302, 1309, 'DISEASE'), (2055, 2062, 'DISEASE'), ,(89, 106, 'GPE'), (205, 222, 'GPE'), (463, 480, 'GPE'), (649, 666, 'GPE'), (110, 114, 'DATE'), (171, 175, 'DATE'), (296, 300, 'DATE'), (785, 789, 'DATE'), (126, 130, 'CARDINAL'), (758, 762, 'CARDINAL'), (140, 144, 'DATE'), (548, 552, 'DATE'), (2383, 2387, 'DATE'), (159, 167, 'STATE'),(240, 243, 'CARDINAL'), (561, 564, 'CARDINAL'), (25, 31, 'LOC_TYPE'), (286, 292, 'LOC_TYPE'), (308, 311, 'CARDINAL'), (321, 334, 'DATE'), (415, 424, 'STATE'), (1310, 1319, 'STATE'), (445, 451, 'GPE'), (572, 578, 'GPE'),(453, 458, 'GPE'), (630, 635, 'GPE'), (481, 490, 'DATE'), (613, 616, 'CARDINAL'), (641, 643, 'CARDINAL'), (676, 683, 'GPE'), (814, 821, 'GPE'), (688, 696, 'GPE'), (702, 704, 'CARDINAL'), (717, 728, 'GPE'), (730, 732, 'CARDINAL'), (734, 739, 'GPE'), (741, 743, 'CARDINAL'), (749, 756, 'GPE'), (1233, 1243, 'PERCENT'), (1281, 1286, 'CHANGE'), (1333, 1339, 'DATE'), (1270, 1277, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1411, 1418, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1438, 1445, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1536, 1541, 'DISEASE'), (1552, 1570, 'DISEASE'), (1585, 1600, 'DISEASE'), (1624, 1635, 'CARDINAL'), (1759, 1772, 'GPE'), (1803, 1811, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1815, 1829, 'GPE'), (1836, 1845, 'DATE'), (1922, 1932, 'DATE'), (2162, 2178, 'PERCENT'), (2320, 2326, 'CARDINAL'), (2355, 2359, 'DATE'), (2364, 2370, 'CARDINAL'), (2391, 2401, 'PERCENT')]"
},
{
    "title": "Measles down 8 in Negros Oriental",
    "timestamp": "January 10, 2014",
    "content": "AT LEAST eight persons were down due to measles infection in Negros Oriental, according to the Integrated Provincial Health Office (IPHO). Records also show that four of them were coming from Dumaguete City, two from Amlan town, one from Dauin, and another one from Basay town. Assistant Provincial Health officer Dr. Edgardo Barredo told Sun.Star that the youngest patient was a four-year-old child from Banilad, Dumaguete City and the oldest was a 29-year-old from Dumaguete City, Basay and Amlan towns.",
    "url": "http://archive.sunstar.com.ph/dumaguete/local-news/2014/01/10/measles-down-8-negros-oriental-322590",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(9, 14, 'CARDINAL'), (40, 47, 'DISEASE'), (61, 76, 'GPE'), (95, 130, 'ORG'), (132, 136, 'ORG'), (162, 166, 'CARDINAL'), (192, 206, 'GPE'), (467, 481, 'GPE'), (208, 211, 'CARDINAL'), (217, 222, 'GPE'), (493, 498, 'GPE'), (238, 243, 'GPE'), (229, 232, 'CARDINAL'), (257, 260, 'CARDINAL'), (266, 271, 'GPE'), (483, 488, 'GPE'), (405, 428, 'GPE'), (223, 227, 'LOC_TYPE'), (272, 276, 'LOC_TYPE'), (499, 503, 'LOC_TYPE'), (499, 504, 'LOC_TYPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "23 fall ill in Toledo; dengue possible",
    "timestamp": "March 15, 2015",
    "content": "Provincial health authorities ruled out typhoid fever as having caused 23 residents of sitio Bayabas, barangay Subayon Toledo City to fall sick last week. Dr. Cynthia Genosolango, head of the Provincial Health Office (PHO), said 23 persons consulted with doctors at the Toledo City Hospital yesterday. Some complained of fever and abdominal pain, while some had fever with cough and cold. Nine of them who had fever for several days were admitted to the hospital. “The PESU (Provincial Epidemiological Surveillance Unit) administered a Typhidot test for admitted patients. All tested negative,” Genosolango said. In text messages to Cebu Daily News, Dr. Genosolango said a mandatory follow-up test still has to be conducted after three to five days. Despite ruling out typhoid fever, the PHO and the Toledo City Health Office have yet to confirm whether the patients have contracted dengue. Dr. Bonito Zanoria, Toledo City Hospital chief, said he suspected that the residents may have contracted dengue based on  their low platelet count result after the CBC tests. Cebu Daily News tried calling Dr. Genosolango but calls to her phone were left unanswered. Genosolango said in her text message that samples from water sources were taken from the area, including two open dug wells and an improvised spring. She said results are expected to come out after three days. A PESU team met with Subayon barangay chairman Florante Lariba early yesterday morning to gather initial data. Earlier this week, the residents personally came to see Lariba to inform him of their situation. Medicines were given to the rural midwife for distribution, said Dr. Genosolango. Genosolango said the PHO will closely monitor the progress of the case.",
    "url": "http://cebudailynews.inquirer.net/53041/23-fall-ill-intoledo-dengue-possible",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(40, 53, 'DISEASE'), (769, 782, 'DISEASE'), (71, 73, 'CARDINAL'), (229, 231, 'CARDINAL'), (93, 100, 'GPE'), (102, 110, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1396, 1404, 'LOC_TYPE'), (111, 118, 'GPE'), (1388, 1395, 'GPE'), (119, 130, 'GPE'),(144, 153, 'DATE'), (192, 216, 'ORG'), (42, 45, 'ORG'), (788, 791, 'ORG'), (1129, 1132, 'ORG'), (1678, 1681, 'ORG'), (270, 290, 'ORG'), (911, 931, 'ORG'), (389, 393, 'CARDINAL'), (282, 290, 'LOC_TYPE'), (454, 462, 'LOC_TYPE'), (923, 931, 'LOC_TYPE'), (469, 473, 'ORG'), (1369, 1373, 'ORG'), (475, 519, 'ORG'), (800, 825, 'ORG'), (1246, 1250, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1262, 1265, 'CARDINAL'), (730, 735, 'CARDINAL'), (1355, 1360, 'CARDINAL'), (739, 743, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH notes quick rise in dengue ‘hot zones’",
    "timestamp": "August 17, 2016",
    "content": "The Department of Health (DOH) on Tuesday identified more barangays around the country as dengue hot zones, after more than 84,000 cases have been reported since Jan. 1 this year. From 47 barangays last week, the number of dengue hot zones shot to 80. In the National Capital Region, declared hot zones were barangays Pinagbuhatan in Pasig City, and Batasan Hills, Fairview, Holy Spirit and Pinyahan in Quezon City. “A hot zone means there is a clustering of cases. Clustering means the barangay has three or more cases for four consecutive weeks,“ DOH spokesperson Dr. Eric Tayag said. He however said there was no outbreak of the disease. “We expect the cases will increase because of the rain, floods. But we can do something to prevent that from happening. Get rid of sources of water where dengue mosquitoes could lay their eggs. Let’s keep our surroundings clean,” he said. Apart from the NCR, hot spots were declared in the provinces of Apayao, Benguet, Pangasinan, Pampanga, Zambales, Batangas, Laguna, Rizal, Oriental Mindoro, Antique, Negros Occidental, Negros Oriental, Cebu, Southern Leyte, Bukidnon, Lanao del Norte, Misamis Oriental, Davao del Norte, Davao del Sur and Davao Oriental. Earlier, Tayag advised hospitals in the hot zones to activate their dengue express lanes. The DOH had issued a directive reactivating dengue-dedicated lanes in public hospitals to hasten the admittance of dengue cases, both suspected and confirmed. “Dengue express lanes are like a one-stop shop where patients, especially children with fever, can be assessed. There they are subjected to tests. Results are faster so they can immediately be advised if they need to be given oresol or IV fluids, or if they could continue their medication at home or need to be hospitalized,” Tayag said. He said that from Jan. 1 to Aug. 6 this year, a total of 84,085 dengue cases were reported, including 372 deaths.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/806910/doh-notes-quick-rise-in-dengue-hot-zones",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(4, 24, 'ORG'), (26, 29, 'ORG'), (549, 552, 'ORG'), (1293, 1296, 'ORG'), (34, 41, 'DATE'), (58, 67, 'LOC_TYPE'), (188, 197, 'LOC_TYPE'), (308, 317, 'LOC_TYPE'), (79, 86, 'LOC_TYPE'), (90, 96, 'DISEASE'), (223, 229, 'DISEASE'), (795, 801, 'DISEASE'), (1267, 1273, 'DISEASE'), (1333, 1339, 'DISEASE'), (1404, 1410, 'DISEASE'), (1851, 1857, 'DISEASE'), (97, 106, 'STATE'), (230, 239, 'STATE'), (293, 302, 'STATE'), (1239, 1248, 'STATE'), (124, 130, 'CARDINAL'), (131, 136, 'CASE'), (459, 464, 'CASE'), (514, 519, 'CASE'), (656, 661, 'CASE'), (1411, 1416, 'CASE'), (1858, 1863, 'CASE'), (162, 168, 'DATE'), (169, 178, 'DATE'), (1822, 1831, 'DATE'), (185, 187, 'CARDINAL'), (198, 207, 'DATE'), (213, 219, 'CASE'), (248, 250, 'CARDINAL'), (259, 282, 'GPE'), (318, 330, 'GPE'), (334, 344, 'GPE'), (350, 363, 'GPE'), (365, 373, 'GPE'), (375, 386, 'GPE'), (391, 399, 'GPE'), (403, 414, 'GPE'), (419, 427, 'STATE'),(487, 495, 'LOC_TYPE'), (500, 505, 'CARDINAL'), (524, 528, 'CARDINAL'), (616, 624, 'STATE'), 667, 675, 'CHANGE'), (668, 671, 'GPE'), (895, 898, 'GPE'), (944, 950, 'GPE'), (952, 959, 'GPE'), (961, 971, 'GPE'), (973, 981, 'GPE'), (983, 991, 'GPE'), (993, 1001, 'GPE'), (1003, 1009, 'GPE'), (1011, 1016, 'GPE'), (1018, 1034, 'GPE'), (1036, 1043, 'GPE'), (1045, 1062, 'GPE'), (1064, 1079, 'GPE'), (1081, 1085, 'GPE'), (1087, 1101, 'GPE'), (1103, 1111, 'GPE'), (1113, 1128, 'GPE'), (1130, 1146, 'GPE'), (1148, 1163, 'GPE'), (1165, 1178, 'GPE'), (1183, 1197, 'GPE'), (1222, 1231, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1366, 1375, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1800, 1821, 'DATE'), (1844, 1850, 'CARDINAL'), (1889, 1892, 'CARDINAL')]"
}
]
