[
{
    "title": "Dengue cases rise by 36% nationwide, says DOH",
    "timestamp": "July 21, 2016",
    "content": "For 39-year-old housewife Maribel, the rainy season used to bring happy memories of her childhood as she and her siblings would frolic in the heavy downpour. But not anymore. Not since a year ago when she almost lost her 8-year-old daughter to dengue hemorrhagic fever, the more severe form of dengue fever, a viral infection transmitted by the Aedes aegypti mosquito. “I had no idea it was that bad. I thought she was just having a flu because she was complaining of headache, she had fever. But it took a few days before we took her to the hospital,” she said. “The doctor said that her blood platelet count dropped to dangerously low levels and she was at risk of bleeding complications and even death,“ recalled the mother of two from Makati City. Nowadays, the rain makes her paranoid because their place easily gets flooded and she knows the risk it brings to her children. Now the mosquito-borne disease is on the rise and the Department of Health (DOH) is reminding the public that dengue is no longer a “rainy season disease” as cases are being reported nationwide throughout the year. Based on the report prepared by the DOH epidemiology bureau, there were 57,026 dengue cases recorded nationwide from Jan. 1 to June 25, or 35.7 percent higher than the 42,026 cases recorded during the same period last year. There was also a higher number of dengue deaths in 2016, with 248 compared with 148 in 2015 during the same period. Based on its latest report, the DOH noted that the regions with the most number of dengue cases during the six-month period were Calabarzon with 7,463 (13.1 percent); Central Visayas, 5,783 (10.1 percent); Central Luzon, 5,586 (9.8 percent); northern Mindanao, 5,521 (9.7 percent); and Socssksargen, 4,583 (8 percent). Calabarzon, Central Visayas and Central Luzon accounted for the highest number of dengue cases in the country despite the introduction of the dengue vaccines to public elementary school students in these regions. Earlier, Grade 4 pupils aged 9 years old and above in public elementary schools in Calabarzon, Central Visayas, Central Luzon, as well as in Metro Manila, were identified as beneficiaries of the Dengue School-Based Immunization program of the DOH that started in April. Through the program, the DOH began the administration of dengue vaccines to students in three doses, with the first one given between April and June. Found to have the biggest increase in dengue cases were Eastern Visayas with a 206-percent increase from 610 last year to 1,870 this year; followed by Davao region with a 138-percent increase from 1,679 to 4,002; and Central Visayas with a 137-percent increase from 2,432 to 5,783. A declining number of dengue cases was noted in Cagayan Valley that saw a 43-percent drop from 2,664 in 2015 to 1,523 this year; and Metro Manila from 4,964 cases to 4,179.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/797679/dengue-cases-rise-by-36-nationwide-says-doh",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(185,195,'DATE'),(244,268,'DISEASE'),(294,306,'DISEASE'),(310,325,'DISEASE'),(433,436,'DISEASE'),(486,491,'DISEASE'),(505,515,'DATE'),(542,550,'ORG'),(610,617,'CHANGE'),(667,689,'DISEASE'),(739,750,'GPE'),(888,910,'DISEASE'),(921,925,'CHANGE'),(934,960,'ORG'),(990,996,'DISEASE'),(1038,1043,'CASE'),(1063,1073,'LOC_TYPE'),(1085,1093,'DATE'),(1131,1154,'ORG'),(1167,1173,'CARDINAL'),(1174,1180,'DISEASE'),(1182,1187,'CASE'),(1196,1207,'LOC_TYPE'),(1212,1229,'DATE'),(1234,1246,'PERCENT'),(1247,1253,'CHANGE'),(1263,1269,'CARDINAL'),(1271,1276,'CASE'),(1308,1317,'DATE'),(1336,1342,'CHANGE'),(1343,1349,'CASE'),(1353,1359,'DISEASE'),(1370,1374,'DATE'),(1381,1384,'CARDINAL'),(1399,1402,'CARDINAL'),(1407,1411,'DATE'),(1467,1470,'ORG'),(1487,1494,'LOC_TYPE'),(1508,1514,'CASE'),(1518,1524,'DISEASE'),(1526,1531,'CASE'),(1542,1551,'DATE'),(1564,1574,'GPE'),(1580,1585,'CARDINAL'),(1587,1599,'PERCENT'),(1602,1618,'GPE'),(1620,1624,'CARDINAL'),(1626,1638,'PERCENT'),(1641,1654,'GPE'),(1656,1661,'CARDINAL'),(1663,1674,'PERCENT'),(1677,1694,'GPE'),(1696,1701,'CARDINAL'),(1703,1714,'PERCENT'),(1721,1733,'GPE'),(1735,1740,'CARDINAL'),(1742,1751,'PERCENT'),(1754,1764,'GPE'),(1766,1781,'GPE'),(1786,1799,'GPE'),(1826,1832,'CASE'),(1836,1842,'DISEASE'),(1844,1849,'CASE'),(1856,1863,'LOC_TYPE'),(1896,1902,'DISEASE'),(1958,1965,'LOC_TYPE'),(2021,2046,'ORG'),(2050,2060,'GPE'),(2062,2077,'GPE'),(2079,2092,'GPE'),(2108,2120,'GPE'),(2162,2168,'DISEASE'),(2210,2213,'ORG'),(2230,2235,'DATE'),(2262,2265,'ORG'),(2294,2300,'DISEASE'),(2325,2330,'CARDINAL'),(2371,2385,'DATE'),(2413,2421,'CHANGE'),(2425,2431,'DISEASE'),(2433,2438,'CASE'),(2443,2458,'GPE'),(2466,2477,'PERCENT'),(2478,2486,'CHANGE'),(2493,2496,'CARDINAL'),(2496,2505,'DATE'),(2509,2514,'CARDINAL'),(2515,2524,'DATE'),(2538,2543,'GPE'),(2544,2550,'LOC_TYPE'),(2558,2569,'PERCENT'),(2570,2578,'CHANGE'),(2584,2589,'CARDINAL'),(2593,2598,'CARDINAL'),(2604,2619,'GPE'),(2627,2638,'PERCENT'),(2639,2647,'CHANGE'),(2653,2658,'CARDINAL'),(2662,2667,'CARDINAL'),(2671,2680,'CHANGE'),(2681,2687,'CASE'),(2691,2697,'DISEASE'),(2699,2705,'CASE'),(2717,2731,'GPE'),(2743,2753,'PERCENT'),(2764,2769,'CARDINAL'),(2773,2777,'DATE'),(2781,2786,'CARDINAL'),(2792,2796,'DATE'),(2802,2814,'GPE'),(2820,2825,'CARDINAL'),(2827,2832,'CASE'),(2835,2840,'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue fever cases going up in Cavite",
    "timestamp": "September 26, 2015",
    "content": "The number of dengue cases in Cavite province remains on a steady rise since health officials declared an outbreak of the mosquito-borne disease last week. Dr. George Repique, provincial health officer, said 3,904 dengue cases had been recorded so far from January to Sept. 12, but added that the number might still increase. The health office listed 16 fatalities among the cases. “Even the number of deaths [may also rise],” Repique said by telephone on Thursday. He said his office was confirming the actual number of fatalities, which the regional health office would release soon. Public hospitals do not have enough health personnel to attend to patients, Repique said, even as more people were showing signs of infection. At the provincial hospital in Trece Martires City alone, 79 people had been admitted in the last four days. On Sept. 18, government officials placed Cavite under a state of calamity after the provincial health office recorded a 200-percent increase in the number of dengue cases from last year’s 1,120. They identified at least four cities—Dasmariñas, Trece Martires, Bacoor and Imus—and General Trias town with the highest number of cases. In Dasmariñas alone, more than 700 cases have been reported. Gov. Juanito Victor Remulla on Wednesday ordered a massive cleanup in all cities and towns, using fogging and misting pesticides from the Department of Health (DOH), to stop dengue-carrying mosquitoes from breeding. “We advise households to keep their surroundings clean and avoid keeping stagnant water where the mosquitoes breed,” Repique said. The province also sought help from the Philippine Red Cross for more health workers. In Bicol, health officials reported a decline in dengue cases but recorded three fatalities from January to Sept. 5. Data from the DOH Regional Epidemiology Surveillance Unit (Resu) showed 895 patients were diagnosed with dengue in the region, indicating an 8-percent decline compared to the 969 recorded over the same period last year. But dengue cases rose in the provinces of Masbate, Camarines Sur and Camarines Norte, said Dr. Aurora Daluro, Resu chief. She, however, said the increase had not reached an alarming level. Daluro asked the public not to be complacent as dengue cases could still rise amid the El Niño-induced dry spell, when people tend to store water in pails or drums that may become breeding areas of mosquitoes.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/725480/dengue-fever-cases-going-up-in-cavite",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(4,10,'CASE'),(14,20,'DISEASE'),(21,26,'CASE'),(30,36,'GPE'),(106,114,'STATE'),(122,144,'DISEASE'),(145,154,'DATE'),(208,213,'CARDINAL'),(214,220,'DISEASE'),(221,226,'CASE'),(257,276,'DATE'),(297,303,'CASE'),(316,324,'CHANGE'),(351,353,'CARDINAL'),(392,398,'CASE'),(66,70,'CHANGE'),(456,464,'DATE'),(511,517,'CASE'),(543,565,'ORG'),(759,778,'GPE'),(786,788,'CARDINAL'),(821,835,'DATE'),(840,848,'DATE'),(878,884,'GPE'),(893,910,'STATE'),(921,945,'ORG'),(957,968,'PERCENT'),(969,977,'CHANGE'),(985,991,'CASE'),(995,1001,'DISEASE'),(1002,1007,'CASE'),(1013,1024,'DATE'),(1025,1030,'CARDINAL'),(1057,1061,'CARDINAL'),(1069,1079,'GPE'),(1081,1095,'GPE'),(1097,1103,'GPE'),(1108,1112,'GPE'),(1117,1135,'GPE'),(1153,1159,'CASE'),(1163,1168,'CASE'),(1173,1183,'GPE'),(1201,1204,'CARDINAL'),(1205,1210,'CASE'),(1262,1271,'DATE'),(1305,1311,'LOC_TYPE'),(1316,1321,'LOC_TYPE'),(1369,1395,'ORG'),(1582,1590,'LOC_TYPE'),(1617,1637,'ORG'),(1666,1671,'GPE'),(1701,1708,'CHANGE'),(1712,1718,'DISEASE'),(1719,1724,'CASE'),(1738,1743,'CARDINAL'),(1760,1778,'DATE'),(1794,1843,'ORG'),(1852,1855,'CARDINAL'),(1885,1891,'DISEASE'),(1899,1905,'LOC_TYPE'),(1921,1930,'PERCENT'),(1931,1938,'CHANGE'),(1955,1958,'CARDINAL'),(1989,1998,'DATE'),(2004,2010,'DISEASE'),(2011,2016,'CASE'),(2029,2038,'LOC_TYPE'),(2042,2049,'GPE'),(2051,2064,'GPE'),(2069,2084,'GPE'),(2145,2153,'CHANGE'),(2237,2243,'DISEASE'),(2244,2249,'CASE'),(2262,2266,'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Cebu declares state of calamity over 5,000 dengue cases",
    "timestamp": "October 17, 2016",
    "content": "CEBU CITY — The entire province of Cebu has declared a state of calamity due to the rising cases of dengue, which have exceeded 5,000 cases since the start of the year. The declaration was embodied in a resolution passed by the Cebu Provincial Board, even without a recommendation from the Department of Health (DOH). Provincial Board Member Christopher Baricuatro, who authored the resolution, said the calamity status would maximize the use of resources and funds to stop or control the spread of dengue. “Given the magnitude of its effect and the necessity to immediately address and prevent the increase of dengue cases in the province, it is imperative to declare a state of calamity in the entire province ,” Baricuatro said. The Provincial Disaster Risk Reduction Management Office (PDRRMO) pushed for the declaration after the Provincial Health Office (PHO) reported a “dramatic” or “abnormal” increase in dengue cases from January to September this year compared to the same period last year. As of last week, the number of cases had gone up to 5,821 — the highest recorded in the province. The PHO reported that 5,505 dengue cases were reported as of September 24. More than 300 cases had been added in a span of three weeks. The figures didn’t include dengue patients admitted in private hospitals since the PHO only had access to public hospitals.“",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/826252/cebu-declares-state-of-calamity-over-5000-dengue-cases",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,4,'GPE'),(5,9,'LOC_TYPE'),(23,31,'LOC_TYPE'),(35,39,'GPE'),(55,72,'STATE'),(84,90,'CHANGE'),(91,96,'CASE'),(100,106,'DISEASE'),(128,133,'CARDINAL'),(134,139,'CASE'),(150,167,'DATE'),(228,249,'ORG'),(290,316,'ORG'),(404,419,'STATE'),(499,505,'DISEASE'),(599,607,'CHANGE'),(611,617,'DISEASE'),(618,623,'CASE'),(631,639,'LOC_TYPE'),(671,688,'STATE'),(703,711,'LOC_TYPE'),(736,797,'ORG'),(835,865,'ORG'),(902,910,'CHANGE'),(914,920,'DISEASE'),(921,926,'CASE'),(932,962,'DATE'),(991,1000,'DATE'),(1008,1017,'DATE'),(1023,1029,'CASE'),(1033,1038,'CASE'),(1048,1050,'CHANGE'),(1054,1059,'CARDINAL'),(1090,1098,'LOC_TYPE'),(1104,1107,'ORG'),(1122,1127,'CASE'),(1128,1134,'DISEASE'),(1135,1140,'CASE'),(1161,1173,'DATE'),(1185,1188,'CARDINAL'),(1189,1194,'CASE'),(1223,1234,'DATE'),(1263,1269,'DISEASE'),(1291,1308,'ORG'),(1319,1322,'ORG'),(1342,1358,'ORG')]"
},
{
    "title": "‘Typhoid’ kills 2 in Pinamungajan town",
    "timestamp": "February 25, 2015",
    "content": "TWO people died of suspected typhoid fever in barangay Camugao, Pinamungajan town, midwestern Cebu last week, the town’s municipal health office said yesterday. Municipal health officer Dr. Sheila Faciol identified the victims as Marivic Macalipay, 16 and Eduardo Caniban, 27, both residents of barangay Camugao. She said the water reservoir was contaminated with fecal coliform caused by residents washing their laundry near the area. Dr. Faciol said they recorded 10 to 15 cases of suspected typhoid fever. But she said only the Department of Health (DOH) can declare an outbreak. “We gave the the households chlorine and chlorine tablets to make the water safe for consumption,” Dr. Faciol said. Faciol said Macalipay and Caniban, both relatives, suffered fever for more than a month. Macalipay died at the Vicente Sotto Memorial Medical Center (VSMMC) while Caniban died at the Pinamungajan District Hospital. Dr. Faciol said Caniban ignored the doctor’s order to stay at the hospital in favor of staying at home, resulting in his death. She said they’re monitoring another patient from the same area who has been confined in a private hospital in Cebu City with typhoid fever symptoms. Typhoid fever is caused by consumption of contaminated food and water or through close contact with someone infected by typhoid. Signs and symptoms include sustained high fever, headache, malaise (weakness), anorexia (loss of appetite), either diarrhea or constipation and abdominal discomfort. Treatment includes antiobiotics such as ciprofloxacin for adults and cetriaxone (injectable antibiotic) for pregnant women and children. People are advised to boil water first before drinking and cooking food well and covering them to prevent contamination from flies. They should also wash their hands with soap and water after using the toilet and before eating.",
    "url": "http://cebudailynews.inquirer.net/51941/typhoid-kills-2-in-pinamungajan-town",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0,3,'CARDINAL'),(29,42,'DISEASE'),(46,54,'LOC_TYPE'),(55,98,'GPE'),(99,108,'DATE'),(121,144,'ORG'),(150,159,'DATE'),(249,251,'CARDINAL'),(273,275,'CARDINAL'),(295,303,'LOC_TYPE'),(304,311,'GPE'),(466,474,'CARDINAL'),(475,480,'CASE'),(494,507,'DISEASE'),(531,557,'ORG'),(573,581,'STATE'),(769,786,'DATE'),(788,797,'GPE'),(810,855,'ORG'),(882,912,'ORG'),(1100,1104,'LOC_TYPE'),(1132,1148,'ORG'),(1152,1161,'GPE'),(1167,1180,'DISEASE'),(1191,1204,'DISEASE'),(1311,1318,'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH verifying reports of typhoid fever epidemic",
    "timestamp": "March 3, 2015",
    "content": "The Department of Health (DOH-7) recorded 47 suspected cases and seven confirmed cases of typhoid fever in barangay Camugao, Pinamungajan town in northern Cebu. “It’s not an outbreak but it is an epidemic. Based on our review, the area has not experienced typhoid cases beyond the usual number for the past five years,” said Reynan Cimafranca, head of the Regional Epidemiological and Surveillance Unit (RESU-7). He said they are monitoring an 11-year-old girl who has been confined in a private hospital in Cebu City. The girl is the younger sister of 16-year-old Marivic Macalipay, the first barangay Camugao resident to die of typhoid fever. “She has been suffering peritonitis or accumulation of fluids in her intestine. She needs exploratory laporatomy to remove the fluids. Her condition is serious,” he told reporters. Her father tested positive of the same illness and has been given medications, Cimafranca said. There are two other children referred to hospitals in Cebu City for confinement. Aside from Macalipay, also testing positive for typhoid were the one-year-old daughter and three-year-old son of 27-year-old Eduardo Caniban, the second casualty from typhoid fever. Their neighbor tested positive of typhoid and received medication, Cimafranca said. He added one of the barangay’s water sources had been treated last week while two others remain untreated. Last week, Pinamungajan health officer Dr. Sheila Faciol confirmed the presence of garbage like soiled diapers near the water source. They also directed barangay officials to remove the garbage. Cimafranca said the water source should be fenced to prevent animals from reaching the water source. Typhoid fever is an infectious disease caused by the salmonella typhi bacteria. It spreads and contaminates food and water or through close contact with an infected person. Signs and symptoms include sustained high fever, headache, malaise (weakness), anorexia (loss of appetite) either diarrhea or constipation and abdominal discomfort. Treatment consists of antibiotics such as ciprofloxacin for adults and Cetriaxone (injectable antibiotic) may be administered to children andpregnant women.",
    "url": "http://cebudailynews.inquirer.net/52215/doh-verifying-reports-of-typhoid-fever-epidemic",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(4,33,'ORG'),(42,44,'CARDINAL'),(55,60,'CASE'),(65,70,'CARDNAL'),(81,86,'CASE'),(90,103,'DISEASE'),(107,115,'LOC_TYPE'),(116,159,'GPE'),(174,182,'STATE'),(196,204,'STATE'),(256,263,'DISEASE'),(264,269,'CASE'),(287,293,'CASE'),(302,317,'DATE'),(356,411,'ORG'),(508,517,'GPE'),(594,602,'LOC_TYPE'),(603,609,'GPE'),(630,644,'DISEASE'),(932,935,'CARDINAL'),(976,985,'GPE'),(1051,1058,'DISEASE'),(1170,1183,'DISEASE'),(1219,1226,'DISEASE'),(1289,1313,'LOC_TYPE'),(1331,1340,'DATE'),(1347,1350,'CARDINAL'),(1376,1385,'DATE'),(1496,1508,'LOC_TYPE'),(1529,1537,'LOC_TYPE'),(1591,1603,'LOC_TYPE'),(1658,1670,'LOC_TYPE'),(1672,1685,'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Typhoid cases in Cebu contained",
    "timestamp": "April 19, 2015",
    "content": "There are more cases of typhoid fever in Central Visayas this year compared to the first quarter of last year, said Regional Epidemiology Surveillance Unit (RESU)-7 head Renan Cimafranca. However, no new cases were reported in Cebu after April 11, a welcome development for the province which recorded 20 cases in barangay Subayon, Toledo City early this year. As of April 11, the health department recorded 219 cases and two deaths in the region due to typhoid fever while there were only 162 in the same period in 2014.",
    "url": "http://cebudailynews.inquirer.net/55025/typhoid-cases-in-cebu-contained",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(15,20,'CASE'),(24,37,'DISEASE'),(41,56,'GPE'),(57,66,'DATE'),(83,109,'DATE'),(116,164,'ORG'),(204,209,'CASE'),(227,231,'GPE'),(238,246,'DATE'),(278,286,'LOC_TYPE'),(302,304,'CARDINAL'),(305,310,'CASE'),(314,322,'LOC_TYPE'),(323,343,'GPE'),(344,359,'DATE'),(367,375,'DATE'),(408,411,'CARDINAL'),(412,417,'CASE'),(422,425,'CARDINAL'),(454,467,'DISEASE'),(490,493,'CARDINAL'),(516,520,'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Three suspected typhoid cases in Malabuyoc town",
    "timestamp": "March 14, 2012",
    "content": "AFTER the outbreak in Tuburan, the Integrated Provincial Health Office (IPHO) admitted there are three suspected typhoid fever cases in Malabuyoc District Hospital. Dr. Cristina Giango, IPHO head, said the patients showed signs and symptoms of typhoid fever. She  asked the Rural Health Unit (RHU) in the town to check where these patients came from to determine if there are other similar cases in the area. But Giango said they had yet to confirm if the cases in Alegria town were indeed typhoid fever. At least 11 suspected victims  ages between 5 and 18 and mostly children from barangays Legaspi and Poblacion of Alegria were brought to a local hospital after showing signs of typhoid fever. But Giango said she has not received reports from the municipal health office confirming that these were cases of typhoid fever. In Tuburan, cases have gone down as of yesterday. Giango said that there were only four patients admitted yesterday and 10 were treated at the out-patient department. There are now 46 patients confined in Tuburan District Hospital. Giango confirmed that the blood samples and stool culture taken from at least eight patients admitted at the Tuburan District Hospital yielded positive results of typhoid fever. She advised the residents to be more cautious especially in their drinking water. The typhoid outbreak in Tuburan was considered the worst in Central Visayas after almost a thousand were hospitalized and five died because of the disease.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/161243/%E2%80%98three-suspected-typhoid-cases-in-malabuyoc-town%E2%80%99",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(10,18,'STATE'),(22,29,'GPE'),(35,77,'ORG'),(97,102,'CARDINAL'),(113,126,'DISEASE'),(127,132,'CASES'),(136,145,'GPE'),(186,190,'ORG'),(244,257,'DISEASE'),(274,297,'ORG'),(305,309,'LOC_TYPE'),(390,395,'CASE'),(456,461,'CASE'),(465,477,'GPE'),(490,503,'DISEASE'),(514,516,'CARDINAL'),(583,592,'LOC_TYPE'),(593,625,'GPE'),(682,695,'DISEASE'),(802,807,'CASE'),(811,824,'DISEASE'),(829,836,'GPE'),(838,843,'CASE'),(854,858,'CHANGE'),(865,874,'DATE'),(909,913,'CARDINAL'),(932,941,'DATE'),(946,948,'CARDINAL'),(1007,1009,'CARDINAL'),(1031,1038,'GPE'),(1136,1141,'CARDINAL'),(1167,1174,'GPE'),(1221,1234,'DISEASE'),(1322,1329,'DISEASE'),(1330,1338,'STATE'),(1342,1349,'GPE'),(1378,1393,'GPE'),(1407,1417,'CARDINAL'),(1440,1444,'CARDINAL')]"
}
]