[
{
    "title": "Dengue cases increase in 4 Cordillera provinces",
    "timestamp": "July 21, 2015",
    "content": "Baguio City (CNN Philippines) — Dengue cases continue to rise in the Cordillera Region after monsoon rains have battered the region for the past two weeks, creating more breeding sites for mosquitoes. Department of Health (DOH) Program Coordinator for Dengue Dr. Alexei Marrero says as of July 13 the region posted a 48 percent increase in dengue cases, mainly in the provinces of Abra, Apayao, Benguet and Mountain Province. Marrero says their concentration now is in Mountain Province where there is a 500 percent increase in dengue cases, particularly in the town of Paracelis. He added that areas with posted unprecedented number of increased cases were already allowed to conduct misting or fogging operations to eliminate dengue-carrying mosquitoes. The DOH regional office is now concentrating on fogging operations in the towns of Paracelis in Mt. Province and Luba in Abra due to high cases of dengue. This year, the region has recorded two deaths, one involving an 85-year-old man from San Jose, Luna, Apayao and a seven-year-old child from Rosario, La Union who was treated at the Baguio General Hospital. Aside from fogging activities, Marrero stressed it is important to conduct clean-up activities or search and destroy activities, stressing that dengue cases are prevalent during the rainy season because dengue mosquitoes tend to breed on wet places. “The public should always keep their surroundings dry. If there’s stagnant water, drain it. Using mosquito repellent is also helpful. Most of all, clean house and workplace can prevent dengue from breeding,” Marrero stressed. The DOH has been implementing its Vector Surveillance Project to identify barangays with a high population of dengue-carrying mosquitoes to distribute ovicidal-larvicidal traps to prevent further spreading of the disease.",
    "url": "http://cnnphilippines.com/regional/2015/07/21/dengue-cases-increase-4-cordillera-provinces.html",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,11,'GPE'),(13,28,'ORG'),(32,38,'DISEASE'),(39,44,'CASE'),(69,86,'GPE'),(125,131,'LOC_TYPE'),(140,154,'DATE'),(201,221,'ORG'),(223,226,'ORG'),(252,258,'DISEASE'),(289,296,'DATE'),(301,307,'LOC_TYPE'),(317,327,'PERCENT'),(328,336,'CHANGE'),(340,346,'DISEASE'),(347,352,'CASE'),(368,377,'LOC_TYPE'),(381,385,'GPE'),(387,393,'GPE'),(395,402,'GPE'),(407,424,'GPE'),(469,486,'GPE'),(504,515,'PERCENT'),(516,524,'INCREASE'),(528,534,'DISEASE'),(535,540,'CASE'),(570,579,'GPE'),(595,600,'LOC_TYPE'),(627,633,'CASE'),(637,645,'INCREASE'),(647,652,'CASE'),(728,734,'DISEASE'),(760,763,'ORG'),(764,770,'LOC_TYPE'),(839,848,'GPE'),(852,864,'GPE'),(869,873,'GPE'),(877,881,'GPE'),(894,899,'CASE'),(903,909,'DISEASE'),(911,920,'DATE'),(926,932,'LOC_TYPE'),(946,949,'CARDINAL'),(958,961,'CARDINAL'),(996,1004,'GPE'),(1006,1010,'GPE'),(1012,1018,'GPE'),(1051,1068,'GPE'),(1261,1267,'DISEASE'),(1268,1273,'CASE'),(1320,1326,'DISEASE'),(1552,1558,'DISEASE'),(1597,1600,'ORG'),(1667,1676,'LOC_TYPE'),(1703,1709,'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases rise in several provinces",
    "timestamp": "July 15, 2015",
    "content": "Metro Manila (CNN Philippines) — The number of dengue cases continue to increase in some provinces in the country. The City Health Office (CHO) in Zamboanga said that there are already 71 dengue cases in the city for the first week of July, based on the partial report submitted by health personnel from data submitted by hospitals in the area. CHO Officer Dr. Rodel Agbulos said the figure could easily reach 200 once the data from five other hospitals come in. Meanwhile in Sagbayan, Bohol, around 20 dengue cases have been recorded in just the first 10 days of this month. Marilou Tampos, public health nurse of the Rural Health Unit (RHU) of the municipality of Sagbayan, said that there have been 17 cases as of July 4 and three more were added yesterday (July 13). Most of the dengue patients were from Barangay Poblacion, Sagbayan, added the RHU. In Bacolod City, a total of 55 cases of dengue and other waterborne diseases from January to July 2015 were recorded by the CHO. The numbers are expected to increase until next year, according to Dr. Grace Tan, medical officer of Bacolod CHO’s Environmental and Sanitation Division.",
    "url": "http://cnnphilippines.com/regional/2015/07/14/dengue-cases-rise-zamboanga-bacolod-bohol.html",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,12,'GPE'),(37,43,'CASE'),(47,53,'DISEASE'),(54,59,'CASE'),(72,80,'CHANGE'),(89,98,'LOC_TYPE'),(106,113,'LOC_TYPE'),(119,137,'ORG'),(139,142,'ORG'),(147,156,'GPE'),(185,187,'CARDINAL'),(188,194,'DISEASE'),(195,200,'CASE'),(208,212,'LOC_TYPE'),(221,239,'DATE'),(339,343,'LOC_TYPE'),(345,348,'ORG'),(410,413,'CARDINAL'),(433,437,'CARDINAL'),(476,491,'GPE'),(500,502,'CARDINAL'),(503,509,'DISEASE'),(510,515,'CASE'),(547,574,'DATE'),(619,636,'ORG'),(638,641,'ORG'),(650,674,'GPE'),(702,704,'CARDINAL'),(705,710,'CASE'),(717,723,'DATE'),(728,733,'CARDINAL'),(750,769,'DATE'),(783,789,'DISEASE'),(809,827,'GPE'),(829,837,'GPE'),(849,852,'ORG'),(857,869,'GPE'),(882,884,'CARDINAL'),(885,890,'CASE'),(894,900,'DISEASE'),(911,930,'DISEASE'),(936,956,'DATE'),(952,954,'CARDINAL'),(978,981,'ORG'),(987,993,'CASE'),(1011,1019,'CHANGE'),(1026,1035,'DATE'),(1084,1091,'GPE'),(1092,1095,'ORG')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases rise in 3 Cordillera provinces, Baguio City",
    "timestamp": "July 1, 2015",
    "content": "Baguio City (CNN Philippines) — With the onset of the rainy season, the Department of Health-Cordillera regional office here encouraged the public to eliminate breeding of sites of dengue-carrying mosquitoes as three provinces and one city in the region saw increasing cases of dengue. Dr. Amelita Pangilinan, regional director of DOH-CAR, reported an increase of dengue in the provinces of Abra, Apayao, and Mountain Province and in Baguio City. Reports from the DOH-CAR Regional Epidemiological Surveillance Unit showed a 101-percent increase of dengue cases in Abra, 77-percent increase in Apayao, 90-percent increase in Mountain Province and 16-percent increase of cases in Baguio City from January to June 26 this year compared to the same period in 2014. From 80 cases recorded last year the number of dengue patients in Abra province rose to 161 for the first six months of the year. In Apayao, from 47 cases recorded last year it increased to 83 cases this year and in Mountain Province, Debgue cases rose from 22 cases recorded last year to 42 cases this year. In Baguio City, from 83 cases recorded last year it rose to 96 cases this year. Meantime, the provinces of Benguet, Ifugao, and Kalinga had a decrease in dengue cases. A lone fatality has been recorded in San Jose, Luna, Apayao last January due to dengue shock syndrome. Pangilinan also reported clustering of cases in several barangays in Baguio City, Abra, Benguet and Mt. province. DOH regional director, who stressed early detection and treatment of dengue cases are important in preventing deaths among the affected population, asked for vigilance from the public in removing breeding sites of aedes aegypti mosquitoes that harbor the disease. She added that the public should not be complacent even if their respective provinces saw a decrease in the numbers of dengue cases since the overall regional data shows the number of cases only dipped by one percent from 722 cases last year to 713 cases this year. She adds majority of those affected by dengue are males with a median age of 16 years old. Meantime, the Baguio City Health Department said they are now conducting massive information drives to control breeding site of aedes mosquitoes. The health office will also distribute treated curtains that prevent entry of mosquitoes in daycare centers and in schools buildings.",
    "url": "http://cnnphilippines.com/regional/2015/07/01/dengue-cases-cordillera-region-baguio-city.html",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,11,'GPE'),(72,119,'ORG'),(211,216,'CARDINAL'),(217,226,'LOC_TYPE'),(231,234,'CARDINAL'),(235,239,'LOC_TYPE'),(247,254,'LOC_TYPE'),(258,268,'CHANGE'),(269,274,'CASE'),(278,284,'DISEASE'),(310,316,'LOC_TYPE'),(331,338,'ORG'),(352,360,'CHANGE'),(364,370,'DISEASE'),(378,387,'LOC_TYPE'),(391,395,'GPE'),(397,403,'GPE'),(409,426,'GPE'),(434,445,'GPE'),(464,471,'ORG'),(472,478,'LOC_TYPE'),(524,535,'PERCENT'),(536,544,'CHANGE'),(548,554,'DISEASE'),(555,560,'CASE'),(564,568,'GPE'),(570,580,'PERCENT'),(581,589,'CHANGE'),(593,599,'GPE'),(601,611,'PERCENT'),(612,620,'CHANGE'),(624,641,'GPE'),(646,656,'PERCENT'),(657,665,'CHANGE'),(669,674,'CASE'),(678,689,'GPE'),(695,723,'DATE'),(714,723,'DATE'),(755,759,'DATE'),(766,768,'CARDINAL'),(769,774,'CASE'),(784,793,'DATE'),(808,814,'DISEASE'),(827,831,'GPE'),(841,845,'CHANGE'),(849,852,'CARDINAL'),(857,889,'DATE'),(894,900,'GPE'),(907,909,'CARDINAL'),(910,915,'CASE'),(925,934,'DATE'),(938,947,'CHANGE'),(951,953,'CARDINAL'),(954,959,'CASE'),(960,969,'DATE'),(977,994,'GPE'),(1003,1008,'CASE'),(1009,1013,'CHANGE'),(1019,1021,'CARDINAL'),(1022,1027,'CASE'),(1037,1046,'DATE'),(1050,1052,'CARDINAL'),(1053,1058,'CASE'),(1059,1068,'DATE'),(1073,1084,'GPE'),(1091,1093,'CARDINAL'),(1094,1099,'CASE'),(1109,1118,'DATE'),(1122,1126,'CHANGE'),(1130,1132,'CARDINAL'),(1177,1184,'GPE'),(1133,1138,'CASE'),(1139,1148,'DATE'),(1164,1173,'LOC_TYPE'),(1186,1192,'GPE'),(1198,1205,'GPE'),(1212,1220,'CHANGE'),(1224,1230,'DISEASE'),(1231,1236,'CASE'),(1241,1244,'CARDINAL'),(1275,1297,'GPE'),(1298,1310,'DATE'),(1318,1324,'DISEASE'),(1380,1385,'CASE'),(1410,1421,'GPE'),(1423,1427,'GPE'),(1429,1436,'GPE'),(1459,1465,'LOC_TYPE'),(1524,1530,'DISEASE'),(1531,1536,'CASE'),(1795,1804,'LOC_TYPE'),(1811,1819,'CHANGE'),(1838,1844,'DISEASE'),(1845,1850,'CASE'),(1903,1908,'CASE'),(1924,1935,'PERCENT'),(1941,1944,'CARDINAL'),(1945,1950,'CASE'),(1951,1960,'DATE'),(1964,1967,'CARDINAL'),(1968,1973,'CASE'),(1974,1983,'DATE'),(2024,2030,'DISEASE'),(2090,2119,'ORG')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases in Pangasinan up",
    "timestamp": "December 04, 2017",
    "content": "THE Provincial Health Office (PHO) reiterated its appeal to Pangasinan residents to ensure that their homes and surroundings are free of stagnant water to prevent spread of dengue, as cases continue to rise in the province. Dr. Anna de Guzman, provincial health officer, said on December 1 that Pangasinan reported 4,472 dengue cases from January 1 up to November 30. This is more than the 3,824 cases registered in the province for the same period last year, she added. Statistics showed there were more cases reported in the province during the rainy month of August than in any other month of the year. Rainy season results in the presence of stagnant water, which is a breeding ground for dengue mosquitoes. De Guzman again called on the residents to clean their homes and surroundings, and get rid of possible sites for mosquitoes to lay their eggs. Since most of the victims are school-age children, the provincial health officer stressed the need for a renewed clean-up drive in schools to destroy the breeding places of dengue-causing mosquitoes. De Guzman said in the case of students, “They can do the extra effort of wearing long sleeves and pants as their protection from mosquito bites.” At home, it is always advisable to sleep under the mosquito net, she added. The PHO also asked the people to watch out for dengue symptoms, such as on and off fever lasting for days, body rashes, weakening of the muscles, and nose and gum bleeding.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/pangasinan/local-news/2017/12/04/dengue-cases-pangasinan-578108",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(4,28,'ORG'),(30,33,'ORG'),(60,70,'GPE'),(173,179,'DISEASE'),(184,189,'CASE'),(190,206,'CHANGE'),(214,222,'LOC_TYPE'),(244,268,'ORG'),(279,289,'DATE'),(295,305,'GPE'),(315,320,'CARDINAL'),(321,327,'DISEASE'),(328,333,'CASE'),(339,366,'DATE'),(390,395,'CARDINAL'),(396,401,'CASE'),(420,428,'LOC_TYPE'),(449,458,'DATE'),(505,510,'CASE'),(527,535,'LOC_TYPE'),(562,568,'DATE'),(693,699,'DISEASE'),(910,934,'ORG'),(1028,1034,'DISEASE'),(1281,1284,'ORG'),(1324,1330,'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Pampanga records decrease in dengue cases",
    "timestamp": "July 18, 2017",
    "content": "CITY OF SAN FERNANDO -- The Provincial Government on Tuesday, July 18, noted the reported decrease in dengue cases in Pampanga and the significant downward trend in the last three years. According to Jolly Garcia, provincial dengue and malaria coordinator, there were 9,980 dengue cases recorded in the province in 2015 and 6,625 cases in 2016. In the two consecutive years, the Provincial Health Office (PHO) recorded 41 deaths due to dengue. As of July this year, dengue cases in the province numbered 2,006 and is expected to be lower from last year's figure. Garcia explained that the declining trend in dengue cases can be attributed to awareness and intervention efforts by all stakeholders concerned. Specifically, the Dengue Task Force (DTF), composed of barangay captain, kagawad on health, school principal, Barangay Health Workers (BHW) and non-government organizations (NGOs) has been tasked to educate the village folks on how to combat the dreaded dengue fever. DTF is also responsible in monitoring dengue cases in their areas and as well as searching for mosquito breeding grounds. Barangay folks, meanwhile, are required to submit breeding sites of kiti-kiti to the Rural Health Unit (RHU) every first Friday of the month, while the remaining Fridays of the month are intended for “search and seek” strategy to defeat dengue. Garcia said community efforts are slowly paying off but the public cannot be complacent as the mosquito-borne disease is painful, debilitating and fatal. With all the support given and the strengthening of forces to curb the dengue problem in the province, he expressed optimism that a 50 percent reduction target can be reached.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/pampanga/local-news/2017/07/18/pampanga-records-decrease-dengue-cases-553681",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,20,'GPE'),(53,69,'DATE'),(90,98,'CHANGE'),(102,108,'DISEASE'),(109,114,'CASE'),(118,126,'GPE'),(147,161,'CHANGE'),(169,185,'DATE'),(225,231,'DISEASE'),(236,243,'DISEASE'),(268,273,'CARDINAL'),(274,280,'DISEASE'),(281,286,'CASE'),(303,311,'LOC_TYPE'),(315,319,'DATE'),(324,329,'CARDINAL'),(330,335,'CASE'),(339,343,'DATE'),(379,403,'ORG'),(405,408,'ORG'),(419,421,'CARDINAL'),(436,442,'DISEASE'),(450,464,'DATE'),(466,472,'DISEASE'),(473,478,'CASE'),(486,494,'LOC_TYPE'),(504,509,'DATE'),(589,604,'CHANGE'),(608,614,'DISEASE'),(615,620,'CASE'),(726,743,'ORG'),(745,748,'ORG'),(818,841,'ORG'),(843,846,'ORG'),(852,880,'ORG'),(962,968,'DISEASE'),(976,979,'ORG'),(1014,1020,'DISEASE'),(1021,1026,'CASE'),(1183,1200,'ORG'),(1201,1206,'ORG'),(1213,1238,'DATE'),(1260,1267,'DATE'),(1335,1341,'DISEASE'),(1568,1574,'DISEASE'),(1590,1598,'LOC_TYPE'),(1629,1639,'PERCENT'),(1640,1649,'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases in Bacolod up by 84.5%",
    "timestamp": "July 15, 2017",
    "content": "DENGUE cases in Bacolod City increased by 84.5 percent from January to July 8 this year compared to the figures for the same period in 2016, records of the City Health Office (CHO) showed. CHO Environment Sanitation Division Head Grace Tan said, on Thursday, July 13, that as of July 8, Bacolod has a total of 535 dengue cases, from only 290 cases in the previous year. Five young children died in the first seven months this year. In January, the fatalities were a 10-year-old boy in Barangay Sum-ag, and five-year-old boy in Barangay Singcang-Airport. In March, an eight-year-old boy in Barangay Granada also died. In May, a two-year-old boy in Barangay 14 and 12-year-old in Barangay Handumanan passed away as well. From January to July in 2016, only two children died due to dengue. Of 535 cases, Barangay Vista Alegre recorded the highest number with 62 cases. Others include Barangay Mansilingan with 52 cases; Barangay Granada, 42; Barangay Handumanan, 36; Barangay Mandalagan, 33; Barangay Villamonte, 31; Barangays Estefania and Banago, 28 each; Barangay Alijis, 27; and Barangay Taculing, 26. Tan said the cases have been increasing since two weeks ago because of the rains and stagnant water. “It’s our advocate now the searching and destroying the breeding grounds of the mosquitoes,” she said. She added they continue the fogging in various areas. Tan also urged the public to always clean the surroundings to destroy the breeding grounds of the mosquitoes.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/bacolod/local-news/2017/07/14/dengue-cases-bacolod-845-552898",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,20,'GPE'),(53,60,'DATE'),(62,69,'DATE'),(90,98,'CHANGE'),(102,108,'DISEASE'),(109,114,'CASE'),(118,124,'GPE'),(147,161,'CHANGE'),(162,185,'DATE'),(225,231,'DISEASE'),(236,243,'DISEASE'),(268,273,'CARDINAL'),(274,280,'DISEASE'),(281,286,'CASE'),(303,311,'LOC_TYPE'),(315,319,'DATE'),(324,329,'CARDINAL'),(339,343,'DATE'),(352,355,'CARDINAL'),(379,403,'ORG'),(405,408,'ORG'),(419,421,'CARDINAL'),(422,428,'DISEASE'),(486,494,'LOC_TYPE'),(330,335,'CASE'),(436,442,'DISEASE'),(450,464,'DATE'),(466,472,'DISEASE'),(473,478,'CASE'),(504,509,'CARDINAL'),(543,552,'DATE'),(589,604,'CHANGE'),(608,614,'DISEASE'),(615,620,'CASE'),(726,743,'ORG'),(745,748,'ORG'),(818,826,'LOC_TYPE'),(843,846,'ORG'),(852,880,'ORG'),(882,886,'ORG'),(962,974,'DISEASE'),(976,979,'ORG'),(1014,1020,'DISEASE'),(1021,1026,'CASE'),(1036,1041,'LOC_TYPE'),(1183,1120,'ORG'),(1202,1205,'ORG'),(1213,1238,'DATE'),(1260,1280,'DATE'),(1335,1341,'DISEASE'),(1438,1460,'DISEASE'),(1568,1574,'DISEASE'),(1590,1598,'LOC_TYPE'), (1629,1639,'PERCENT'),(1640,1649,'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Davao City records 15 dengue deaths since January",
    "timestamp": "May 5, 2017",
    "content": "DAVAO City assistant health officer Dr. Marjorie Culas reported that their office recorded 15 deaths due to dengue since January to May 4, 2017. “Since January 2017 until today, we have 552 cases of dengue, really, there is really a reduction of cases compared with the last year with the same period unfortunately since January we have 15 deaths,“ she said during the I-Speak weekly media forum at the Davao City Hall. Culas underscored that the number of cases is lower compared to same period last year with more or less 2,000 cases from January to May, but the number of cases is alarming. “Based on our investigation on the number of deaths, it is health seeking behavior of the immediate family of the victim. They really ask for consultation too late,“ she said. She asked public to immediately report the case upon the first onset of fever to the nearest health office. Culas said that it is better if the patients get blood test immediately for the doctors to have a basis if the number of platelet count has gone down or not. Culas added that based on what they have encountered most of the households in a community are only active in prevention methods only if there are deaths recorded near them. “Pagwala nay mamatay magrelax napud so dapat dili jud ta magrelax, samtang naay kaso, samtang naa pay virus, dili jud dapat magpapaak og lamok, dili jud ta magkumpiyansa (If there are no deaths, they will relax again. As long as there are cases, and as long as the virus is still there we must make sure that we should not be bitten by mosquitoes, we should always be vigilant),“ she said. She said rapid testing kits for dengue are still available at the health centers. An emergency lane for families of dengue patients is also in place at the “Lingap Para sa Mahirap“ office at Southern Philippines Medical Center.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/davao/local-news/2017/05/05/davao-city-records-15-dengue-deaths-january-540267",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,10,'GPE'),(91,93,'CARDINAL'),(108,114,'DISEASE'),(121,143,'DATE'),(152,164,'DATE'),(171,176,'DATE'),(186,189,'CARDINAL'),(190,195,'CASE'),(199,205,'DISEASE'),(233,243,'CHANGE'),(246,251,'CASE'),(270,279,'DATE'),(321,328,'DATE'),(337,339,'CARDINAL'),(447,453,'CASE'),(457,462,'CASE'),(496,505,'DATE'),(524,529,'CARDINAL'),(530,535,'CASE'),(541,555,'DATE'),(565,571,'CASE'),(575,580,'CASE'),(629,635,'CASE'),(813,817,'CASE'),(989,995,'CASE'),(1449,1454,'CASE'),(1632,1638,'DISEASE'),(1716,1722,'DISEASE'),(1791,1826,'ORG')]"
}
]