[
{
    "title": "Isabela town in state of calamity due to dengue",
    "timestamp": "2015-06-30T13:54:00",
    "content": "ISABELA, Philippines – The rainy season has just started, but the municipality of Luna in Isabela province in the northern Philippines already declared state of calamity after their health office recorded 54 cases of dengue in just the month of June. Dengue is a fever, usually fatal, caused by a bite of Aedes mosquito. It targets the immune system of the body. Dr Claire Francisco, Luna’s health officer, said on Tuesday, June 30, the number of cases reported for the month is “significantly“ higher compared to the numbers reported in the same month in previous years. Although there is no case of death from dengue yet, the increase in the reported cases of the disease prompted the local government unit to declare a state of calamity to be able to release funds for the purchase of medical equipment. Francisco said the purchase of equipment will also be anticipation of more cases during the rainy season. Thirteen out of 19 barangays (villages) in the town were affected, she said. Francisco advised residents to maintain cleanliness and get rid of stagnant waters so dengue-causing mosquitoes would not have places to breed in. In April, the Department of Health (DOH) reported 6.49% increase of dengue cases in the country, citing 19,946 cases in the first quarter of 2015. The number reached 744 in Cagayan Valley, while Calabarzon had the highest with 3,778 and the Autonomous Region of Muslim Mindanao (ARMM) had the lowest with 312. Philhealth subsidizes dengue case confinement with to P31,300 for level 3. The subsidy covers the maximum allowable expense for room, drugs and medicines, and laboratory tests. The health department is expecting the number of dengue cases to peak in the months of July and August.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/97920-luna-isabela-state-of-calamity-dengue",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0, 7, 'GPE'), (9, 20, 'GPE'), (66, 78, 'LOC_TYPE'), (82, 86, 'GPE'), (90, 97, 'GPE'), (98, 106, 'LOC_TYPE'), (123, 134, 'GPE'), (152, 169, 'STATE'), (205, 207, 'CARDINAL'), (208, 213, 'CASE'), (217, 223, 'DISEASE'), (227, 249, 'DATE'), (251, 257, 'DISEASE'), (384, 388, 'GPE'), (415, 431, 'DATE'), (437, 443, 'CASE'), (447, 452, 'CASE'), (466, 475, 'DATE'), (480, 501, 'CHANGE'), (518, 525, 'CASE'), (538, 552, 'DATE'), (556, 570, 'DATE'), (712, 739, 'STATE'), (913, 921, 'CARDINAL'), (929, 931, 'CARDINAL'), (932, 941, 'LOC_TYPE'), (943, 951, 'LOC_TYPE'), (960, 964, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1154, 1159, 'DATE'), (1165, 1185, 'ORG'), (1187, 1190, 'ORG'), (1201, 1206, 'PERCENT'), (1207, 1215, 'CHANGE'), (1219, 1225, 'DISEASE'), (1226, 1231, 'CASE'), (1239, 1246, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1255, 1261, 'CARDINAL'), (1262, 1267, 'CASE'), (1271, 1296, 'DATE'), (1302, 1308, 'CASE'), (1317, 1320, 'CARDINAL'), (1324, 1339, 'GPE'), (1346, 1356, 'GPE'), (1378, 1383, 'CARDINAL'), (1392, 1428, 'GPE'), (1430, 1434, 'GPE'), (1456, 1459, 'CARDINAL'), (1677, 1683, 'CASE'), (1687, 1693, 'DISEASE'), (1694, 1699, 'CASE'), (1711, 1740, 'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue outbreak strikes 1,800 in Iloilo",
    "timestamp": "2013-07-06T17:20:00",
    "content": "ILOILO, Philippines – The number of dengue cases has surged in this Western Visayas province, infecting more than 1,800 people and killing at least 10, a provincial official said Saturday, July 6. The number of people struck down by the mosquito-borne disease in Iloilo this year is already 71% higher than the same period last year, provincial administrator Raul Banias told Agence France-Presse. He added dengue fatalities in the first half of 2013 were already equal to the total deaths for the whole of 2012. The latest outbreak in the province, located around 400 kilometers south of Manila, has caused particular alarm, because it began before the start of rainy season in June, when mosquitoes are less plentiful, he said. He added that the outbreak may be a sign of the changing behavior of mosquitoes and a result of people storing water improperly. Dengue is spread by mosquitoes that breed in stagnant water and usually bite people during daytime. “But the behavior of the mosquitoes has changed. They are no longer biting only during the day. Even at night, they are biting,“ he said. Additionally, many of the 1.6 million people living in the largely-rural province still stockpile water in their homes due to lack of proper plumbing, making it easier for the mosquitoes to breed. Provincial health workers are now being deployed to the hardest-hit areas to inspect homes, searching for any water container where the mosquitoes might breed, Banias said. Residents are also being advised to keep their water containers covered while victims are being given free treatment in government hospitals, he said. Dengue fever is a recurring problem in the Philippines. While the number of incidents this year is slightly lower nationwide, it has been spiking in certain areas such as Iloilo.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/33088-dengue-outbreak-iloilo",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (26, 32, 'CASE'), (36, 42, 'DISEASE'), (43, 48, 'CASE'), (68, 83, 'LOC_TYPE'), (94, 100, 'CASE'), (104, 119, 'CARDINAL'), (131, 135, 'CASE'), (139, 150, 'CARDINAL'), (179, 195, 'DATE'), (201, 207, 'CASE'), (237, 259, 'DISEASE'), (263, 269, 'GPE'), (270, 279, 'DATE'), (291, 294, 'PERCENT'), (295, 301, 'CHANGE'), (307, 332, 'DATE'), (407, 413, 'DISEASE'), (414, 424, 'CASE'), (428, 450, 'DATE'), (464, 469, 'CHANGE'), (483, 489, 'CASE'), (494, 511, 'DATE'), (524, 532, 'STATE'), (536, 548, 'LOC_TYPE'), (748, 756, 'STATE'), (859, 865, 'DISEASE'), (1123, 1134, 'CARDINAL'), (1618, 1624, 'DISEASE'), (1661, 1672, 'GPE'), (1684, 1690, 'CASE'), (1694, 1703, 'CASE'), (1704, 1713, 'DATE'), (1717, 1731, 'CHANGE'), (1732, 1742, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1756, 1763, 'CHANGE'), (1775, 1780, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1789, 1795, 'GPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue in Davao up 300%",
    "timestamp": "2012-09-24T11:08:00",
    "content": "DAVAO CITY, Philippines - A total of 3,096 dengue cases have been recorded here from January to September this year, an increase of more than 300% from last year's data. In 2011, the local health office documented a total of 896 cases during the same period, according to Melody Pabante, pest control officer of the Davao City's health office. Pabante added that the highest number of incidents this year was recorded during the month of August: 1,069 cases. A total of 42 dengue victims from the city have died since January. Clemarie Secuya, a 3rd year Computer Science student in Ateneo de Davao University, suffered from dengue days after school opened in June this year. “I thought it was just an ordinary case of fever due to the weather that time. I tried taking medicines but my temperature kept on rising,” Secuya recalled. She added that after 3 days of high fever, her mother brought her to the hospital. “When I had my blood checked, we discovered that my platelets were already very low because of dengue,“ Secuya narrated. “We tried every treatment available including herbal medicine like tawa-tawa and even durian, which is believed to be an effective treatment,“ said Secuya. Fortunately, the combination of traditional and alternative medicine was effective, she said. The city health office said the local government is trying its best to regularly remind residents to clean their surroundings to keep dengue mosquitoes away. Aside from information campaign, the local government also conducts fogging in different villages in the city. But fogging is a mere stop-gap measure, Pabante added. She said that the health office has also been distributing Olyset-treated curtains and ovicidal larvicidal (OL) traps to address the problem. In partnership with the Department of Education, Pabante said that the local government was successful in setting up OL traps and Olyset curtains in all public schools in the city. “The increase is really alarming. We are hoping that the people would act on this. The efforts of the residents in removing the breeding ground of mosquitoes is the best solution,“ Pabante said.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/12942-dengue-in-davao-up-300",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "(0, 10, 'GPE'), (12, 23, 'GPE'), (37, 42, 'CARDINAL'), (43, 49, 'DISEASE'), (50, 55, 'CASE'), (80, 115, 'DATE'), (120, 128, 'CHANGE'), (132, 146, 'PERCENT'), (152, 163, 'DATE'), (174, 178, 'DATE'), (183, 202, 'ORG'), (225, 228, 'CARDINAL'), (229, 234, 'CASE'), (242, 257, 'DATE'), (316, 326, 'GPE'), (329, 342, 'ORG'), (375, 381, 'CASE'), (385, 394, 'CASE'), (395, 404, 'DATE'), (425, 444, 'DATE'), (446, 451, 'CARDINAL'), (452, 457, 'CASE'), (470, 472, 'CARDINAL'), (473, 479, 'DISEASE'), (480, 487, 'CASE'), (493, 501, 'LOC_TYPE'), (518, 525, 'DATE'), (625, 631, 'DISEASE'), (660, 674, 'DATE'), (1292, 1309, 'ORG'), (1319, 1335, 'ORG'), (1482, 1498, 'ORG'), (1534, 1542, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1550, 1554, 'LOC_TYPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue alarm in Davao region",
    "timestamp": "2012-06-28T19:05:00",
    "content": "DAVAO CITY, Philippines - The Davao region is bracing for an expected increase in dengue cases, which local health officials said already rose by 108% this year. The Department of Health in Region 11 said that they have already documented 3,083 dengue cases from January to June this year, up from only 1,363 cases during the same period last year. “These figures are unimaginably high. And we are all doing our best to address this increase,“ said DOH-11 regional director Dr. Abdullah Dumama. He said that 82% of the 3,083 cases come from Davao while the rest are from neighboring provinces and towns. At least 27 died of dengue in the city, according to the Davao City Health Office. Dumama said the rainy season is likely to worsen the situation. “Yes, an increase is expected during this time of the year. But to experience a 108% [increase] is very alarming. Our teams in the localities were already mobilized to investigate the cases in the hotspot areas,“ Dumama said. Villages have also launched massive clean-up drives in possible breeding areas. Dumama gave assurances the region's blood bank has enough supply. “I think we still have enough blood supply to cater to the present need as long as we will not have an outbreak here,“ Dumama said.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/7711-dengue-up-108-in-davao-region",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (30, 35, 'GPE'), (36, 42, 'LOC_TYPE'), (70, 78, 'CHANGE'), (82, 88, 'DISEASE'), (89, 94, 'CASE'), (138, 142, 'CHANGE'), (146, 150, 'PERCENT'), (151, 160, 'DATE'), (166, 186, 'ORG'), (190, 199, 'GPE'), (239, 244, 'CARDINAL'), (245, 251, 'DISEASE'), (252, 257, 'CASE'), (258, 288, 'DATE'), (290, 292, 'CHANGE'), (298, 308, 'CARDINAL'), (309, 314, 'CASE'), (322, 347, 'DATE'), (508, 511, 'PERCENT'), (519, 524, 'CARDINAL'), (525, 530, 'CASE'), (541, 546, 'GPE'), (583, 592, 'LOC_TYPE'), (597, 602, 'LOC_TYPE'), (604, 615, 'CARDINAL'), (616, 620, 'CASE'), (624, 630, 'DISEASE'), (638, 642, 'LOC_TYPE'), (661, 685, 'ORG'), (757, 768, 'CHANGE'), (788, 809, 'DATE'), (831, 835, 'PERCENT'), (837, 845, 'CHANGE'), (850, 863, 'STATE'), (882, 892, 'LOC_TYPE'), (935, 940, 'CASE'), (948, 961, 'STATE'), (1080, 1090, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1226, 1234, 'STATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue outbreak declared in Tuguegarao",
    "timestamp": "2015-07-10T21:40:00",
    "content": "CAGAYAN, Philippines – A dengue outbreak was declared in Tuguegarao City on Friday, July 10, after the city health office recorded 3 casualties. The 3 casualties – from 3 different villages – were aged 4, 8, and 16, City Health Officer Dr James Guzman told Rappler. Based on the historical data, the previous years' cases are much higher. The city health office only recorded 188 cases since January. But Guzman said the 3 casualties alarmed them enough to declare an outbreak. “It is not normal to have one death in every 60 cases in the history of dengue in Tuguegarao,“ Guzman said. Mayor Jefferson Soriano ordered the city health office to conduct assessment and information drive about the disease. Guzman said they already mobilized barangay health officers and schools to ensure sanitation. He said that two of those who died likely got the disease in their homes because they were not attending school. A few weeks ago, another area in Cagayan Valley – the municipality of Luna in Isabela province – declared a state of calamity after its health office recorded 54 cases of dengue in just the month of June. In the first quarter of 2015, the health department reported 20,000 cases of dengue nationwide. On Friday, Isabela Governor Faustino Dy II declared a non-working holiday so residents could participate in an anti-dengue cleanup drive and bloodletting activities. As of July 2, the provincial health office recorded about 748 cases of dengue in the province since January, with 2 deaths in Santiago City. “The rise in dengue fever cases necessitates public support to sustain the supply of blood reserves in government hospitals to meet the needs of critical dengue patients who undergo immediate blood transfusion,“ Dy said. Free blood testing services were offered at 4 government hospitals across the province: the Governor Faustino N. Dy Sr Memorial Hospital in Ilagan City, the Southern Isabela General Hospital in Santiago City, Manuel A. Roxas District Hospital in Roxas town, and Echague District Hospital in Echague town.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/98986-dengue-outbreak-tuguegarao-cagayan",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0, 7, 'GPE'), (9, 20, 'GPE'), (25, 31, 'DISEASE'), (32, 40, 'STATE'), (57, 72, 'GPE'), (76, 91, 'DATE'), (131, 132, 'CARDINAL'), (133, 143, 'CASE'), (149, 150, 'CARDINAL'),  (151, 161, 'CASE'), (169, 170, 'CARDINAL'), (181, 189, 'LOC_TYPE'), (300, 314, 'DATE'), (316, 321, 'CASE'), (331, 337, 'CHANGE'), (343, 361, 'ORG'), (376, 379, 'CARDINAL'), (380, 385, 'CASE'), (392, 399, 'DATE'), (421, 422, 'CARDINAL'), (423, 433, 'CASE'), (468, 476, 'STATE'), (504, 507, 'CARDINAL'), (508, 513, 'CASE'), (523, 525, 'CARDINAL'), (526, 531, 'CASE'), (550, 556, 'DISEASE'), (560, 570, 'GPE'), (811, 814, 'CARDINAL'), (911, 926, 'DATE'), (936, 940, 'LOC_TYPE'), (944, 958, 'GPE'), (965, 977, 'LOC_TYPE'), (981, 985, 'GPE'), (989, 996, 'GPE'), (997, 1005, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1019, 1036, 'STATE'), (1070, 1072, 'CARDINAL'), (1073, 1078, 'CASE'), (1082, 1088, 'DISEASE'), (1097, 1114, 'DATE'), (1119, 1144, 'DATE'), (1150, 1167, 'ORG'), (1177, 1183, 'CARDINAL'), (1184, 1189, 'CASE'), (1193, 1199, 'DISEASE'), (1200, 1210, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1215, 1221, 'DATE'), (1223, 1230, 'GPE'), (1384, 1390, 'DATE'), (1396, 1420, 'ORG'), (1436, 1439, 'CARDINAL'), (1440, 1445, 'CASE'), (1449, 1455, 'DISEASE'), (1463, 1471, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1478, 1485, 'DATE'), (1492, 1493, 'CARDINAL'), (1494, 1500, 'CASE'), (1504, 1517, 'GPE'), (1532, 1538, 'DISEASE'), (1539, 1544, 'DISEASE'), (1545, 1550, 'CASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH: 372 deaths due to dengue since January",
    "timestamp": "2016-08-17T12:20:00",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines – The Department of Health (DOH) said on Tuesday, August 16, that it has recorded a total of 84,085 suspected dengue cases in the country from January 1 to August 6, 2016. This is 15.8% higher compared to the same period in 2015 (72,627), and out of this number, 372 people died. Dengue is a disease common in tropical and sub-tropical countries in the world. It is transmitted through the bite of an Aedes mosquito, according to the World Health Organization. The Philippines is one of 4 countries in the Western Pacific which reported the highest dengue incidence in recent years. According to the health department, most of the dengue cases in the country were from Calabarzon (11.2%), Central Visayas (9.5%), Northern Mindanao (9.3%), Western Visayas and Soccsksargen (8.9%), and Central Luzon (8.5%) There were 585 laboratory-confirmed dengue cases in the country. Dengue fever is potentially fatal and mainly affects children. Among the hundreds who died, for instance, the age group with the highest case fatality rate is composed of children who are less than one year old. Central Visayas has so far the highest number of deaths this year, with 65 recorded deaths as of August 6. The DOH has already identified around 80 barangays (villages) in the country as dengue clusters or “hot zones.“ These are areas that reported 3 or more dengue cases for the past 4 straight weeks. Health Spokesperson Eric Tayag earlier said if the cases in a cluster continue to rise, it could indicate a possible dengue outbreak in that barangay, especially if deaths were reported in the area.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/143318-doh-philippines-dengue-updates-january-august-2016",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (26, 46, 'ORG'), (48, 51, 'ORG'), (61, 68, 'DATE'), (113, 119, 'CARDINAL'), (130, 136, 'DISEASE'), (137, 142, 'CASE'), (146, 157, 'LOC_TYPE'), (158, 190, 'DATE'), (200, 205, 'PERCENT'), (206, 212, 'CHANGE'), (225, 248, 'DATE'), (250, 256, 'CARDINAL'), (283, 286, 'CARDINAL'), (294, 298, 'CASE'), (300, 306, 'DISEASE'), (454, 479, 'ORG'), (485, 496, 'GPE'), (620, 637, 'ORG'), (651, 657, 'DISEASE'), (658, 663, 'CASE'), (667, 678, 'LOC_TYPE'), (689, 699, 'GPE'), (701, 706, 'PERCENT'), (709, 724, 'GPE'), (726, 730, 'PERCENT'), (733, 750, 'GPE'), (753, 757, 'PERCENT'), (759, 774, 'GPE'), (779, 791, 'GPE'), (793, 797, 'PERCENT'), (804, 817, 'GPE'), (819, 823, 'PERCENT'), (836, 839, 'CARDINAL'), (861, 867, 'DISEASE'), (868, 873, 'CASE'), (878, 888, 'LOC_TYPE'), (890, 896, 'DISEASE'), (897, 902, 'CASE'), (1102, 1117, 'GPE'), (1141, 1147, 'CASE'), (1151, 1157, 'CASE'), (1158, 1167, 'DATE'), (1174, 1176, 'CARDINAL'), (1186, 1192, 'CASE'), (1199, 1207, 'DATE'), (1213, 1216, 'ORG'), (1247, 1249, 'CARDINAL'), (1250, 1259, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1261, 1269, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1274, 1285, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1289, 1295, 'DISEASE'), (1309, 1318, 'STATE'), (1331, 1335, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1351, 1360, 'CARDINAL'), (1361, 1367, 'DISEASE'), (1368, 1375, 'CASE'), (1522, 1528, 'DISEASE'), (1529, 1537, 'STATE'), (1547, 1554, 'LOC_TYPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "PH 'exported' measles to other countries",
    "timestamp": "4:30 PM, September 18, 2014",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines – The Philippines’ 2014 measles outbreak – the worst since 2010 – has “exported” the highly contagious disease to other countries, a Department of Health (DOH) official said on Wednesday, August 27. “Philippines became the amplifier of measles infection to other countries. Nage-export na tayo ng (We already export) measle cases, importations to other countries like US, Japan, Australia, Singapore,” Dulce Elfa of the health department’s Family Health Office said at a seminar. For 2014 alone, the DOH already recorded 6,287 laboratory-confirmed cases of measles. Elfa said the top 3 regions with the most measle cases are the National Capital Region, Calabarzon and Central Luzon. Most of the cases are unvaccinated children under two years of age. Measles is a viral, highly-contagious respiratory disease. Infected persons exhibit symptoms such as high fever, red eyes, runny nose, and cough. Rashes appear throughout the body after two days. The illness can be spread through cough or direct contact with body secretions of an infected person. A person with measles can pass the disease on to 18 other people. Factors Elfa enumerated 6 main reasons for the outbreak: Variation in subnational coverage for the 1st dose measles vaccination Slow uptake for the MCV2 Large birth cohort of 2.7 million leads to quick accumulation of susceptibles and densely populated in many areas Immunization coverage in 2011 campaign was not high and uniform from area to area Series of major disasters from December 2012 to end of 2013 affected some regions, with significant damage to general infrastructure, health facilities, staff capacities and service implementation Widespread domestic population movements further aggravated by disasters Data from the National Epidemiology Center showed that in 2013, there was a large drop in the percentage of children who completed their two vaccines for protection from measles. From the 91% of children who were administered their first vaccine, only 55% came back for their second vaccine. (READ: DOH: Measles upsurge due to kids missing free vaccination) The health department prescribes that children should get their first measles vaccine at 9 to 11 months old, and their booster shot at 15 months old. As Health Assistant Secretary Eric Tayag earlier said, the first vaccine is 90% effective, while the booster is 100% effective. As of July 5, the country’s measles incidence rate is at 162 people for every population of 1 million. There are also 16,214 confirmed cases of measles, which include both laboratory-confirmed cases and epidemiologically-linked ones. “Halos lahat ng regions may outbreak na ng measles (Almost all regions already have an outbreak),” Elfa noted. Health Secretary Enrique Ona earlier explained that a measles outbreak means “there have been cases of a disease – either suspected or confirmed – in a community or a locality where in the past there was none.“ There is also a high number of confirmed cases among children below 9 months old who are not yet eligible for vaccination. DOH is set to conduct a month-long nationwide vaccination in September to interrupt the transmission of measles and rubella, and to protect Filipinos from the consequences of importation of wild poliovirus. The department’s strategy will be to reach every purok (area) and achieve over 95% coverage. Health service delivery will also be re-established in disaster-hit areas. “Before the year ends sana makita natin drop [in] cases (Before the year ends we hope to see a drop [in] cases),“ Elfa said.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/67427-doh-measles-mass-immunization",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (26, 37, 'GPE'), (39, 43, 'DATE'), (504, 508, 'DATE'), (79, 83, 'DATE'), (1428, 1432, 'DATE'), (1540, 1544, 'DATE'), (1813, 1817, 'DATE'), (2397, 2403, 'DATE'), (197, 217, 'DATE'), (952, 966, 'DATE'), (1511, 1544, 'DATE'), (3131, 3140, 'DATE'), (3094, 3104, 'DATE'), (3446, 3466, 'DATE'), (153, 179, 'ORG'), (440, 457, 'ORG'), (2117, 2134, 'ORG'), (520, 523, 'ORG'), (2054, 2057, 'ORG'), (3070, 3073, 'ORG'), (140, 149, 'LOC_TYPE'), (283, 292, 'LOC_TYPE'), (373, 382, 'LOC_TYPE'), (220, 231, 'GPE'), (3502, 3522, 'DATE'), (649, 672, 'GPE'), (674, 684, 'GPE'), (689, 702, 'GPE'), (1769, 1797, 'ORG'), (2409, 2416, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2641, 2648, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1943, 1946, 'PERCENT'), (2007, 2010, 'PERCENT'), (2339, 2342, 'PERCENT'), (2375, 2379, 'PERCENT'), (3356, 3359, 'PERCENT'), (541, 546, 'CARDINAL'), (754, 757, 'CARDINAL'), (1892, 1895, 'CARDINAL'), (604, 605, 'CARDINAL'), (1119, 1121, 'CARDINAL'), (541, 542, 'CARDINAL'), (1311, 1322, 'CARDINAL'), (2202, 2203, 'CARDINAL'), (2207, 2209, 'CARDINAL'), (2248, 2250, 'CARDINAL'), (2448, 2451, 'CARDINAL'), (2483, 2492, 'CARDINAL'), (2509, 2515, 'CASE'), (3015, 3016, 'CARDINAL'), (52, 60, 'STATE'), (1183, 1191, 'STATE'), (2712, 2720, 'STATE'), (2798, 2806, 'STATE'), (44, 51, 'DISEASE'), (256, 263, 'DISEASE'), (577, 584, 'DISEASE'), (772, 779, 'DISEASE'), (1084, 1091, 'DISEASE'), (1244, 1251, 'DISEASE'), (1925, 1932, 'DISEASE'), (2059, 2066, 'DISEASE'), (2183, 2190, 'DISEASE'), (2419, 2426, 'DISEASE'), (2535, 2542, 'DISEASE'), (2668, 2675, 'DISEASE'), (2790, 2797, 'DISEASE'), (3174, 3181, 'DISEASE'), (337, 343, 'DISEASE'), (628, 634, 'DISEASE'), (1084, 1090, 'DISEASE'), (2183, 2189, 'DISEASE'), (344, 349, 'CASE'), (568, 573, 'CASE'), (635, 640, 'CASE'), (716, 721, 'CASE'), (2526, 2531, 'CASE'), (2584, 2589, 'CASE'), (2830, 2835, 'CASE'), (2988, 2993, 'CASE'), (3495, 3500, 'CASE'), (3550, 3555, 'CASE'), (3186, 3193, 'DISEASE'), (3265, 3275, 'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH steps up drive vs measles amid outbreak",
    "timestamp": "8:52 PM, January 05, 2014",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines – The Department of Health (DOH) is stepping up its campaign against tigdas or measles, following the increase in the number of cases recorded last year and outbreak in some barangays in Metro Manila. The DOH reported that there were 1,724 cases of measles nationwide from January 1 to December 14, 2013, with 43% or 744 cases recorded in Metro Manila alone. Some 21 barangays in 9 cities have declared an outbreak in their areas, according to state-run Philippine News Agency. These barangays include: Caloocan City: Bagong Barrio and Dagat-dagatan Las Piñas City: Pamplona Uno, Talon Dos, and Talon Singko Malabon City: Longos and Tonsuya Manila: Binondo, Quiapo, Port Area, Sampaloc, Sta. Cruz, Sta. Mesa, and Tondo Muntinlupa City: Alabang and Putatan Navotas: North Bay Boulevard South Parañaque City: Don Bosco and Moonwalk Taguig City: Bagong Tanyag Valenzuela City: Ugong Measles is a viral, highly-contagious respiratory disease. Infected persons exhibit symptoms such as high fever, red eyes, runny nose and cough. Rashes would then appear throughout the body after two days. The illness can be spread through cough or direct contact with body secretions of an infected person. Free vaccination DOH Assistant Secretary Eric Tayag, on his Twitter account, reminded Filipinos that vaccination is free in all health centers nationwide. Tayag noted that children who missed their measles vaccine shot 5 years ago are more vulnerable to measles now and in the coming days. As a precautionary measure, Tayag told parents to have their children immunized, saying that babies aged 6 to 11 months should take their first vaccine shot, while they should be vaccinated the second time when they are 12 to 18 months old. He also advised students who exhibit symptoms of measles to stay home and not go to school on Monday, January 6. The DOH will meet with health officers in Metro Manila and civil society organizations on Monday to step up its vaccination drive, said Tayag.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/47268-doh-measles-outbreak",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (207, 219, 'GPE'), (359, 371, 'GPE'), (1900, 1906, 'GPE'), (661, 667, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (523, 536, 'GPE'), (538, 551, 'GPE'), (556, 569, 'GPE'), (570, 584, 'GPE'), (586, 598, 'GPE'), (600, 609, 'GPE'), (615, 627, 'GPE'), (628, 640, 'GPE'), (642, 648, 'GPE'), (653, 660, 'GPE'), (669, 676, 'GPE'), (678, 684, 'GPE'), (686, 695, 'GPE'), (697, 705, 'GPE'), (707, 716, 'GPE'), (718, 727, 'GPE'), (733, 738, 'GPE'), (739, 754, 'GPE'), (756, 763, 'GPE'), (768, 775, 'GPE'), (776, 783, 'GPE'), (785, 804, 'GPE'), (805, 825, 'GPE'), (827, 836, 'GPE'), (841, 849, 'GPE'), (850, 861, 'GPE'), (863, 876, 'GPE'), (894, 899, 'GPE'), (26, 52, 'ORG'), (225, 228, 'ORG'), (1225, 1228, 'ORG'), (1856, 1859, 'ORG'), (474, 496, 'ORG'), (402, 408, 'LOC_TYPE'), (194, 203, 'LOC_TYPE'), (387, 396, 'LOC_TYPE'), (504, 513, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1833, 1850, 'DATE'), (1427, 1438, 'DATE'), (163, 172, 'DATE'), (288, 323, 'DATE'), (337, 340, 'CASE'), (148, 153, 'CASE'), (260, 265, 'CASE'), (341, 346, 'CASE'), (254, 259, 'CASE'), (384, 386, 'CARDINAL'), (400, 401, 'CARDINAL'), (1096, 1099, 'CARDINAL'), (1603, 1604, 'CARDINAL'), (1608, 1610, 'CARDINAL'), (1718, 1720, 'CARDINAL'), (1724, 1726, 'CARDINAL'), (330, 333, 'PERCENT'), (89, 95, 'DISEASE'), (99, 106, 'DISEASE'), (269, 276, 'DISEASE'), (900, 907, 'DISEASE'), (1406, 1413, 'DISEASE'), (1462, 1469, 'DISEASE'), (1788, 1795, 'DISEASE'), (177, 185, 'STATE'), (426, 434, 'STATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH: Measles upsurge due to kids missing free vaccination",
    "timestamp": "9:56 PM, January 06, 2014",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines – The recent upsurge of measles cases in certain areas of the country, especially Metro Manila, was due to children missing crucial measles vaccinations at an early age, the health department said on Monday, January 6. The irony is that the vaccines are readily available for free in rural health clinics across the country. Latest figures from government showed that the number of confirmed cases in Metro Manila in 2013 was almost 17 times more than the figure from 2012. Of the 417 cases of measles recorded in the national capital region 2013, Health Secretary Enrique Ona said 88% didn't have any history of vaccination. In a press conference, Ona attributed the increase in measles cases to children missing their preliminary and booster vaccination shots. Babies aged 6 to 11 months should be administered their first vaccine shot. At 12 to 18 months, they should get vaccination a second time. “There are a good number of parents who, for one reason or another, don't get their child vaccinated,“ said Ona. As an example, he cited certain tribes or religious sectors whose members refuse vaccinations. The Department of Health (DOH) was able to vaccinate only 85% of Filipino children during the last nationwide vaccination program in 2011, he said. “As you go in the last 3 years, there were a lot of children who missed the vaccinations, making them suscepticle to measles,“ Ona continued. “The point is, there should have been no more measles in Metro Manila, or even in the whole Philippines, but that has not happened yet. The Philippines is not yet measles-free,“ said Ona. The DOH is slated to conduct another nationwide vaccination drive this year. Extent of the outbreak Ona said that the DOH is aware of the measles outbreak in certain areas of the country, and is closely coordinating with local health officials to address the matter. “Yes, there have been an increase in reports in some areas in Metro Manila. We are aware of it. We are monitoring it very closely,“ said Ona. Ona then clarified to media the definition of an outbreak. “It means that there have been cases of a disease – either suspected or confirmed – in a community or a locality where in the past there was none.“ Even a single case, if it is the first ever in area, is considered an outbreak, he said. There were a total of 1,724 measles cases reported nationwide, from Jan 1 to Dec 14, 2013, with 21 deaths. Latest figures in the National Capital Region (NCR) from the DOH Center for Health Development (CHD) show that there have been 417 confirmed measles cases, including 3 deaths, logged in 2013. In 2012, only 25 cases were reported in NCR. Children between one and 4 years old were affected the most, consisting 38% of the cases. Las Piñas City reported the most number of measles cases with 78, followed by Manila (72), Muntinlupa City (65), Caloocan City (45), and Parañaque City (32). The DOH report also noted that 88% of the measles cases in the NCR in 2013 had no history of previous measles vaccination. Ona said that all cities in Metro Manila have been actively expanding their vaccination drives since September 2013, when most measles cases started rising drastically. “As a matter of fact, in December 2013 in the city of Manila, there was a 28% decrease in suspected measles cases. In Caloocan City, there were no suspected cases in November and December,“ said Ona. “There is no reason to be scared, or to be too concerned. However, it is imperative that the parents take a good look at their children always, so that when symptoms of measles appear, the child should be brought to the hospital or health center,“ Ona added. When asked if adults can also avail themselves of measles vaccines, Ona said that they could, but the children are top priority.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/47329-doh-measles-upsurge-kids-miss-free-vaccination",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(102, 114, 'GPE'), (421, 433, 'GPE'), (1477, 1489, 'GPE'), (1937, 1947, 'GPE'), (3056, 3068, 'GPE'), (3251, 3257, 'GPE'), (0, 6, 'GPE'), (2825, 2831, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (1512, 1523, 'GPE'), (1560, 1571, 'GPE'), (2442, 2471, 'GPE'), (538, 561, 'GPE'), (689, 692, 'GPE'), (2652, 2655, 'GPE'), (2968, 2971, 'GPE'), (2747, 2761, 'GPE'), (2838, 2853, 'GPE'), (2860, 2873, 'GPE'), (3315, 3328, 'GPE'), (2884, 2898, 'GPE'), (44, 51, 'DISEASE'), (152, 159, 'DISEASE'), (514, 521, 'DISEASE'), (700, 707, 'DISEASE'), (1395, 1402, 'DISEASE'), (1466, 1473, 'DISEASE'), (1583, 1590, 'DISEASE'), (1746, 1753, 'DISEASE'), (2341, 2348, 'DISEASE'), (2561, 2568, 'DISEASE'), (2790, 2797, 'DISEASE'), (2947, 2954, 'DISEASE'), (3007, 3014, 'DISEASE'), (3155, 3162, 'DISEASE'), (3297, 3304, 'DISEASE'), (3566, 3573, 'DISEASE'), (3706, 3713, 'DISEASE'), (52, 57, 'CASE'), (412, 417, 'CASE'), (505, 510, 'CASE'), (708, 713, 'CASE'), (2107, 2112, 'CASE'), (2349, 2354, 'CASE'), (2569, 2574, 'CASE'), (2629, 2634, 'CASE'), (2740, 2745, 'CASE'), (2798, 2803, 'CASE'), (3163, 3168, 'CASE'), (3305, 3310, 'CASE'), (3354, 3359, 'CASE'), (501, 504, 'CASE'), (2547, 2550, 'CASE'), (2238, 2242, 'CASE'), (2335, 2340, 'CASE'), (2626, 2628, 'CASE'), (2809, 2811, 'CASE'), (2337, 2339, 'CASE'), (2855, 2857, 'CASE'), (2875, 2877, 'CASE'), (2900, 2902, 'CASE'), (194, 211, 'ORG'), (1134, 1160, 'ORG'), (1612, 1615, 'ORG'), (1726, 1729, 'ORG'), (2481, 2484, 'ORG'), (2909, 2912, 'ORG'), (2481, 2520, 'ORG'), (82, 89, 'LOC_TYPE'), (336, 343, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1787, 1794, 'LOC_TYPE'), (3046, 3052, 'LOC_TYPE'), (220, 237, 'DATE'), (2376, 2402, 'DATE'), (3123, 3143, 'DATE'), (3222, 3235, 'DATE'), (437, 441, 'DATE'), (562, 566, 'DATE'), (2606, 2610, 'DATE'), (2975, 2979, 'DATE'), (488, 492, 'DATE'), (2615, 2619, 'DATE'), (1263, 1267, 'DATE'), (1296, 1308, 'DATE'), (1674, 1683, 'DATE'), (3363, 3371, 'DATE'), (3376, 3384, 'DATE'), (453, 466, 'CHANGE'), (688, 696, 'CHANGE'), (1900, 1908, 'CHANGE'), (3177, 3183, 'CHANGE'), (602, 605, 'PERCENT'), (2936, 2939, 'PERCENT'), (1188, 1191, 'PERCENT'), (2729, 2732, 'PERCENT'), (3271, 3274, 'PERCENT'), (795, 796, 'CARDINAL'), (800, 802, 'CARDINAL'), (862, 864, 'CARDINAL'), (868, 870, 'CARDINAL'), (2409, 2411, 'CARDINAL'), (2586, 2587, 'CARDINAL'), (2674, 2677, 'CARDINAL'), (2682, 2683, 'CARDINAL'), (1699, 1707, 'STATE'), (1754, 1762, 'STATE'), (2066, 2074, 'STATE'), (2294, 2302, 'STATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Did You Know: DOH notes fewer cases of measles-rubella",
    "timestamp": "05:00 AM September 27, 2017",
    "content": "A total of 1,964 suspected cases of measles-rubella were reported nationwide from Jan. 1 to Aug. 5 this year, according to the Department of Health. Of these cases, 28 or 1.43 percent were classified as confirmed measles, while 329 cases or 16.75 percent were classified as rubella (german measles). The measles cases were 41.67 percent lower than the 48 cases during the same period last year, while the rubella cases were 257.61 percent higher than the 92 cases reported the previous year.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/933627/did-you-know-doh-notes-fewer-cases-of-measles-rubella",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(11, 16, 'CASE'), (27, 32, 'CASE'), (158, 163, 'CASE'), (232, 237, 'CASE'), (312, 317, 'CASE'), (355, 360, 'CASE'), (413, 418, 'CASE'), (458, 463, 'CASE'), (165, 167, 'CASE'), (228, 231, 'CASE'), (352, 354, 'CASE'), (455, 457, 'CASE'), (36, 51, 'DISEASE'), (274, 298, 'DISEASE'), (213, 220, 'DISEASE'), (304, 311, 'DISEASE'), (405, 412, 'DISEASE'), (82, 108, 'DATE'), (384, 393, 'DATE'), (477, 490, 'DATE'), (171, 183, 'PERCENT'), (241, 254, 'PERCENT'), (323, 336, 'PERCENT'), (424, 438, 'PERCENT'), (127, 147, 'ORG'), (337, 342, 'CHANGE'), (439, 445, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "21 dead as DOH declares measles outbreak",
    "timestamp": "09:17 PM January 03, 2014",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines—The Department of Health appealed to parents to have their children vaccinated against measles on Friday as it declared an outbreak of the disease in Metro Manila and other parts of the country. Health Assistant Secretary Dr. Eric Tayag, who is also director of the National Epidemiology Center, said that from Jan. 1 to Dec. 14, 2013, there were already 1,724 confirmed measles cases nationwide, 21 of which led to death. He added that among the 17 regions in the country, only four did not report an increase in the number of measles cases. These are Central Visayas, Eastern Visayas, Northern Mindanao and the Caraga region in Mindanao. The National Capital Region had the most number of cases with 744. Measles outbreak had been declared in the following Metro Manila areas: Quiapo, Sampaloc, Tondo, Binondo, Sta. Cruz, Port Area and Sta. Mesa in Manila; Dagat-dagatan and Bagong Barrio, in Caloocan City; Talon 5, Talon 2 and Pamplona Uno in Las Piñas; Longos and Tonsuya in Malabon; Alabang and Putatan in Muntinlupa; North Bay Boulevard South in Navotas; Moonwalk and Don Bosco in Parañaque; Bagong Tanyag in Taguig; and Ugong in Valenzuela. But Tayag noted that mass vaccinations had already been conducted in those places. He said mass vaccinations would also soon be conducted nationwide, preferably during the summer break. He urged parents to bring their children, especially those between the ages of 6 to 18 months, to health centers for free vaccination. Tayag noted that measles is a contagious viral illness, which can be deadly. He said it commonly spreads among children and even adults, but the most susceptible are children 10 years old and below. He said infants and children with measles should be hospitalized. Children 6 to 18 months old must complete the required two vaccinations to prevent them from contracting measles, he said. Newborn children must take the first preventive vaccine shot for measles upon reaching 6 months to 12 months. The second vaccine shot should be taken upon reaching the age of 12 months to 18 months. “These two consecutive shots must be taken to avoid having the risk of getting measles,” he said. He said measles usually begins with common cold symptoms like high fever, cough, runny nose, red eyes that can last for several days before the appearance of a red, blotchy rash. Tayag suggested that parents bring down the fever with paracetamol and sponge bath to prevent the onset of convulsions, and to get rid of the thick discharges from the nose. He also urged parents to count a child’s inhalations, noting a child less than five years old with more than 40 breaths per minute may have pneumonia.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/557253/21-dead-as-doh-declares-measles-outbreak",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(170, 182, 'GPE'), (779, 791, 'GPE'), (0, 6, 'GPE'), (871, 877, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (573, 588, 'GPE'), (590, 605, 'GPE'), (607, 624, 'GPE'), (633, 646, 'GPE'), (616, 624, 'GPE'), (650, 658, 'GPE'), (664, 687, 'GPE'), (799, 805, 'GPE'), (807, 815, 'GPE'), (817, 822, 'GPE'), (824, 831, 'GPE'), (833, 842, 'GPE'), (844, 853, 'GPE'), (858, 867, 'GPE'), (879, 892, 'GPE'), (897, 910, 'GPE'), (915, 928, 'GPE'), (930, 937, 'GPE'), (939, 946, 'GPE'), (951, 963, 'GPE'), (967, 976, 'GPE'), (978, 984, 'GPE'), (989, 996, 'GPE'), (1000, 1007, 'GPE'), (1009, 1016, 'GPE'), (1021, 1028, 'GPE'), (1032, 1042, 'GPE'), (1044, 1069, 'GPE'), (1073, 1080, 'GPE'), (1082, 1090, 'GPE'), (1095, 1104, 'GPE'), (1108, 1117, 'GPE'), (1119, 1132, 'GPE'), (1136, 1142, 'GPE'), (1148, 1153, 'GPE'), (1157, 1167, 'GPE'), (24, 44, 'LOC_TYPE'), (286, 314, 'LOC_TYPE'), (107, 114, 'DISEASE'), (391, 398, 'DISEASE'), (548, 555, 'DISEASE'), (727, 734, 'DISEASE'), (1507, 1514, 'DISEASE'), (1723, 1730, 'DISEASE'), (1860, 1867, 'DISEASE'), (1943, 1950, 'DISEASE'), (2156, 2163, 'DISEASE'), (2183, 2190, 'DISEASE'), (2668, 2677, 'DISEASE'), (143, 151, 'STATE'), (735, 743, 'STATE'), (115, 124, 'DATE'), (326, 354, 'DATE'), (1330, 1353, 'DATE'), (2295, 2307, 'DATE'), (206, 213, 'LOC_TYPE'), (485, 492, 'LOC_TYPE'), (470, 477, 'LOC_TYPE'), (375, 380, 'CASE'), (399, 404, 'CASE'), (556, 561, 'CASE'), (711, 716, 'CASE'), (417, 419, 'CASE'), (722, 725, 'CASE'), (499, 503, 'CARDINAL'), (467, 469, 'CARDINAL'), (1434, 1435, 'CARDINAL'), (1764, 1765, 'CARDINAL'), (1965, 1966, 'CARDINAL'), (1439, 1441, 'CARDINAL'), (1769, 1771, 'CARDINAL'), (2066, 2068, 'CARDINAL'), (1665, 1667, 'CARDINAL'), (1977, 1979, 'CARDINAL'), (2053, 2055, 'CARDINAL'), (1810, 1813, 'CARDINAL'), (2084, 2087, 'CARDINAL'), (2607, 2611, 'CARDINAL'), (2637, 2639, 'CARDINAL'), (522, 530, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "PhilHealth says measles covered by hospitalization benefits",
    "timestamp": "06:36 PM January 14, 2014",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines—The Philippine Health Insurance announced Tuesday that patients hospitalized due to measles may avail themselves of PhilHealth benefits. In a news forum, PhilHealth president and CEO Alexander Padilla said that patients confined even due to simple measles cases are now covered by PhilHealth following the outbreak of the disease in many parts of the country. According to him, measles was previously removed from its list of benefits because there had been almost no hospital admissions due to simple measles. “But those with complications due to measles such as pneumonia, dehydration and encephalitis have been continuously covered by PhilHealth,” he said. “Since there is an outbreak of the disease, we decided to revive this month the simple measles case rate package, but it has to involve hospital confinement,” added PhilHealth spokesperson Dr. Israel Francis Pargas. Pargas said patients will be covered for P7,000 and up to P32,000 if it involves complications from the disease. He added that the coverage will be implemented retroactively, which means those who were admitted even from January 1 to 14 can file for PhilHealth claims. Meanwhile, almost 800 suspected cases of measles have been reported in Metro Manila for the first 11 days of the month, according to the Department of Health. Based on the DOH-National Capital report, there were 760 suspected cases reported from January 1 to 11, 2014 compared with only 10 cases during the same period last year. Most (272) cases were in Manila City, followed by Parañaque City with 138 cases. Other cities with significant increase in cases were Quezon, Taguig, Navotas and Las Piñas. The DOH report said clustering of suspected measles cases has been noted in the cities of Caloocan, Las Piñas, Malabon, Mandaluyong, Manila, Muntinlupa, Navotas, Parañaque, Pasay, Quezon, Taguig, and Valenzuela. Three deaths from suspect measles cases were also reported during the period, the report added. Thirty-nine percent of those affected belonged to the 1-4 years age-group, the DOH report said, adding that 9 percent or 67 victims had history of previous measles vaccination. A total of 1,724 cases of measles have been reported from Jan. 1 to Dec, 14, 2013 nationwide, including 21 deaths. The DOH is to launch in September a nationwide mass vaccination campaign to eliminate measles in the country.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/563837/philhealth-says-measles-covered-by-hospitalization-benefits",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (1236, 1248, 'GPE'), (1520, 1531, 'GPE'), (1801, 1807, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (1545, 1559, 'GPE'), (1629, 1635, 'GPE'), (1848, 1854, 'GPE'), (1637, 1643, 'GPE'), (1856, 1862, 'GPE'), (1645, 1652, 'GPE'), (1821, 1828, 'GPE'), (1657, 1666, 'GPE'), (1768, 1777, 'GPE'), (1758, 1766, 'GPE'), (1779, 1786, 'GPE'), (1788, 1799, 'GPE'), (1809, 1819, 'GPE'), (1645, 1652, 'GPE'), (1821, 1828, 'GPE'), (1545, 1554, 'GPE'), (1830, 1839, 'GPE'), (1841, 1846, 'GPE'), (1868, 1878, 'GPE'), (24, 51, 'ORG'), (136, 146, 'ORG'), (174, 184, 'ORG'), (301, 311, 'ORG'), (658, 668, 'ORG'), (845, 855, 'ORG'), (1146, 1156, 'ORG'), (1302, 1322, 'ORG'), (1337, 1340, 'ORG'), (1672, 1675, 'ORG'), (2055, 2058, 'ORG'), (2272, 2275, 'ORG'), (62, 69, 'DATE'), (745, 755, 'DATE'), (1112, 1132, 'DATE'), (1257, 1283, 'DATE'), (1406, 1432, 'DATE'), (1484, 1493, 'DATE'), (2206, 2234, 'DATE'), (2292, 2301, 'DATE'), (104, 111, 'DISEASE'), (268, 275, 'DISEASE'), (398, 405, 'DISEASE'), (522, 529, 'DISEASE'), (568, 575, 'DISEASE'), (767, 774, 'DISEASE'), (1206, 1213, 'DISEASE'), (1712, 1719, 'DISEASE'), (1906, 1913, 'DISEASE'), (2132, 2139, 'DISEASE'), (2179, 2186, 'DISEASE'), (2354, 2361, 'DISEASE'), (326, 334, 'STATE'), (699, 707, 'STATE'), (371, 378, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2369, 2376, 'LOC_TYPE'), (938, 943, 'CARDINAL'), (955, 961, 'CARDINAL'), (1880, 1885, 'CARDINAL'), (2030, 2033, 'CARDINAL'), (2097, 2099, 'CARDINAL'), (2257, 2259, 'CARDINAL'), (276, 281, 'CASE'), (1197, 1202, 'CASE'), (1391, 1396, 'CASE'), (1455, 1460, 'CASE'), (1506, 1511, 'CASE'), (1569, 1574, 'CASE'), (1618, 1623, 'CASE'), (1720, 1725, 'CASE'), (1914, 1919, 'CASE'), (2170, 2175, 'CASE'), (1183, 1186, 'CASE'), (1377, 1380, 'CASE'), (1452, 1454, 'CASE'), (1501, 1504, 'CASE'), (1565, 1568, 'CASE'), (2164, 2169, 'CASE'), (1976, 1995, 'PERCENT'), (2084, 2093, 'PERCENT')]"
},
{
    "title": "Measles outbreak to peak in summer, says Tayag",
    "timestamp": "02:12 PM January 06, 2014",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines—Health Assistant Secretary Dr. Eric Tayag on Monday said the measles outbreak would continue and peak in the dry season. According to the latest statistics, measles cases reached 1,724 from January 1 to December 14, 2013. Of the number, 21 patients died. “There are outbreaks last year and it is going on right now” Tayag in an interview with Inquirer Radio 990AM. Tayag said the measles outbreak, which started last year, would linger until summer. “That’s when the measles will peak (summer) and we hope we can contain it so we can reduce the number of children getting sick and even adults because measles spread easily because it is airborne.” Tayag, known for his dance moves to campaign for crucial health programs, said the local government units are in charge of the vaccination of children in their areas. The Health Department only supplies the vaccines. “The local government’s primary responsibility is to make sure that the vaccines the Department of Health buys and distributes to them are actually used,” he said. According to Tayag, measles vaccines should be administered twice – first when a child is nine to 11 months old and another when the child is 12-months-old to 18 months-old. He added that if mothers or relatives would not bring the children to the health centers, DOH personnel would come personally to the houses to administer the measles vaccine.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/558743/measles-outbreak-to-peak-in-summer-says-tayag",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(185, 190, 'CASE'), (199, 204, 'CASE'), (0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (363, 383, 'ORG'), (839, 856, 'ORG'), (751, 767, 'ORG'), (890, 906, 'ORG'), (970, 990, 'ORG'), (1297, 1311, 'ORG'), (1313, 1316, 'ORG'), (65, 71, 'DATE'), (129, 139, 'DATE'), (205, 240, 'DATE'), (296, 305, 'DATE'), (432, 441, 'DATE'), (456, 468, 'DATE'), (325, 334, 'DATE'), (505, 513, 'DATE'), (117, 121, 'CHANGE'), (500, 504, 'CHANGE'), (286, 295, 'STATE'), (89, 97, 'STATE'), (286, 294, 'STATE'), (408, 416, 'STATE'), (81, 88, 'DISEASE'), (177, 184, 'DISEASE'), (400, 407, 'DISEASE'), (487, 494, 'DISEASE'), (621, 628, 'DISEASE'), (1069, 1076, 'DISEASE'), (1381, 1388, 'DISEASE'), (257, 259, 'CARDINAL'), (1191, 1193, 'CARDINAL'), (1208, 1210, 'CARDINAL'), (1147, 1149, 'CARDINAL'), (1139, 1143, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "Less than half of target children get measles vaccine",
    "timestamp": "September 18, 2014 10:58 PM",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines – Two weeks after the Department of Health (DOH) launched its month-long mass immunization campaign, only 44% of the target number of children had received vaccines for measles-rubella and oral polio. In a press conference Thursday, September 18, Health Undersecretary Janette Garin said the department’s target is to reach 50% by 2nd week of September. “We need a more aggressive campaign now na nasimulan na natin. Being on [its] 2nd week, supposedly nasa 50% na ang nareach [ng campaign],” she explained. (We need a more aggressive campaign now that we already started it. Being on [its] 2nd week, supposedly the campaign already reached 50%.) There are several reasons why DOH did not hit the target, Garin said. Some areas started the campaign late, while some are still recovering from disasters. There are also areas which lacked preparation. In the Autonomous Region in Muslim Mindanao (ARMM), for example, DOH had to sort through issues of logistical support. “Hindi basta-basta puwedeng ibaba kung 'di mo ma-assure na yung pondo ay mapupunta sa pagpapabakuna,“ she said, adding that the funds from the Central Office are only supplementary to funds of the local government. (You can't just make fund releases if you can't be sure they will really go to vaccination.) Measles is a viral, highly-contagious respiratory disease. Infected persons exhibit symptoms such as high fever, red eyes, runny nose, and cough. Rashes appear throughout the body after two days. The illness can be spread through cough or direct contact with body secretions of an infected person. A person with measles can pass the disease on to 18 other people. From January 1 to August 9, 2014, the DOH recorded 48,779 suspected cases of measles. Out of this number, 16,743 are confirmed cases. Participation of provinces, cities Garin praised the provinces and cities with the highest immunization rates: Top performing provinces Top performing cities In the National Capital Region, the top performing cities for measles-rubella immunization (47% to 62%) are San Juan, Navotas, Caloocan, Las Piñas, and Valenzuela. For the oral polio vaccine, the top performing cities (47% to 60%) are San Juan, Las Piñas, Caloocan, Navotas, and Pateros. But the areas below have some catching up to do: Low performing areas for measles-rubella and oral polio immunization Garin said the fight of the country against measles will be “useless“ if not everyone will cooperate. She urged local government units to help reach children in their locality. The campaign aims to achieve at least 95% vaccination coverage at all administrative levels. The target covers children who received their vaccination from health centers, barangay health stations, local churches, and other designated vaccination posts. “Sayang naman kung patuloy nating papayagan yung isang sakit na manatili sa bansa natin [kung] meron naman tayong pera at kakayanan para sugpuin ito,“ she said. (It’s a shame if we will let a disease affect our country when we have the resources and the capability to fight it.) She added: “Mahirap kung maraming missed children from 0-5 [years old] dahil sila [ang] source ng infection (It’s hard to have a lot of missed chldren from 0-5 years old because they can be the source of the infection).“ Sustain awareness DOH is deploying rapid coverage assessment teams in areas with low immunization rates. If the teams find at least 2 unvaccinated children, it means the area has not yet been fully covered by the campaign. If the teams find no unvaccinated children, the department will declare the area fully-covered, since the actual number of children is different from the estimated target. Garin said there is a need to sustain the awareness on the importance of immunization to reach the 95% target. After all, some of the complications of measles are permanent, like blindness. The disease can also be deadly. “Nung una very maingay [yung campaign]. Ang bilis makalimutan. Kailangan pa ng dagdag na ingay. It’s not the cost, it’s the lives that we can save,“ she added. (There was a lot of noise at the start of the campaign. People are quick to forget. We need to make some more noise. It’s not the cost, it’s the lives that we can save.) Despite missing its initial target, Garin hopes the health department will still reach the 95% target, so that the campaign would not have to be extended. “If we extend, the more difficult it will be to fight it. But as the need arises, we will make a decision,“ she said in a mix of English and Filipino. The Philippines, which “exported” measles to other countries, hopes to eliminate measles by 2017.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/69480-doh-misses-target-measles-vaccination-september",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (4547, 4558, 'GPE'), (877, 920, 'GPE'), (1960, 1983, 'GPE'), (2061, 2069, 'GPE'), (2188, 2196, 'GPE'), (2071, 2078, 'GPE'), (2219, 2226, 'GPE'), (2080, 2088, 'GPE'), (2209, 2217, 'GPE'), (2090, 2099, 'GPE'), (2198, 2207, 'GPE'), (2105, 2115, 'GPE'), (2232, 2239, 'GPE'), (42, 68, 'ORG'), (1132, 1146, 'ORG'), (1186, 1202, 'ORG'), (2471, 2487, 'ORG'), (64, 67, 'ORG'), (697, 700, 'ORG'), (935, 938, 'ORG'), (1699, 1702, 'ORG'), (3308, 3311, 'ORG'), (2692, 2706, 'ORG'), (2708, 2732, 'ORG'), (2734, 2748, 'ORG'), (126, 129, 'PERCENT'), (344, 347, 'PERCENT'), (478, 481, 'PERCENT'), (661, 664, 'PERCENT'), (2045, 2055, 'PERCENT'), (2172, 2182, 'PERCENT'), (2574, 2577, 'PERCENT'), (3784, 3787, 'PERCENT'), (4328, 4331, 'PERCENT'), (189, 204, 'DISEASE'), (2015, 2030, 'DISEASE'), (2315, 2330, 'DISEASE'), (209, 219, 'DISEASE'), (2125, 2135, 'DISEASE'), (2335, 2345, 'DISEASE'), (1297, 1304, 'DISEASE'), (1609, 1616, 'DISEASE'), (1738, 1745, 'DISEASE'), (2403, 2410, 'DISEASE'), (3836, 3843, 'DISEASE'), (4577, 4584, 'DISEASE'), (4624, 4631, 'DISEASE'), (243, 265, 'DATE'), (351, 372, 'DATE'), (1661, 1693, 'DATE'), (4635, 4639, 'DATE'), (1712, 1718, 'CASE'), (1729, 1734, 'CASE'), (1788, 1793, 'CASE'), (1767, 1773, 'CASE'), (2866, 2871, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2387, 2394, 'LOC_TYPE'), (3001, 3008, 'LOC_TYPE'), (4594, 4603, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1644, 1646, 'CARDINAL'), (22, 25, 'CARDINAL'), (1483, 1486, 'CARDINAL'), (3124, 3127, 'CARDINAL'), (3422, 3423, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH: Measles upsurge due to kids missing free vaccination",
    "timestamp": "January 06, 2014 9:56 PM",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines – The recent upsurge of measles cases in certain areas of the country, especially Metro Manila, was due to children missing crucial measles vaccinations at an early age, the health department said on Monday, January 6. The irony is that the vaccines are readily available for free in rural health clinics across the country. Latest figures from government showed that the number of confirmed cases in Metro Manila in 2013 was almost 17 times more than the figure from 2012. Of the 417 cases of measles recorded in the national capital region 2013, Health Secretary Enrique Ona said 88% didn't have any history of vaccination. In a press conference, Ona attributed the increase in measles cases to children missing their preliminary and booster vaccination shots. Babies aged 6 to 11 months should be administered their first vaccine shot. At 12 to 18 months, they should get vaccination a second time. “There are a good number of parents who, for one reason or another, don't get their child vaccinated,“ said Ona. As an example, he cited certain tribes or religious sectors whose members refuse vaccinations. The Department of Health (DOH) was able to vaccinate only 85% of Filipino children during the last nationwide vaccination program in 2011, he said. “As you go in the last 3 years, there were a lot of children who missed the vaccinations, making them suscepticle to measles,“ Ona continued. “The point is, there should have been no more measles in Metro Manila, or even in the whole Philippines, but that has not happened yet. The Philippines is not yet measles-free,“ said Ona. The DOH is slated to conduct another nationwide vaccination drive this year. Extent of the outbreak Ona said that the DOH is aware of the measles outbreak in certain areas of the country, and is closely coordinating with local health officials to address the matter. “Yes, there have been an increase in reports in some areas in Metro Manila. We are aware of it. We are monitoring it very closely,“ said Ona. Ona then clarified to media the definition of an outbreak. “It means that there have been cases of a disease – either suspected or confirmed – in a community or a locality where in the past there was none.“ Even a single case, if it is the first ever in area, is considered an outbreak, he said. There were a total of 1,724 measles cases reported nationwide, from Jan 1 to Dec 14, 2013, with 21 deaths. Latest figures in the National Capital Region (NCR) from the DOH Center for Health Development (CHD) show that there have been 417 confirmed measles cases, including 3 deaths, logged in 2013. In 2012, only 25 cases were reported in NCR. Children between one and 4 years old were affected the most, consisting 38% of the cases. Las Piñas City reported the most number of measles cases with 78, followed by Manila (72), Muntinlupa City (65), Caloocan City (45), and Parañaque City (32). The DOH report also noted that 88% of the measles cases in the NCR in 2013 had no history of previous measles vaccination. Ona said that all cities in Metro Manila have been actively expanding their vaccination drives since September 2013, when most measles cases started rising drastically. “As a matter of fact, in December 2013 in the city of Manila, there was a 28% decrease in suspected measles cases. In Caloocan City, there were no suspected cases in November and December,“ said Ona. “There is no reason to be scared, or to be too concerned. However, it is imperative that the parents take a good look at their children always, so that when symptoms of measles appear, the child should be brought to the hospital or health center,“ Ona added. When asked if adults can also avail themselves of measles vaccines, Ona said that they could, but the children are top priority.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/47329-doh-measles-upsurge-kids-miss-free-vaccination",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(102, 114, 'GPE'), (421, 433, 'GPE'), (1477, 1489, 'GPE'), (1937, 1949, 'GPE'), (3056, 3068, 'GPE'), (2825, 2831, 'GPE'), (3251, 3257, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (1512, 1523, 'GPE'), (1560, 1571, 'GPE'), (44, 51, 'DISEASE'), (152, 159, 'DISEASE'), (514, 521, 'DISEASE'), (700, 707, 'DISEASE'), (1395, 1402, 'DISEASE'), (1466, 1473, 'DISEASE'), (1583, 1590, 'DISEASE'), (1746, 1753, 'DISEASE'), (2341, 2348, 'DISEASE'), (2561, 2568, 'DISEASE'), (2790, 2797, 'DISEASE'), (2947, 2954, 'DISEASE'), (3007, 3014, 'DISEASE'), (3155, 3162, 'DISEASE'), (3297, 3304, 'DISEASE'), (3566, 3573, 'DISEASE'), (3706, 3713, 'DISEASE'), (52, 57, 'CASE'), (412, 417, 'CASE'), (505, 510, 'CASE'), (708, 713, 'CASE'), (2107, 2112, 'CASE'), (2349, 2354, 'CASE'), (2569, 2574, 'CASE'), (2629, 2634, 'CASE'), (2740, 2745, 'CASE'), (2798, 2803, 'CASE'), (2955, 2960, 'CASE'), (3163, 3168, 'CASE'), (3305, 3310, 'CASE'), (3354, 3359, 'CASE'), (82, 89, 'LOC_TYPE'), (336, 343, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1787, 1794, 'LOC_TYPE'), (194, 211, 'ORG'), (220, 237, 'DATE'), (304, 324, 'ORG'), (437, 441, 'DATE'), (562, 566, 'DATE'), (2398, 2402, 'DATE'), (2606, 2610, 'DATE'), (2975, 2979, 'DATE'), (3139, 3143, 'DATE'), (3231, 3235, 'DATE'), (453, 466, 'CHANGE'), (488, 492, 'DATE'), (2615, 2619, 'DATE'), (501, 504, 'CASE'), (2547, 2550, 'CASE'), (538, 561, 'GPE'), (602, 605, 'PERCENT'), (2936, 2939, 'PERCENT'), (688, 696, 'CHANGE'), (1900, 1908, 'CHANGE'), (1134, 1160, 'ORG'), (1188, 1191, 'PERCENT'), (1263, 1267, 'DATE'), (1296, 1308, 'DATE'), (1583, 1595, 'DISEASE'), (1612, 1615, 'DATE'), (1699, 1707, 'STATE'), (1754, 1762, 'STATE'), (2066, 2074, 'STATE'), (2294, 2302, 'STATE'), (2335, 2340, 'CASE'), (2376, 2402, 'CASE'), (2442, 2471, 'GPE'), (2481, 2520, 'ORG'), (501, 504, 'CASE'), (2547, 2550, 'CASE'), (2626, 2628, 'CASE'), (689, 692, 'GPE'), (2652, 2655, 'GPE'), (2968, 2971, 'GPE'), (2747, 2761, 'GPE'), (2825, 2831, 'GPE'), (2838, 2853, 'GPE'), (2860, 2873, 'GPE'), (3315, 3328, 'GPE'), (2884, 2898, 'GPE'), (2809, 2811, 'CASE'), (2337, 2339, 'CASE'), (2855, 2857, 'CASE'), (2875, 2877, 'CASE'), (2900, 2902, 'CASE'), (602, 605, 'PERCENT'), (2936, 2939, 'PERCENT'), (3123, 3143, 'DATE'), (3177, 3183, 'CHANGE'), (3222, 3235, 'DATE'), (3271, 3274, 'PERCENT'), (3275, 3283, 'CHANGE'), (3363, 3371, 'DATE'), (3376, 3384, 'DATE'), (795, 796, 'CARDINAL'), (800, 802, 'CARDINAL'), (862, 864, 'CARDINAL'), (868, 870, 'CARDINAL'), (967, 970, 'CARDINAL'), (2674, 2677, 'CARDINAL'), (2409, 2411, 'CARDINAL'), (2586, 2587, 'CARDINAL'), (2682, 2683, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "Measles outbreak declared in Maguindanao – report",
    "timestamp": "April 30, 2014 5:02am",
    "content": "Health authorities in Maguindanao have declared a measles outbreak in the province, state-run Philippines News Agency reported Tuesday. According to the report, Autonomous Region in Muslim Mindanao regional health secretary Kadil Sinolinding said 12 measles cases were recorded in April alone. “We are addressing it, we declared outbreak to contain the measles and prevent its spread,“ Sinolinding explained. While there have been no fatalities so far, Sinolinding said the situation was alarming “because this is highly contagious and can be transferred to other persons by air.“ He was also surprised to learn of the 12 cases, believing that the province was measles-free. Sinolinding said he had ordered an investigation into why the provincial health office did not submit a status report to him. He also asked the Department of Health in Manila for additional vaccines for heavily affected towns. The April measles cases had been taken to and confined at the Cotabato Regional Hospital and Medical Center (CRMC). The PNA report said that since January, 49 cases have been reported in Maguindanao. Of these, 37 were confirmed by the Research Institute for Tropical Medicine (RITM). The measles cases were from Parang, Shariff Aguak, Datu Odin Sinsuat, Datu Abdullah Sangki, Matanog, Barira, Upi, Datu Unsay, Datu Hoffer, Mamasapano, Sultan Kudarat and Pagalungan towns. Symptoms of measles, which include high fever, usually develop seven to 14 days after exposure to an infected person.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/358926/measles-outbreak-declared-in-maguindanao-report/story/",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(22, 33, 'GPE'), (1089, 1100, 'GPE'), (50, 57, 'DISEASE'), (250, 257, 'DISEASE'), (353, 360, 'DISEASE'), (661, 668, 'DISEASE'), (912, 919, 'DISEASE'), (1190, 1197, 'DISEASE'), (1386, 1393, 'DISEASE'), (58, 66, 'STATE'), (329, 337, 'STATE'), (74, 82, 'LOC_TYPE'), (648, 656, 'LOC_TYPE'), (94, 117, 'ORG'), (127, 134, 'DATE'), (161, 197, 'GPE'), (247, 249, 'CASE'), (619, 621, 'CASE'), (258, 263, 'CASE'), (622, 627, 'CASE'), (920, 925, 'CASE'), (1061, 1066, 'CASE'), (1198, 1203, 'CASE'), (281, 286, 'DATE'), (906, 911, 'DATE'), (737, 761, 'ORG'), (819, 839, 'ORG'), (843, 849, 'GPE'), (895, 900, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1367, 1372, 'LOC_TYPE'), (964, 1016, 'GPE'), (1022, 1025, 'ORG'), (1049, 1056, 'DATE'), (1058, 1060, 'CASE'), (1112, 1114, 'CASE'), (1137, 1184, 'ORG'), (1214, 1220, 'GPE'), (1222, 1235, 'GPE'), (1237, 1254, 'GPE'), (1256, 1276, 'GPE'), (1278, 1285, 'GPE'), (1287, 1293, 'GPE'), (1295, 1298, 'GPE'), (1300, 1310, 'GPE'), (1312, 1323, 'GPE'), (1325, 1335, 'GPE'), (1337, 1351, 'GPE'), (1356, 1366, 'GPE'), (1437, 1442, 'CARDINAL'), (1446, 1448, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "7 measles deaths recorded in Davao City in August",
    "timestamp": "August 31, 2014 9:56am",
    "content": "At least seven children died due to measles in Davao City in August, a Mindanao news site quoted a city health official as saying late Saturday. City Health Office immunization head Armi Capili said the spike in such cases was due to many mothers' failure to have their children immunized, MindaNews reported. She said another reason could be the disease's contagious nature where one case can contaminate up to 20 people. Of some 1,228 suspected measles cases as of August 27, 120 have been confirmed so far. As of August 8, the CHO said most reports of suspected measles cases came from Talomo North with 201, Talomo South with 133, and Buhangin with 116. In 2012, Capili said there were only four confirmed cases in Davao City. She said this could be due to an intensified immunization campaign in 2011. There were 50 confirmed cases in 2013. Department of Health regional unit head for health education and promotion Divene Hilario said the total regional prevalence of measles in 2013 was only 129. Capili said the department will head a massive immunization program for measles, rubela, and polio from September 1 to 30 at health centers and other vaccination points. Miscommunication? MindaNews quoted Hilario as saying there may be a miscommunication with mothers on immunization against measles. “The problem is that some parents do not take their children back to the health centers after the prescribed nine months for a second shot,“ she said. She said parents need to take their children to the centers again for a second booster dose. In the meantime, the City Health Office urged parents to take their children below five years old for free vaccination during September. On the other hand, CHO assistant officer for operations Marjorie Culas said the expanded immunization campaign may have been a victim of online misinformation. Culas cited online information claiming “bad effects” of immunization such as a cause of abortion and autism.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/377136/7-measles-deaths-recorded-in-davao-city-in-august/story/",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(36, 43, 'DISEASE'), (447, 454, 'DISEASE'), (565, 572, 'DISEASE'), (974, 981, 'DISEASE'), (1076, 1083, 'DISEASE'), (1296, 1303, 'DISEASE'), (47, 57, 'GPE'), (719, 729, 'GPE'), (61, 67, 'DATE'), (467, 473, 'DATE'), (516, 522, 'DATE'), (71, 89, 'ORG'), (135, 143, 'DATE'), (290, 299, 'ORG'), (1192, 1201, 'ORG'), (381, 384, 'CASE'), (217, 222, 'CASE'), (385, 389, 'CASE'), (455, 460, 'CASE'), (573, 578, 'CASE'), (710, 715, 'CASE'), (831, 836, 'CASE'), (431, 436, 'CASE'), (385, 389, 'CASE'), (467, 476, 'DATE'), (478, 481, 'CASE'), (516, 524, 'DATE'), (530, 533, 'ORG'), (1705, 1708, 'ORG'), (489, 601, 'GPE'), (607, 611, 'DATE'), (612, 624, 'GPE'), (630, 633, 'CASE'), (639, 647, 'GPE'), (653, 656, 'CASE'), (661, 665, 'DATE'), (801, 805, 'DATE'), (818, 820, 'CASE'), (840, 844, 'DATE'), (985, 989, 'DATE'), (1085, 1091, 'DISEASE'), (1097, 1102, 'DISEASE'), (1103, 1125, 'DATE'), (1129, 1143, 'ORG'), (1378, 1392, 'ORG'), (145, 163, 'ORG'), (1570, 1588, 'ORG'), (1108, 1117, 'DATE'), (1675, 1684, 'DATE'), (9, 14, 'CARDINAL'), (412, 414, 'CARDINAL'), (999, 1002, 'CARDINAL'), (1414, 1418, 'CARDINAL'), (1632, 1636, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "160 measles cases prompt vaccination drive in Surigao City",
    "timestamp": "May 17, 2014 2:13pm",
    "content": "A large-scale measles vaccination drive is now ongoing in Surigao City after local health authorities recorded a rise in the number of cases, a Mindanao news site reported Saturday. Surigao City health officials had declared a measles outbreak on May 3 due to the number of cases, according to a report on MindaNews. City information officer Annette Villaces said at least 160 people, mostly children, have been affected by measles from January 1 to May 13, the report added. Surigao City Health Office chief epidemiologist Dr. Romulo Ybiernas said the vaccination drive includes mainly Barangays Taft, Washington and San Juan, where most of the victims reside. Particularly targeted in the massive vaccination drive are children six months to four years old. The report said at least one patient had died due to measles in a private hospital last April 2. For its part, the Department of Health in Caraga has dispatched personnel from the Regional Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit to help fight measles.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/361447/160-measles-cases-prompt-vaccination-drive-in-surigao-city/story/",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(14, 21, 'DISEASE'), (227, 234, 'DISEASE'), (424, 431, 'DISEASE'), (813, 820, 'DISEASE'), (998, 1005, 'DISEASE'), (58, 70, 'GPE'), (182, 194, 'GPE'), (476, 488, 'GPE'), (113, 117, 'CHANGE'), (135, 140, 'CASE'), (274, 279, 'CASE'), (144, 162, 'ORG'), (172, 180, 'DATE'), (235, 243, 'STATE'), (247, 252, 'DATE'), (306, 315, 'ORG'), (432, 456, 'DATE'), (587, 596, 'LOC_TYPE'), (597, 601, 'GPE'), (603, 613, 'GPE'), (618, 626, 'GPE'), (848, 855, 'DATE'), (875, 895, 'ORG'), (899, 905, 'GPE'), (940, 983, 'ORG'), (785, 788, 'CARDINAL'), (373, 376, 'CARDINAL'), (730, 733, 'CARDINAL'), (744, 748, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH issues measles alert in NCR as cases rise",
    "timestamp": "December 11, 2013 4:27pm",
    "content": "The Department of Health on Wednesday advised residents in Metro Manila to take precautions against measles, after noting two deaths and a rise in cases in at least five cities in the National Capital Region. In a statement posted on the government website, DOH Metro Manila head Eduardo Janairo cited records showing a rapid rise in measles cases in Las Piñas, Muntinlupa, Caloocan, Manila, and Parañaque. “Everyone should take necessary precaution because measles is a severe disease that causes complications like ear infections, pneumonia and even inflammation of the brain. It is also highly contagious and can be spread easily through cough and sneeze and direct contact with affected persons through nose or mouth secretions,“ Janairo said The DOH Metro Manila said its records showed the fatalities came from Malabon and Muntinlupa. It added that most of those affected were one to four years old, and most were male. Janairo advised parents and guardians of children to look out for symptoms including: common cold symptoms like high fever, cough, runny nose, sore eyes that can last for several days, appearance of a red, blotchy rash. “If you believe you are exposed to someone with measles, you should observe for measles symptoms to appear after nine days. Some person can be affected immediately before the rash appears four days after being exposed.“ he said. Janairo also advised the public to make sure they and members of their families are up to date on measles-mumps-rubella (MMR) vaccines and other age-appropriate immunizations. “Measles vaccination not only protects the person but also serves as safeguard to family members who are too young to get the vaccine or haven’t received it yet. Receiving two doses of measles vaccine is highly effective in preventing measles,“ he said. 616% rise Citing partial reports from the Regional Epidemiology Surveillance Unit, the DOH said there were 179 confirmed measles cases from January 1 to December 10. It said this was 616 percent higher compared to the same period last year, with only 25 cases recorded. For this year, the ages of cases ranged from one month to 37 years. Most of those affected were one to four years old, and most were male. The cities with most number of measles cases were: Las Piñas, 44 cases; Muntinlupa, 32; Caloocan, 26; Manila, 22; Parañaque, 15; Malabon, 10; Quezon City, 8; Taguig, 8; Navotas, 7; Pasay, 4; Makati, 2; Pasig, 1; Mandaluyong, Marikina, San Juan and Valenzuela Cities, along with Pateros town, recorded zero case so far. Meanwhile, the DOH Metro Manila dispatched teams of nurses who will act as Anti-Measles Task Force to identified areas in the NCR. It said the nurses will “assist in evaluating patients and provide the necessary vaccination to prevent further transmission of the disease.“ Janairo urged all parents and caregivers of children aged 0-12 years old to go the nearest health center and have their children immunized against measles. Further, the DOH Metro Manila advised the public to report suspected measles cases to a health care provider before going to a hospital. It said a suspected measles case must first be evaluated as a precaution and protection for other patients and health workers from possible infection. The DOH noted measles can easily be spread through the air when an infected person talks, coughs, or sneezes. “People can also get sick when they come in contact with mucus or saliva from an infected person. Anyone who hasn’t been vaccinated or has not had measles is at risk if they are exposed to the virus,“ it said. It added measles can cause serious complications such as pneumonia and encephalitis (swelling of the brain). Measles infection in a pregnant woman can lead to miscarriage, premature birth, or a low-birth weight baby, it said. “Those who have developed symptoms of measles should stay away from public places such as work, school, child care, shops, and public transport to avoid putting others at risk,“ it said.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/metro/339346/doh-issues-measles-alert-in-ncr-as-cases-rise/story/",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(4, 24, 'ORG'), (258, 274, 'ORG'), (751, 767, 'ORG'), (2548, 2564, 'ORG'), (2975, 2991, 'ORG'), (1892, 1895, 'ORG'), (3254, 3257, 'ORG'), (1847, 1886, 'ORG'), (2608, 2631, 'ORG'), (1473, 1500, 'DISEASE'), (100, 107, 'DISEASE'), (334, 341, 'DISEASE'), (458, 465, 'DISEASE'), (1194, 1201, 'DISEASE'), (1226, 1233, 'DISEASE'), (1736, 1743, 'DISEASE'), (1786, 1793, 'DISEASE'), (1926, 1933, 'DISEASE'), (2245, 2252, 'DISEASE'), (2953, 2960, 'DISEASE'), (3031, 3038, 'DISEASE'), (3119, 3126, 'DISEASE'), (3264, 3271, 'DISEASE'), (3507, 3514, 'DISEASE'), (3579, 3586, 'DISEASE'), (3679, 3686, 'DISEASE'), (3834, 3841, 'DISEASE'), (139, 143, 'CHANGE'), (326, 330, 'CHANGE'), (1810, 1814, 'CHANGE'), (2000, 2006, 'CHANGE'), (147, 152, 'CASE'), (342, 347, 'CASE'), (1934, 1939, 'CASE'), (2059, 2064, 'CASE'), (2102, 2107, 'CASE'), (2253, 2258, 'CASE'), (2279, 2284, 'CASE'), (3039, 3044, 'CASE'), (1912, 1915, 'CASE'), (2056, 2058, 'CASE'), (2276, 2278, 'CASE'), (2298, 2300, 'CASE'), (2312, 2314, 'CASE'), (2324, 2326, 'CASE'), (2413, 2414, 'CASE'), (2339, 2341, 'CASE'), (1967, 1969, 'CASE'), (2352, 2354, 'CASE'), (2369, 2370, 'CASE'), (2380, 2381, 'CASE'), (1913, 1914, 'CASE'), (2392, 2393, 'CASE'), (2402, 2403, 'CASE'), (2423, 2424, 'CASE'), (2515, 2519, 'CASE'), (170, 176, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2218, 2224, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2473, 2479, 'LOC_TYPE'), (184, 207, 'GPE'), (351, 360, 'GPE'), (2265, 2274, 'GPE'), (362, 372, 'GPE'), (829, 839, 'GPE'), (2286, 2296, 'GPE'), (374, 382, 'GPE'), (2302, 2310, 'GPE'), (59, 71, 'GPE'), (384, 390, 'GPE'), (2316, 2322, 'GPE'), (396, 405, 'GPE'), (2328, 2337, 'GPE'), (817, 824, 'GPE'), (2343, 2350, 'GPE'), (2356, 2367, 'GPE'), (2372, 2378, 'GPE'), (2383, 2390, 'GPE'), (2395, 2400, 'GPE'), (2416, 2421, 'GPE'), (2405, 2411, 'GPE'), (2426, 2437, 'GPE'), (2439, 2447, 'GPE'), (2449, 2457, 'GPE'), (2462, 2472, 'GPE'), (2492, 2499, 'GPE'), (2659, 2662, 'GPE'), (1805, 1809, 'PERCENT'), (1988, 1999, 'PERCENT'), (1097, 1109, 'DATE'), (1940, 1969, 'DATE'), (2035, 2044, 'DATE'), (122, 125, 'CARDINAL'), (1723, 1726, 'CARDINAL'), (413, 416, 'CARDINAL'), (883, 886, 'CARDINAL'), (2120, 2123, 'CARDINAL'), (2171, 2174, 'CARDINAL'), (165, 169, 'CARDINAL'), (890, 894, 'CARDINAL'), (1334, 1338, 'CARDINAL'), (2178, 2182, 'CARDINAL'), (1259, 1263, 'CARDINAL'), (2133, 2135, 'CARDINAL'), (2864, 2868, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "Typhoid outbreak declared in Tuburan, Cebu",
    "timestamp": "March 05, 2012 8:42 PM",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines - The health department on Monday, March 5, declared a typhoid fever outbreak in 54 barangays in Tuburan, Cebu. As much as 400 individuals in the area have been afflicted by the disease. The number of cases was observed to have started piling up last February 22. Of the 400 reported cases, 31 were confined in hospitals in Tuburan, a coastal town located north of Cebu City. Department of Health Assistant Secretary Eric Tayag said the department is eyeing “contaminated water“ as the cause of the outbreak. He said, however, that it is not clear yet whether the contaminated water came from pipelines or deep wells, the two sources of residents for their water. Tayag said the health department has already dispatched teams to look into the outbreak. Meantime, he advised residents of the affected areas to boil or disinfect water, while health officials are waiting for lab results on the water tests. Tayag said antibiotics were already distributed to those requiring treatment. This is to prevent deaths due to intestinal hemorrhage or severe bacterial infection. Potentially fatal disease Typhoid fever is a life-threatening illness caused by the bacterium Salmonella Typhi. A person can get it from food or drink contaminated by the feces or urine of infected people. Typhoid symptoms usually develop 1–3 weeks after exposure, and may be mild or severe. Symptoms include high fever, malaise, headache, constipation or diarrhea, rose-colored spots on the chest, and an enlarged spleen and liver. Even after symptoms go away, those afflicted may still be carrying Salmonella Typhi, according to information published by the Atlanta-based Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). This means the illness could return, or the person previously afflicted could pass the disease to other people. How to avoid typhoid The CDC lists down the following tips to avoid typhoid:  If you drink water, buy it bottled or bring it to a rolling boil for 1 minute before you drink it. Ask for drinks without ice--unless the ice is made from bottled or boiled water. Avoid popsicles and flavored ices that may have been made with contaminated water. Eat foods that have been thoroughly cooked and that are still hot and steaming. Avoid raw vegetables and fruits that cannot be peeled. Vegetables like lettuce are easily contaminated and are very hard to wash well. When you eat raw fruit or vegetables that can be peeled, peel them yourself. (Wash your hands with soap first.) Do not eat the peelings. Avoid foods and beverages from street vendors. It is difficult for food to be kept clean on the street, and many travelers get sick from food bought from street vendors.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/2126-typhoid-outbreak-declared-in-tuburan,-cebu",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (47, 62, 'DATE'), (75, 88, 'DISEASE'), (1115, 1128, 'DISEASE'), (89, 97, 'STATE'), (519, 527, 'STATE'), (763, 771, 'STATE'), (104, 113, 'LOC_TYPE'), (117, 130, 'GPE'), (221, 226, 'CASE'), (304, 309, 'CASE'), (266, 282, 'DATE'), (143, 146, 'CASE'), (291, 294, 'CASE'), (311, 313, 'CASE'), (385, 394, 'GPE'), (26, 43, 'ORG'), (699, 716, 'ORG'), (1649, 1711, 'ORG'), (1707, 1710, 'ORG'), (1850, 1853, 'ORG'), (2549, 2555, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2614, 2620, 'LOC_TYPE'), (2672, 2678, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1295, 1302, 'DISEASE'), (1838, 1845, 'DISEASE'), (1893, 1900, 'DISEASE'), (101, 103, 'CARDINAL'), (143, 146, 'CARDINAL'), (642, 645, 'CARDINAL'), (1972, 1973, 'CARDINAL'), (1328, 1331, 'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "Contaminated water caused typhoid outbreak - DoH",
    "timestamp": "March 10, 2008 2:08pm",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines - (Updated 7:10 p.m.) The Department of Health (DOH) on Monday confirmed that the typhoid fever outbreak in Calamba City in Laguna was caused by contaminated water found to have “low chlorine level.“ In a press conference in Calamba City on Monday morning, Health Secretary Francisco Duque revealed the results of the health department's microbiological testing showed organisms called coliform bacteria were present in some water samples obtained from the water source in affected areas. The test also showed that chlorine level in the water from the Calamba Water District was insufficient to fully disinfect the water and rid it of coliform. Dr Dennis Labro, spokesman of the city health office, however said that the test does not entirely put the blame on the Calamba Water District, which supplies water in the city, since contamination with coliform could has happened “along the line.“ Contaminated water samples were said to have been obtained in areas near the CWD-owned Bucal Pumping Station, a QTV report said Monday. The television report quoted officials from the Calamba Water District as denying that the water they supply is contaminated, adding that they have laboratory tests to prove it. The DOH since last week started gathering water samples from 18 affected villages in Calamba to determine whether the drinking water in the area carried salmonella typhi, which causes typhoid fever. While the first few water samples tested negative for the bacteria, later tests showed the presence of coliform, an organism that usually indicates the presence of other fecal bacteria like salmonella typhi. “The coliform bacteria is too general to say that what caused the outbreak was salmonella (typhi),“ Labro said in a phone interview with GMANews.TV. Labro clarified however that coliform bacteria were not present in all water samples, saying there were only “specific areas“ where water was found to be contaminated. “May mga household na may lumabas na ganun ang findings at may mga business establishment na ganun din,“ Labro said. The DOH is now considering on forwarding the water samples to a private laboratory, which has the appropriate equipment to specifically ascertain the kind of coliform present in the water samples. Aside from baring the findings of the DOH test, the Health Secretary likewise urged Calamba Water District officials to coordinate with the agency in order to stamp out the spread of the fever. The Health department also recommended the proper disinfection and continuous monitoring of drinking water being supplied to households and business establishments. Residents were likewise advised to boil their water before consuming them. In his visit to Calamba City, Duque also met with Dr Eric Tayag of the DOH National Epidemiology Center, Calamba Mayor Joaquin Chipeco, and other city health officials. As of Sunday, a total of 732 residents have been hospitalized after showing symptoms of the disease while 1,272 more have visited community health centers to have themselves checked, Labro said. The DOH said that while the number of people ushed to the hospital have declined, they are not about to declare that they have the outbreak contained, adding that they will continue monitoring the situation until the week's end. Although more than two thousand residents have already been affected by the outbreak, city health officials maintained that no confirmed deaths from typhoid fever has been reported yet. Officials refused to confirm two previous deaths, including a 14-year-old girl, as being connected to typhoid since both have not undergone screening tests and autopsies. Labro however said they are still further studying the case of the 14-year-old girl, whose parents have refused to have her subjected to an autopsy. But Labro said they would still undertake “other investigations short of having autopsy.“ For his part, Sen. Richard Gordon, who is the Philippine National Red Cross (PNRC) chairman, slammed the government's sluggish actions in determining the root of the widespread health problem. “Where did this originate? In water pipelines? Many people in 18 villages are affected and the government should come out and tell us this comes from this place, so that we can stop the outbreak,“ Gordon told GMA News in Filipino. The PNRC has been assisting local health officials in attending to hospitalized residents by providing free medicines, tents, and beds. Labro said that health officials were not immediately able to release confirmation of the water contamination since early water samples obtained from various sources tested negative for any bacteria.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/84102/contaminated-water-caused-typhoid-outbreak-doh/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (46, 72, 'ORG'), (102, 115, 'DISEASE'), (1412, 1425, 'DISEASE'), (3442, 3445, 'DISEASE'), (116, 124, 'STATE'), (1701, 1709, 'STATE'), (3195, 3203, 'STATE'), (3369, 3377, 'STATE'), (4268, 4267, 'STATE'), (128, 140, 'GPE'), (245, 257, 'GPE'), (2716, 2728, 'GPE'), (2716, 2728, 'GPE'), (144, 150, 'GPE'), (261, 275, 'DATE'), (572, 594, 'ORG'), (785, 807, 'ORG'), (1098, 1120, 'ORG'), (2350, 2372, 'ORG'), (699, 717, 'ORG'), (695, 703, 'LOC_TYPE'), (833, 841, 'LOC_TYPE'), (76, 82, 'DATE'), (261, 267, 'DATE'), (1042, 1048, 'DATE'), (68, 71, 'ORG'), (1232, 1235, 'ORG'), (2073, 2076, 'ORG'), (2304, 2307, 'ORG'), (2771, 2774, 'ORG'), (3068, 3071, 'ORG'), (1242, 1251, 'DATE'), (1289, 1291, 'CARDINAL'), (4144, 4146, 'CARDINAL'), (245, 252, 'GPE'), (572, 579, 'GPE'), (785, 792, 'GPE'), (1098, 1105, 'GPE'), (1313, 1320, 'GPE'), (2350, 2357, 'GPE'), (2716, 2723, 'GPE'), (2805, 2812, 'GPE'), (110, 115, 'DISEASE'), (1420, 1425, 'DISEASE'), (2453, 2458, 'DISEASE'), (3450, 3455, 'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH investigates typhoid fever outbreak in Cebu town",
    "timestamp": "June 28, 2014 12:47am",
    "content": "Health officials are investigating an outbreak of typhoid fever in a town in Cebu, which some residents have blamed on the local water system. At least 86 cases of typhoid fever have been recorded at the health clinic of Borbon town, GMA Cebu's Vic Serna reported Friday. The cases were from barangays Lugo, Clavera, Cajil, Bili and Laaw. Some of the patients were brought to the Vicente Sotto Memorial Medical Center for treatment. State-run Philippine Information Agency said DOH Central Visayas regional head Jaime Bernadas confirmed a typhoid outbreak had been declared in Borbon Thursday. “We are giving medical assistance to typhoid-affected residents in Borbon,“ Bernadas said. Contaminated water A separate report by GMA Cebu's Chona Carreon said the water used by the residents was contaminated with fecal coliform. Department of Health Central Visayas recommended chlorination of the water sources in the area, and gave medicine to those affected. Bernadas also urged residents to boil their drinking water. GMA Cebu's Serna reported initial qualitative tests by the regional epidemiology and surveillance unit suggested the water from Sitio Makina in Barangay Lugo may have been contaminated with human waste. But Lugo water system and municipal administrator Rolando Bucog said not all who got sick got their water from the area. On the other hand, Bucog admitted their chlorinator's pump has not been working for two months. He said they are working on the problem. Bucog also said the number of cases had been declining since cases were brought to the Borbon health clinic last June 12. He said that if this trend continues, there will be no need to declare the five affected barangays under a state of calamity. Meanwhile, state-run Philippines News Agency said at least 43 inmates of the Cebu Provincial Detention and Rehabilitation Center (CPDRC) in Barangay Kalunasan in Cebu City have reportedly contracted a measles-like disease. The inmates who had such symptoms were isolated to prevent further infections, the report said. The PNA report said the jail has 1,971 inmates.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/367705/doh-investigates-typhoid-fever-outbreak-in-cebu-town/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(38, 46, 'STATE'), (547, 555, 'STATE'), (50, 63, 'DISEASE'), (164, 177, 'DISEASE'), (50, 57, 'DISEASE'), (164, 171, 'DISEASE'), (539, 546, 'DISEASE'), (631, 638, 'DISEASE'), (69, 73, 'LOC_TYPE'), (228, 232, 'LOC_TYPE'), (77, 81, 'GPE'), (238, 242, 'GPE'), (729, 733, 'GPE'), (1022, 1026, 'GPE'), (1804, 1808, 'GPE'), (1889, 1893, 'GPE'), (152, 154, 'CARDINAL'), (1426, 1429, 'CARDINAL'), (1676, 1680, 'CARDINAL'), (1786, 1788, 'CARDINAL'), (2079, 2084, 'CARDINAL'), (221, 232, 'GPE'), (302, 306, 'GPE'), (1171, 1175, 'GPE'), (1225, 1229, 'GPE'), (308, 315, 'GPE'), (324, 328, 'GPE'), (333, 337, 'GPE'), (1889, 1898, 'GPE'), (292, 301, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1690, 1699, 'LOC_TYPE'), (478, 481, 'ORG'), (825, 845, 'ORG'), (1077, 1120, 'ORG'), (1748, 1771, 'ORG'), (1804, 1863, 'ORG'), (1162, 1175, 'GPE'), (1867, 1885, 'GPE'), (1708, 1725, 'STATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Pangasinan gastroenteritis, typhoid cases up in 1st 5 months of 2015",
    "timestamp": "June 17, 2015 3:56am",
    "content": "Pangasinan health authorities on Tuesday reminded the public to be careful of the food they buy, especially from ambulant vendors, as gastroenteritis and typhoid fever cases were on the rise in the province during the first five months of 2015. According to a report from GMA Dagupan, the Provincial Health Office (PHO) found that from January 1 to June 1, there were 261 cases of typhoid fever compared to 230 during the same period last year. There were also 4,100 cases of gastroenteritis from January 1 to June 1, compared to 3,900 last year. The Pangasinan provincial health officer Dr. Anna de Guzman warned that the illnesses came from the contaminated water and mishandled food. Also, food can spoil quickly and is susceptible to contamination, especially during hot and humid periods To prevent more illnesses, vendors applying for a sanitary permit to operate were given lessons on proper food handling by the PHO. “Nagsasagawa kami ng orientation sa mga tindera na dapat may sanitary permit din,“ de Guzman said. According to the MedlinePlus website, typhoid fever is an infection that causes diarrhea and a rash commonly caused by the bacterium Salmonella typhi. Symptoms include fever, general ill-feeling and abdominal pain, as well as high fever (39.5 degrees Celsius) or higher and severe diarrhea. Medline described gastroenteritis - also called stomach flu - as an inflammation of the lining of the intestines caused by a virus, bacteria or parasites. Symptoms include diarrhea, abdominal pain, vomiting, headache, fever and chills, though most may recover with no treatment. But gastroenteritis' most common problem is dehydration, especially in infants, young children, elderly and people with weak immune systems.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/505226/pangasinan-gastroenteritis-typhoid-cases-up-in-1st-5-months-of-2015/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(276, 283, 'GPE'), (0, 10, 'GPE'), (551, 561, 'GPE'), (272, 275, 'ORG'), (289, 319, 'ORG'), (156, 159, 'ORG'), (920, 923, 'ORG'), (1041, 1048, 'ORG'), (1315, 1322, 'ORG'), (1041, 1052, 'ORG'), (336, 345, 'DATE'), (497, 506, 'DATE'), (349, 355, 'DATE'), (510, 516, 'DATE'), (33, 40, 'DATE'), (239, 243, 'CARDINAL'), (368, 371, 'CARDINAL'), (407, 410, 'CARDINAL'), (461, 466, 'CARDINAL'), (134, 149, 'DISEASE'), (476, 491, 'DISEASE'), (1333, 1348, 'DISEASE'), (1598, 1613, 'DISEASE'), (154, 161, 'DISEASE'), (381, 388, 'DISEASE'), (1062, 1069, 'DISEASE'), (154, 167, 'DISEASE'), (381, 394, 'DISEASE'), (1062, 1075, 'DISEASE'), (168, 173, 'CASE'), (372, 377, 'CASE'), (467, 472, 'CASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH: 226 new cases of suspected typhoid fever reported in Quezon",
    "timestamp": "November 24, 2008 4:33pm",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines - Some 226 new cases of suspected typhoid fever have been reported in Real town in the southern Philippine province of Quezon, the Department of Health said Monday. Health secretary Francisco Duque III said this brings to the total number of patients hospitalized due to fever in the province to 370. Duque said they are still confirming if the new patients are indeed suffering from typhoid fever. “The cases appear to be increasing because many are seeking treatment, but not all those are confirmed typhoid cases. We just have to treat them even if they are just suspected typhoid cases,“ he said. The patients are currently confined at the Claro Recto Memorial District Hospital. Initially, 144 cases of typhoid fever, including one death, were recorded at the district hospital. Duque said a team of health experts has already been deployed in Quezon to help in treatment of the patients and in controlling the spread of the typhoid fever. Asde from sending medical experts, Duque sad they have provided the local government of Quezon some P800,000 worth of drugs and other necessary equipment to control the outbreak. Typhoid fever is an illness caused by the bacterium salmonella enterica serovar typhi. It is transmitted by the ingestion of food or water contaminated with feces from an infected person. Symptoms of the disease include high fever, profuse sweating, gastroenteritis, and non-bloody diarrhea.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/135332/doh-226-new-cases-of-suspected-typhoid-fever-reported-in-quezon/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (139, 145, 'GPE'), (869, 875, 'GPE'), (1053, 1059, 'GPE'), (90, 99, 'GPE'), (95, 99, 'LOC_TYPE'), (127, 135, 'LOC_TYPE'), (304, 312, 'LOC_TYPE'), (685, 693, 'LOC_TYPE'), (785, 793, 'LOC_TYPE'), (151, 171, 'ORG'), (177, 183, 'DATE'), (316, 319, 'CARDINAL'), (715, 718, 'CARDINAL'), (1066, 1073, 'CARDINAL'), (54, 67, 'DISEASE'), (404, 417, 'DISEASE'), (728, 741, 'DISEASE'), (950, 963, 'DISEASE'), (1144, 1157, 'DISEASE'), (54, 61, 'DISEASE'), (404, 411, 'DISEASE'), (522, 529, 'DISEASE'), (596, 603, 'DISEASE'), (728, 735, 'DISEASE'), (950, 957, 'DISEASE'), (1144, 1151, 'DISEASE'), (62, 67, 'DISEASE'), (291, 296, 'DISEASE'), (412, 417, 'DISEASE'), (736, 741, 'DISEASE'), (958, 963, 'DISEASE'), (1152, 1157, 'DISEASE'), (1369, 1374, 'DISEASE'), (35, 40, 'CASE'), (424, 429, 'CASE'), (530, 535, 'CASE'), (604, 609, 'CASE'), (719, 724, 'CASE'), (252, 258, 'CASE'), (1134, 1142, 'STATE'), (443, 453, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Typhoid outbreak caused by contaminated water in Quezon - DOH",
    "timestamp": "November 19, 2008 4:39pm",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines - Contaminated water from a stream caused more than a hundred persons from three barangays in Real, Quezon to contact typhoid fever, the Department of Health said Wednesday. According to Dr. Eric Eric Tayag, head of the DoH's National Epidemiology Center, the DOH has sent a team which conducted laboratory analysis on the water samples to determine what caused 109 individuals to contact typhoid fever. “We found out they get water from the stream and no chlorination is being done,“ Tayag said. However, Tayag said they are still determining the type of contaminants found in the water supply. The experts have collected eight blood specimens and nine stool samples from the patients and water samples from 25 sampling points. Blood specimens were brought to the Research Institute for Tropical Medicine in Alabang City for analysis last Tuesday and results are expected to come out in one week. As of Nov. 18, a total of 109 residents have fallen ill and brought to Claro M. Recto Hospital in Infanta.  The victims are residents of barangays Poblacion 1, Poblacion 61 and Ungos, where the stream is located. Health Secretary Francisco Duque III said that there was an upsurge of cases last Nov. 17 when 44 patients developed the illness from the initial 17 cases recorded last Nov. 15. “It seems that's it's going down. We hope that this will continue,“ Duque added. As early as Oct. 24, there had been cases of suspected typhoid in the area. Tayag said the heavy rains last Nov. 1 might have aggravated it. Typhoid fever is a bacterial disease caused by Salmonella typhi which is transmitted through the ingestion of food or drink contaminated by the feces or urine of infected people.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/134467/typhoid-outbreak-caused-by-contaminated-water-in-quezon-doh/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (114, 118, 'GPE'), (120, 126, 'GPE'), (829, 841, 'GPE'), (1016, 1023, 'GPE'), (1065, 1076, 'GPE'), (1078, 1090, 'GPE'), (1095, 1100, 'GPE'), (101, 110, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1055, 1064, 'LOC_TYPE'), (157, 177, 'ORG'), (240, 243, 'ORG'), (280, 283, 'ORG'), (785, 825, 'ORG'), (183, 192, 'DATE'), (855, 867, 'DATE'), (924, 931, 'DATE'), (1300, 1307, 'DATE'), (1213, 1220, 'DATE'), (1402, 1409, 'DATE'), (924, 930, 'DATE'), (1213, 1219, 'DATE'), (1300, 1306, 'DATE'), (1498, 1504, 'DATE'), (72, 81, 'CARDINAL'), (382, 385, 'CARDINAL'), (944, 947, 'CARDINAL'), (643, 648, 'CARDINAL'), (669, 673, 'CARDINAL'), (729, 731, 'CARDINAL'), (499, 502, 'CARDINAL'), (908, 911, 'CARDINAL'), (382, 385, 'CARDINAL'), (944, 947, 'CARDINAL'), (1226, 1228, 'CARDINAL'), (1218, 1220, 'CARDINAL'), (1277, 1279, 'CARDINAL'), (138, 145, 'DISEASE'), (409, 416, 'DISEASE'), (1445, 1452, 'DISEASE'), (1531, 1538, 'DISEASE'), (146, 151, 'DISEASE'), (417, 422, 'DISEASE'), (1539, 1544, 'DISEASE'), (138, 151, 'DISEASE'), (409, 422, 'DISEASE'), (1531, 1544, 'DISEASE'), (1550, 1567, 'DISEASE'), (1202, 1207, 'CASE'), (1280, 1285, 'CASE'), (1426, 1431, 'CASE'), (1331, 1341, 'CHANGE'), (1191, 1198, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "4 dead, 558 downed in typhoid outbreak in Cebu",
    "timestamp": "March 5, 2012 8:04am",
    "content": "At least four people have died in a typhoid outbreak in a town in Cebu province, even as health authorities recommended the installation of water purifiers to stem the spread of the disease. Some 558 people in eight barangays in Tuburan town in Cebu have already fallen ill due to typhoid, radio dzBB's Carlo Mateo reported Monday. The Department of Health was to send a medical team to Tuburan to take a closer look at the situation there, the report said. A separate report by dzBB's Cebu affiliate said the DOH Central Visayas office recommended to the Tuburan government the installation of water purifiers in the affected areas. The Cebu-based report also said local authorities had declared a state of calamity in Tuburan due to the spread of typhoid cases. It cited DOH Region 7 figures indicating at least four had died and more than 500 were affected. Health authorities suspect a contaminated water source may have caused the incidents. They expect test results of blood samples taken from those affected to come out next week. Last weekend, a report on Radyo Mo Nationwide said health authorities in Cebu have declared an outbreak of typhoid fever in Tuburan town following a rise in the number of cases there.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/250311/4-dead-558-downed-in-typhoid-outbreak-in-cebu/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(66, 79, 'GPE'), (229, 241, 'GPE'), (1162, 1174, 'GPE'), (66, 70, 'GPE'), (245, 249, 'GPE'), (486, 490, 'GPE'), (638, 642, 'GPE'), (1111, 1115, 'GPE'), (229, 236, 'GPE'), (387, 394, 'GPE'), (556, 563, 'GPE'), (720, 727, 'GPE'), (1162, 1169, 'GPE'), (514, 529, 'GPE'), (522, 529, 'GPE'), (777, 785, 'GPE'), (58, 62, 'LOC_TYPE'), (237, 241, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1170, 1174, 'LOC_TYPE'), (71, 79, 'LOC_TYPE'), (216, 225, 'LOC_TYPE'), (89, 107, 'ORG'), (861, 879, 'ORG'), (1089, 1107, 'ORG'), (336, 356, 'ORG'), (510, 529, 'ORG'), (564, 574, 'ORG'), (324, 330, 'DATE'), (1027, 1036, 'DATE'), (9, 13, 'CARDINAL'), (814, 818, 'CARDINAL'), (196, 199, 'CARDINAL'), (784, 785, 'CARDINAL'), (842, 845, 'CARDINAL'), (36, 43, 'DISEASE'), (281, 288, 'DISEASE'), (749, 756, 'DISEASE'), (1145, 1152, 'DISEASE'), (1145, 1158, 'DISEASE'), (1153, 1158, 'DISEASE'), (757, 762, 'CASE'), (1209, 1214, 'CASE'), (936, 945, 'CASE'), (44, 52, 'STATE'), (1133, 1141, 'STATE'), (936, 945, 'STATE'), (699, 716, 'STATE'), (168, 174, 'CHANGE'), (739, 745, 'CHANGE'), (1187, 1191, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Man dies in Iloilo City; alert up vs typhoid fever",
    "timestamp": "March 11, 2008 9:59am",
