[
{
    "title": "Tuburan probed for suspected typhoid",
    "timestamp": "March 7, 2015",
    "content": "THE Provincial Health Office (PHO) is looking into a suspected typhoid case in Tuburan, northern Cebu yesterday afternoon. Dr. Cynthia Genosolango, PHO head said they received reports from the municipal health officer of the town that there were five persons confined in the Tuburan District Hospital due to diarrhea. The five suspected typhoid patients are from barangay Kabangkalan, Tuburan, Cebu. Genosolango told Cebu Daily News that their team already went to barangay Kabangkalan to check other suspected victims of typhoid and obtain water samples from the school’s and community’s sources of water. She said the first victim of diarrhea tested positive of amoeba according to the Rural Sanitation Inspector. Genosolango said they consider the case in Tuburan as a new typhoid fever case since the town was hit by a typhoid case March last year. ",
    "url": "http://cebudailynews.inquirer.net/52462/tuburan-probed-for-suspected-typhoid",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(4,34,'ORG'),(63,70,'DISEASE'),(71,75,'CASE'),(79,101,'GPE'),(102,121,'DATE'),(148,151,'ORG'),(225,229,'LOC_TYPE'),(246,250,'CARDINAL'),(275,282,'GPE'),(322,326,'CARDINAL'),(337,344,'DISEASE'),(363,371,'LOC_TYPE'),(372,383,'GPE'),(385,392,'GPE'),(394,398,'GPE'),(417,432,'ORG'),(465,473,'LOC_TYPE'),(474,485,'GPE'),(522,529,'DISEASE'),(589,605,'LOC_TYPE'),(751,755,'CASE'),(759,766,'GPE'),(776,789,'DISEASE'),(790,794,'CASE'),(805,809,'LOC_TYPE'),(823,830,'DISEASE'),(831,835,'CASE'),(836,851,'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Manila team arrives to investigate biggest typhoid wave in C. Visayas",
    "timestamp": "March 08, 2012",
    "content": "Why so many typhoid cases in so short a period in one town? A three-member team of epidemiologists from the Department of Health in Manila arrived in Tuburan, northwest Cebu, to investigate the outbreak of the water-borne disease that neared the 1,000 mark yesterday, making it the highest recorded volume in Central Visayas. “We are here to help not just in controlling the problem but to prevent its reoccurrence,” said Dr. Rowena Capistrano, senior epidemiologist of the National Epidemiological Center (NEC). She said the team would spend 10 days in Tuburan to take samples from patients and water sources in a wider area, testing water supply even in barangays not affected by typhoid. The origin of the contamination and its scope is still not determined. “This is the largest (outbreak) I’ve ever seen. The water system is very vulnerable because there were no chlorinators,” said Renan Cimafranca of the Regional Epidemiological and Surveillance Unit (RESU) of the Department of Health in Central Visayas (DOH-7). What the DOH considers a normal level of typhoid incidence is five cases in a single day for the whole region. Beyond that, it would declare an outbreak. In Tuburan, within a week alone, the RESU recorded 915 typhoid cases, with 139 patients admitted in the Tuburan District Hospital as of yesterday. Four deaths, mostly children, were recorded. Capistrano said the wave of typhoid cases was definitely not related to the Feb. 6 earthquake. Some local officials earlier raised the theory that the powerful quake disturbed water pipes and caused leaks where bacteria could have seeped in. Seven patients from Tuburan town were transported to Vicente Sotto Memorial Medical Center (VSMMC) in Cebu City yesterday, a total of 42 admissions there. But RESU-7 coordinator Cimafranca said the wave of cases is slowing down. “The trend is already to starting to decrease,” he told Cebu Daily News yesterday. He said less than 100 patients were registered in the outpatient department of the Tuburan District Hospital with less than 50 patients admitted. In Cebu province and Central Visayas, Tuburan has recorded the highest incidence of typhoid. He said RESU recorded 600 cases of typhoid fever in Alegria town, southwest Cebu with 36 patients admitted early last year. The 25-bed Tuburan District Hospital has been crammed with patients since Saturday. Hospital chief Dr. Esteban Ligaray said they set up additional beds in the hallways while the staff offices and conference rooms were converted into wards. Ligaray said the situation is under control with assistance from the DOH-7 and the Provincial Health Office. They have enough medicine and supplies to treat patients, he said. Patients are given antibiotics like chloramphenicol and contrimoxazole. The NEC team from Manila came with five doctors from the East Avenue Medical Center and the San Lazaro Hospital in Manila. Dr. Capistrano said the team will verify other suspected typhoid cases, determine the risk factors in the community and make recommendations to the Tuburan municipal government. “We will not leave until we establish the proper monitoring of cases in the area. Our main concern is the investigation,” she said. Patients must be regularly monitored for 14 days to one month, the duration of the disease. Typhoid fever is caused by the parasite called Salmonella typhi, which can be found in contaminated food or water. Capistrano said the simplest solution is to chlorinate the water supply and boil drinking water. “People should observe proper hygiene practices like washing hands regularly,” she added. Symptoms of typhoid fever are continuous fever up to one week, headache, abdominal pain, diarrhea, skin rashes, jaundice and, in extreme cases, psychosis. Cebu Gov. Gwendolyn Garcia will visit Tuburan town today to distribute relief aid in the town’s gym. She said the medicine and services in the hospital are free and that each affected household will receive 10 kilos of rice. ",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/157957/manila-team-arrives-to-investigate-biggest-typhoid-wave-in-c-visayas",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(12,19,'DISEASE'),(682,689,'DISEASE'), (1063, 1070,'DISEASE'), (1231, 1238,'DISEASE'), (1396,1403,'DISEASE'), (2152, 2159,'DISEASE'), (2953, 2960,'DISEASE'), (20, 25,'CASE'), (1089, 1094,'CASE'), (1239, 1244,'CASE'), (1404, 1409,'CASE'), (1816, 1821,'CASE'), (2187, 2192,'CASE'), (2961, 2966,'CASE'), (3137, 3142,'CASE'), (3737, 3742,'CASE'), (50, 53,'CARDINAL'), (3258, 3261,'CARDINAL'), (3653, 3656,'CARDINAL'), (54, 58,'LOC_TYPE'), (1638, 1642,'LOC_TYPE'), (2221, 2225,'LOC_TYPE'), (3801, 3805,'LOC_TYPE'), (3844, 3848,'LOC_TYPE'), (108, 128,'ORG'), (973, 993,'ORG'), (132, 138,'GPE'), (2791, 2797,'GPE'), (2888, 2894,'GPE'), (150, 173,'GPE'), (194, 202,'STATE'), (1166, 1174,'STATE'), (246, 251,'CARDINAL'), (257, 266,'DATE'), (1312, 1321,'DATE'), (1722, 1731,'DATE'), (1911, 1920,'DATE'), (309, 324,'GPE'), (997, 1012,'GPE'), (2089, 2104,'GPE'), (543, 545,'CARDINAL'), (1940, 1942,'CARDINAL'), (3962, 3964,'CARDINAL'), (150, 157,'GPE'), (554, 561,'GPE'), (1179, 1186,'GPE'), (1280, 1287,'GPE'), (1630, 1637,'GPE'), (2005, 2012,'GPE'), (2106, 2113,'GPE'), (2296, 2303,'GPE'), (3044, 3051,'GPE'), (3793, 3800,'GPE'), (596, 609,'LOC_TYPE'), (656, 665,'LOC_TYPE'), (194, 202,'STATE'), (1166, 1174,'STATE'), (912, 958,'ORG'), (973, 1020,'ORG'), (1014, 1017,'ORG'), (1031, 1034,'ORG'), (2594, 2597,'ORG'), (1084, 1088,'CARDINAL'), (2808, 2812,'CARDINAL'), (1100, 1110,'DATE'), (960, 964,'ORG'), (1213, 1217,'ORG'), (1769, 1773,'ORG'), (2169, 2173,'ORG'), (1227, 1230,'CARDINAL'), (1251, 1254,'CARDINAL'), (1323, 1327,'CARDINAL'), (1444, 1450,'DATE'), (1712, 1721,'GPE'), (1744, 1746,'CARDINAL'), (1769, 1775,'ORG'), (1876, 1884,'CHANGE'), (1895, 1910,'ORG'), (1930, 1943,'CARDINAL'), (2036, 2048,'CARDINAL'), (2071, 2084,'GPE'), (2183, 2186,'CARDINAL'), (2247, 2249,'CARDINAL'), (2268, 2283,'DATE'), (2359, 2367,'DATE'), (2608, 2632,'ORG'), (507, 510,'ORG'), (2777, 2780,'ORG'), (2830, 2856,'ORG'), (2865, 2884,'ORG'), (3247, 3267,'DATE'), (2196, 2209,'DISEASE'), (3298, 3311,'DISEASE'), (3612, 3625,'DISEASE'), (3653, 3661,'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Five more Toledo residents show typhoid fever type symptoms",
    "timestamp": "March 15, 2015",
    "content": "Five more residents of Subayon, Toledo were brought to the Toledo City Hospital after showing symptoms associated with typhoid fever. Subayon barangay chairman Florante Lariba said the five residents raised the number of patients showing similar symptoms to 28. The youngest patient is a two-month old daughter of resident Robert Gomez while the oldest is a woman in her 40s. The Provincial Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit (PESU) and the Regional Epidemiology Surveillance Unit (RESU) are continually monitoring the patients who were given IVs. Five gallons of mineral water were given to 15 households in barangay Subayon. The Toledo City government will extend medical assistance from its calamity fund tomorrow.",
    "url": "http://cebudailynews.inquirer.net/53076/five-more-toledo-residents-show-typhoid-fever-type-symptoms",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 4,'CARDINAL'), (185, 189,'CARDINAL'), (548, 552,'CARDINAL'), (23, 30,'GPE'), (134, 141,'GPE'), (618, 625,'GPE'), (32, 38,'GPE'), (59, 65,'GPE'), (631, 637,'GPE'), (119, 132,'DISEASE'), (142, 150,'LOC_TYPE'), (609, 617,'LOC_TYPE'), (211, 217,'CASE'), (258, 260,'CARDINAL'), (380, 432,'ORG'), (441, 487,'ORG'), (592, 594,'CARDINAL'), (708, 716,'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Typhoid claims lives of 2 Alegria residents",
    "timestamp": "July 22, 2011",
    "content": "Typhoid fever in Alegria town, southern Cebu, has killed two persons. The Department of Health in Central Visayas (DOH-7) confirmed yesterday the death of a 61-year-old man and a 21-year-old woman. Both were residents of Alegria town but died in separate hospitals in Cebu City. Their identities were still awaiting verification through death certificates from the hospitals, said engineer Noel Esparagoza, DOH-7 hospital maintenance and service division chief. The 64-year-old man died while he was being brought to a private hospital in Cebu City from Reinhard Wirtgen Memorial Hospital in Alegria while the woman died at the Vicente Sotto Memorial Medical Center after she was moved from Badian District Hospital on July 16. Esparagoza said the two hospitals confirmed typhoid fever as the cause of death. Salmonella bacteria, which causes typhoid fever, was detected in their blood tests. Esparagoza said the woman came from the mountain barangay of Compostela. The man’s home barangay was not yet verified. The DOH recorded 142 typhoid patients as of July 21. He said 14 patients are still admitted at the Badian District Hospital while all the other patients in Reinhard were already discharged. “The situation has already calmed down, but we should not be complacent and observe proper hygiene at home,” Esparagoza said. He said the typhoid cases were already confirmed through blood samples taken from 16 patients, seven of which tested positive with salmonella in their bloodstream. He said the health department would still wait for the water results expected today to confirm if the water system of the municipality was contaminated. The Regional Epidemiological and Surveillance Unit (Resu-7) recommended the installation of an automatic chlorinator to the water system in Alegria last December after a typhoid outbreak affected around 750 patients. Esparagoza said that if the water samples would show contamination, he said that they would assess the measures taken by the local government unit to assure the safety the town’s water source. If proven that the LGU didn’t follow the provision on the sanitation code on maintaining the safety of the water system, then he said that the LGU should be sanctioned.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/27553/typhoid-claims-lives-of-2-alegria-residents",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 13,'DISEASE'), (772, 785,'DISEASE'), (843, 856,'DISEASE'), (17, 44,'GPE'), (57, 60,'CARDINAL'), (748, 751,'CARDINAL'), (74,121,'ORG'),(132, 141,'DATE'), (221, 233,'GPE'), (268, 277,'GPE'), (539, 548,'GPE'), (115, 120,'ORG'), (407, 412,'ORG'), (592, 599,'GPE'), (1785, 1792,'GPE'), (691, 697,'GPE'), (1111, 1117,'GPE'), (719, 726,'DATE'), (933, 950,'LOC_TYPE'), (954, 964,'GPE'), (981, 989,'LOC_TYPE'), (1016, 1019,'ORG'),(1029, 1032,'CARDINAL'), (1033, 1040,'DISEASE'), (1340, 1347,'DISEASE'), (1815, 1822,'DISEASE'), (1056, 1063,'DATE'), (1029, 1031,'CARDINAL'), (1073, 1075,'CARDINAL'), (554, 562,'GPE'), (1168, 1176,'GPE'), (1348, 1353,'CASE'), (724, 726,'CARDINAL'), (1410, 1412,'CARDINAL'), (1423, 1428,'CARDINAL'), (1614, 1626,'LOC_TYPE'), (1649,1704,'ORG'),(1793, 1806,'DATE'), (1823, 1831,'STATE'), (1848, 1851,'CARDINAL'), (2041, 2053,'LOC_TYPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Typhoid kills 3, downs 24 in Tuburan",
    "timestamp": "March 04, 2012",
    "content": "THREE persons were reported dead while at least 24 others were hospitalized for drinking unclean ground water extracted from three barangays in Tuburan town, midwest Cebu. Renan Cimafranca, head of the Regional Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit of the Central Visayas Office of the Department of Health (DOH), said in an interview with radio dyAB that the three casualties were from barangays Poblacion, Cogon and Bagasawe. The victims died at the Tuburan District Hospital. Cimafranca said  about 300 other residents of the two barangays are suspected to also have typhoid and are now placed under observation. He said health officials suspect that unclean water caused the typhoid outbreak in the second-class municipality.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/155915/typhoid-kills-3-downs-24-in-tuburan",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 5,'CARDINAL'), (125, 130,'CARDINAL'), (357, 362,'CARDINAL'), (48, 50,'CARDINAL'), (131, 140,'LOC_TYPE'), (384, 393,'LOC_TYPE'), (530, 539,'LOC_TYPE'), (144, 170,'GPE'), (202, 309,'ORG'), (337, 347,'ORG'), (394, 403,'GPE'), (405, 410,'GPE'), (415, 423,'GPE'), (449, 456,'GPE'), (499, 502,'CARDINAL'), (526, 529,'CARDINAL'), (567, 574,'DISEASE'), (676, 683,'DISEASE'), (684, 692,'STATE'), (713, 725,'LOC_TYPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Typhoid cases slow down in Tuburan",
    "timestamp": "March 11, 2012",
    "content": "Typhoid  fever cases reached the 1,000 mark, but health authorities said  the rate of is declining  as more patients are discharged from Tuburan’s district hospital. Dr. Expedito Medalla, health and emergency management staff coordinator of the Department of health in Central Visayas (DOH-7), said outpatient admissions went down in the hospital since Wednesday. “The cases are down trending,” he said. Since yesterday, they recorded 1,089 suspected cases of typhoid fever in Tuburan. Five patients have died since the outbreak was  declared last week.  At least  213 cases alone were recorded in Tuburan District Hospital. Medalla said they already discharged 102 patients since yesterday. Results of stool, blood sample and water testing  are expected next week. A three-member team of epidemiologists from the DOH Manila office arrived in Tuburan last Wednesday to investigate the cause of the outbreak. The team took samples  samples from patients and water sources in a wider area, testing water supply even in barangays not affected by typhoid. The 25-bed Tuburan District Hospital has been crammed with patients since Saturday. NEC senior epidemiologist Dr. Rowena Capistrano said patients must be regularly monitored for 14 days to one month, the duration of the disease. The town’s municipal water system is fed by springs but lacked chlorine treatment. Chlorinators were installed only after the outbreak was declared. Typhoid fever is caused by the parasite called Salmonella typhi, which can be found in contaminated food or water.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/159515/typhoid-cases-slow-down-in-tuburan",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 14,'DISEASE'),(460, 473,'DISEASE'), (1430, 1443,'DISEASE'), (15, 20,'CASE'), (369, 374,'CASE'), (451, 456,'CASE'), (569, 574,'CASE'), (33, 38,'CARDINAL'), (89, 98,'CHANGE'), (137, 144,'GPE'), (477, 484,'GPE'), (598, 605,'GPE'), (843, 850,'GPE'), (1063, 1070,'GPE'), (245, 292,'ORG'), (353, 362,'DATE'), (856, 865,'DATE'), (379, 392,'CHANGE'), (410, 419,'DATE'), (681, 690,'DATE'), (435, 440,'CARDINAL'), (486, 490,'CARDINAL'), (662, 665,'CARDINAL'), (755, 764,'DATE'), (814, 824,'ORG'), (520, 528,'STATE'), (898, 906,'STATE'), (1407, 1415,'STATE'), (957, 970,'LOC_TYPE'), (1017, 1026,'LOC_TYPE'), (1043, 1050,'DISEASE'), (1056, 1062,'CARDINAL'), (1126, 1134,'DATE'), (1136, 1139,'ORG'), (1230, 1250,'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Typhoid outbreak kills 4 in Cebu town",
    "timestamp": "March 05, 2012",
    "content": "Four people have died from typhoid fever while over 600 other cases have been reported in Tuburan town in Cebu, the top provincial health official said. Almost all of the 54 villages of Tuburan, 96.7 kilometers northwest of Cebu City, were affected by the typhoid outbreak, the town’s mayor, Democrito Diamante, said in an interview yesterday. The municipal council declared a state of calamity on Friday so it could use its calamity fund to provide medical attention to the stricken residents. Dr. Cristina Giango, chief of the Integrated Provincial Health Office, said in a press conference that 646 cases of the water-borne disease were reported by hospitals. At Tuburan District Hospital, 109 were admitted while Vicente Sotto Memorial Medical Center in Cebu City had 14 other patients. Giango said she had already sent two doctors and nine nurses to help the medical staff of Tuburan District Hospital. Diamante said he and the health officials believed that the outbreak was caused by water contamination after last month’s 6.9-magnitude earthquake, which might have damaged water pipes. Eight of the villages have the same water source of water, the mayor said. Diamante said he had ordered the chlorination of all five water sources of the municipality and urged residents to boil their drinking water. He said bottled water had been sent to schools so students would not drink water from the faucets. Interior Secretary Jesse Robredo, who was in Cebu yesterday, pledged to give P10 million for the rehabilitation of the water system, Diamante said. He said a master plan was being prepared and expected to be finished within a month. Governor Gwendolyn Garcia sent the Water Task Force from the Provincial Planning and Development Office to Tuburan to check the pipelines. She also promised to extend P5,000 assistance to each family of the victims who had died from typhoid fever.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/156613/typhoid-outbreak-kills-4-in-cebu-town",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 4,'CARDINAL'), (27, 40,'DISEASE'), (1876, 1889,'DISEASE'), (52, 55,'CARDINAL'), (62, 67,'CASE'), (602, 607,'CASE'), (90, 97,'GPE'), (186, 193,'GPE'), (666, 673,'GPE'), (881, 888,'GPE'), (1750, 1757,'GPE'), (98, 102,'LOC_TYPE'), (278, 282,'LOC_TYPE'), (106, 110,'GPE'), (224, 228,'GPE'), (758, 762,'GPE'), (1455, 1459,'GPE'), (171, 173,'CARDINAL'), (174, 182,'LOC_TYPE'), (1107, 1115,'LOC_TYPE'), (195, 199,'CARDINAL'), (229, 233,'LOC_TYPE'), (763, 767,'LOC_TYPE'), (256, 263,'DISEASE'), (264, 272,'STATE'), (968, 976,'STATE'), (377, 394,'STATE'), (398, 404,'DATE'), (529, 564,'ORG'), (598, 601,'CARDINAL'), (693, 696,'CARDINAL'), (772, 774,'CARDINAL'), (824, 827,'CARDINAL'), (840, 844,'CARDINAL'), (1017, 1027,'DATE'),(1094, 1099,'CARDINAL'), (1130, 1142,'LOC_TYPE'), (1227, 1239,'LOC_TYPE'), (1222, 1226,'CARDINAL'), (333, 342,'DATE'), (1460, 1469,'DATE'), (1636, 1641,'DATE'), (1678, 1694,'ORG'), (1704, 1746,'ORG')]"
}
]