[
{
    "title": "77 downed in Quezon; typhoid fever eyed – DOH",
    "timestamp": "November 17, 2008 12:52pm",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines – The Health Department on Monday said at least 77 residents from Real and Infanta towns in Quezon province were downed by a still undetermined illness, although victims displayed symptoms of typhoid fever.In a telephone interview with GMANews.TV, DOH-National Epidemiology Center head Dr. Eric Tayag said the suspected typhoid fever cases were monitored by the local Center for Health and Development since Friday last week. “So far, we have 77 (victims). We are still waiting for the update from my epidemiology team in the area,“ Tayag said. He added that they have collected drinking water samples to determine the cause of their illness. Test results are expected to be out after three to five days. In a separate interview with QTV Balitanghali anchor Raffy Tima, Tayag expressed fears that more victims may succumb to the illness, saying that they have yet to determine the source of the contaminated water. “Inaasahan pa naming tataaas pa yan hangga’t hindi pa natutukoy ang pinagmumulan ng kontaminasyon ng tubig (We expect the number of cases to rise until we haven’t figured where the contamination of the water was coming from),“ Tayag said. In the telephone interview, Tayag said they have employed precautionary measures to prevent the number of cases from rising. “We are treating the patients immediately who will likely be affected. We are also teaching them (residents) to boil their water first,“ Tayag said. Tayag said that symptoms of the water-borne illness include prolonged fever, stomach pains and irregular bowel movement.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/133958/77-downed-in-quezon-typhoid-fever-eyed-doh/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (112, 127, 'GPE'), (86, 90, 'GPE'), (95, 102, 'GPE'), (103, 108, 'LOC_TYPE'), (119, 127, 'LOC_TYPE'), (26, 43, 'ORG'), (268, 300, 'ORG'), (382, 421, 'ORG'), (47, 53, 'DATE'), (428, 444, 'DATE'), (428, 434, 'DATE'), (435, 444, 'DATE'), (68, 70, 'CARDINAL'), (463, 465, 'CARDINAL'), (705, 710, 'CARDINAL'), (714, 718, 'CARDINAL'), (212, 219, 'DISEASE'), (340, 347, 'DISEASE'), (220, 225, 'DISEASE'), (348, 353, 'DISEASE'), (1518, 1523, 'DISEASE'), (212, 225, 'DISEASE'), (340, 353, 'DISEASE'), (330, 353, 'DISEASE'), (354, 359, 'CASE'), (1067, 1072, 'CASE'), (1280, 1285, 'CASE'), (1116, 1129, 'STATE'), (1291, 1297, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Cebu officials claim typhoid outbreak under control",
    "timestamp": "March 3, 2013 6:11am",
    "content": "A report on Radyo Mo Nationwide said this was the gist of a report by Integrated Provincial Health Office chief Dr. Cristina Giango to acting Cebu Governor Agnes Magpale. The RMN report said at least 31 people were affected by typhoid, two of them being reported on Thursday. It said her initial report pointed to a contaminated water source in some areas in the town. The local government of Badian is now planning to send water purification facilities to the affected areas, the report said. Last Wednesday, a report by radio dzBB's Cebu affiliate Orchids Lapincao said health authorities in Cebu are testing the water supply of Badian after some of its residents were downed by typhoid fever. Giango also reminded residents to boil their drinking water. The United States' National Library of Medicine defined typhoid fever as an infection that causes diarrhea and a rash, and is commonly caused by the Salmonella typhi (S. typhi) bacteria. It said such bacteria can spread through contaminated food, drink, or water, and can travel into intestines, and then into the our bloodstream. Early symptoms of the disease include fever, general ill feeling, and abdominal pain. More extreme symptoms include high fever and severe diarrhea. Some may even develop a rash called “rose spots,“ or small red spots on the abdomen and chest. Other symptoms include: Abdominal tenderness; Agitation; Bloody stool; Chills; Confusion; Attention deficit; Delirium; Fluctuating mood; Hallucinations; Nosebleeds; Severe fatigue; Slow, sluggish, lethargic feeling; Weakness",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/297451/cebu-officials-claim-typhoid-outbreak-under-control/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(142, 146, 'GPE'), (535, 539, 'GPE'), (594, 598, 'GPE'), (393, 399, 'GPE'), (631, 637, 'GPE'), (363, 367, 'LOC_TYPE'), (70, 105, 'ORG'), (266, 274, 'DATE'), (494, 508, 'DATE'), (200, 202, 'CARDINAL'), (236, 239, 'CARDINAL'), (681, 694, 'DISEASE'), (813, 826, 'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "1 dies as typhoid outbreak hits Iloilo waterfront villages",
    "timestamp": "March 7, 2008 5:46pm",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines - At least one resident was confirmed dead as a typhoid outbreak hit waterfront villages in Iloilo City since late February, an online report said Friday. The News Today reported that this prompted city Mayor Jerry Treñas to direct all village captains in the city to monitor and report any typhoid case in their respective areas. Initial reports showed at least one of the victims, 35-year-old Roberto Jusayan of Veterans Village, died last Feb. 28. The city health office also noted some unreported cases in Concepcion and Gen. Hughes villages. Because of the unreported cases, the mayor's office could not immediately release the number of typhoid victims. On the other hand, Treñas also instructed Inspector Dande Deocampo of the Waterfront Detachment police to help village workers in identifying and monitoring all the victims of typhoid fever. The city government also coordinated with the Metro Iloilo Water District (MIWD) to check their pipes that may have leaks and contaminate residents' source of drinking water. Also, Treñas urged residents to be wary of street foods.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/83799/1-dies-as-typhoid-outbreak-hits-iloilo-waterfront-villages/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (112, 123, 'GPE'), (434, 450, 'GPE'), (530, 540, 'GPE'), (545, 556, 'GPE'), (112, 118, 'GPE'), (923, 929, 'GPE'), (100, 108, 'LOC_TYPE'), (557, 565, 'LOC_TYPE'), (119, 123, 'LOC_TYPE'), (218, 222, 'LOC_TYPE'), (280, 284, 'LOC_TYPE'), (475, 479, 'LOC_TYPE'), (875, 879, 'LOC_TYPE'), (100, 107, 'LOC_TYPE'), (256, 263, 'LOC_TYPE'), (443, 450, 'LOC_TYPE'), (557, 564, 'LOC_TYPE'), (791, 798, 'LOC_TYPE'), (475, 493, 'ORG'), (604, 618, 'ORG'), (754, 782, 'ORG'), (917, 951, 'ORG'), (130, 143, 'DATE'), (457, 469, 'DATE'), (31, 34, 'CARDINAL'), (383, 386, 'CARDINAL'), (68, 75, 'DISEASE'), (311, 318, 'DISEASE'), (663, 670, 'DISEASE'), (856, 863, 'DISEASE'), (856, 869, 'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "5 Cebu residents monitored for typhoid fever; water sources tested",
    "timestamp": "February 27, 2013 9:01am",
    "content": "Health authorities are testing the water supply of Badian town in Cebu after at least five of its residents were downed by typhoid fever. Integrated Provincial Health Office head Dr. Cristina Giango was quoted early Wednesday by Orchids Lapincao of dzBB-Cebu as saying they are verifying information that the five may have acquired the typhoid fever through contaminated food or water. Provincial health teams have taken samples from water supplies and sources in the town to see if there is bacteria, the dzBB report said. In the meantime, Giango reminded residents to boil their drinking water. The United States National Library of Medicine defined typhoid fever as an infection that causes diarrhea and a rash, and is commonly caused by the Salmonella typhi (S. typhi) bacteria. It said such bacteria can spread through contaminated food, drink, or water, and can travel into intestines, and then into the our bloodstream. Early symptoms of the disease include fever, general ill feeling, and abdominal pain. More extreme symptoms include high fever and severe diarrhea. Some may even develop a rash called “rose spots,“ or small red spots on the abdomen and chest. Other symptoms include: Abdominal tenderness; Agitation; Bloody stool; Chills; Confusion; Attention deficit; Delirium; Fluctuating mood; Hallucinations; Nosebleeds; Severe fatigue; Slow, sluggish, lethargic feeling; Weakness",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/296848/5-cebu-residents-monitored-for-typhoid-fever-water-sources-tested/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(51, 62, 'GPE'), (66, 70, 'GPE'), (149, 173, 'ORG'), (210, 225, 'DATE'), (86, 90, 'CARDINAL'), (309, 313, 'CARDINAL'), (123, 136, 'DISEASE'), (336, 349, 'DISEASE'), (652, 665, 'DISEASE'), (809, 815, CHANGE)]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue, typhoid cases rising in Samar towns",
    "timestamp": "July 2, 2008 12:50am",
    "content": "TACLOBAN CITY, Philippines - Dengue has killed two people and downed 40 others in the island-town of Daram, Samar, while typhoid fever victims in Villareal town has risen to 69 this week with one death. Both municipalities have no doctors. Boyd Cerro, Department of Health (DOH) regional sentinel nurse, said the case in Barangay Buenavista, Daram town has reached an alarming level as it takes weeks before residents report the illness. Reports reaching the provincial health office said two patients have died. Meanwhile, the number of typhoid fever victims in the village of Igot, Villareal town went up to 69 this week from 43 cases recorded by the DOH regional office last week. The report said the villages' shallow wells triggered the outbreak. The system is the main source of potable water for the residents.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/104453/dengue-typhoid-cases-rising-in-samar-towns/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 13, 'GPE'), (15, 26, 'GPE'), (101, 113, 'GPE'), (321, 340, 'GPE'), (578, 598, 'GPE'), (86, 97, 'LOC_TYPE'), (208, 222, 'LOC_TYPE'), (321, 329, 'LOC_TYPE'), (567, 574, 'LOC_TYPE'), (704, 712, 'LOC_TYPE'), (704, 711, 'LOC_TYPE'), (252, 278, 'ORG'), (459, 483, 'ORG'), (653, 672, 'ORG'), (177, 186, 'DATE'), (613, 622, 'DATE'), (673, 682, 'DATE'), (47, 50, 'CARDINAL'), (489, 492, 'CARDINAL'), (69, 71, 'CARDINAL'), (174, 176, 'CARDINAL'), (610, 612, 'CARDINAL'), (192, 195, 'CARDINAL'), (174, 176, 'CARDINAL'), (610, 612, 'CARDINAL'), (628, 630, 'CARDINAL'), (121, 134, DISEASE), (538, 551, DISEASE), (313, 317, 'CASE'), (631, 635, 'CASE'), (631, 636, 'CASE'), (599, 606, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "DOH dispatches team to Calamba vs typhoid fever",
    "timestamp": "March 3, 2008 11:22am",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines - The Department of Health on Monday said that it has dispatched a probe team to Calamba City in Laguna in bid to contain the outbreak of typhoid fever in the area. Dr. Eric Tayag, head of the DOH-National Epidemiology Center, said the team will try to determine the causes of the typhoid fever which had already downed more than a thousand people in the area.  “Parating na ang mga bagong gamot. Titignan natin kung ano ang gagawin para hindi ganun kadami ang naoospital,“ he also said. He said the DOH received report from the Calamba City Health Office that at least 1,262 Calamba residents were downed by the disease since January this year. Of the number, 752 patients were from the villages of Singko (5), Lecheria, Halang, Bucal, Pansol and La Mesa. Tayag said 27 of the patients were found positive with the bacteria Salmonella typhi which causes typhoid fever while 200 others were being observed in the hospitals. He said the DOH will still verify the data provided by the Calamba Health Office. He said no death was reported yet but he confirmed that typhoid fever is a deadly disease. He said typhoid fever may affect the brain or typhoid psychosis. Tayag also urged the Calamba city government to distribute chlorinated water to the residents. He asked the residents to let their drinking water boil for two to three minutes to kill the bacteria. However, he said this is not enough as the residents should also use chlorinated water in cooking their food.  He added personal hygiene such as frequent hand washing is important to prevent spread of disease. The health official said they have already declared an outbreak of typhoid fever in Calamba even before the number of patients rose.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/83083/doh-dispatches-team-to-calamba-vs-typhoid-fever/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 6, 'GPE'), (8, 19, 'GPE'), (101, 113, 'GPE'), (549, 561, 'GPE'), (1203, 1215, 'GPE'), (117, 123, 'GPE'), (720, 726, 'GPE'), (732, 740, 'GPE'), (742, 748, 'GPE'), (750, 755, 'GPE'), (757, 763, 'GPE'), (768, 775, 'GPE'), (101, 108, 'GPE'), (549, 556, 'GPE'), (596, 603, 'GPE'), (1003, 1010, 'GPE'), (1203, 1210, 'GPE'), (1674, 1681, 'GPE'), (109, 113, 'LOC_TYPE'), (557, 561, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1211, 1215, 'LOC_TYPE'), (26, 46, 'ORG'), (213, 245, 'ORG'), (213, 216, 'ORG'), (520, 523, 'ORG'), (956, 959, 'ORG'), (557, 575, 'ORG'), (562, 575, 'ORG'), (1011, 1024, 'ORG'), (1211, 1226, 'ORG'), (350, 360, 'CARDINAL'), (590, 595, 'CARDINAL'), (681, 684, 'CARDINAL'), (682, 683, 'CARDINAL'), (788, 790, 'CARDINAL'), (895, 898, 'CARDINAL'), (1337, 1340, 'CARDINAL'), (1344, 1349, 'CARDINAL'), (158, 165, 'DISEASE'), (301, 308, 'DISEASE'), (875, 882, 'DISEASE'), (1082, 1089, 'DISEASE'), (1125, 1132, 'DISEASE'), (1163, 1170, 'DISEASE'), (1657, 1664, 'DISEASE'), (166, 171, 'DISEASE'), (309, 314, 'DISEASE'), (883, 888, 'DISEASE'), (1090, 1095, 'DISEASE'), (1133, 1138, 'DISEASE'), (1665, 1670, 'DISEASE'), (158, 171, 'DISEASE'), (301, 314, 'DISEASE'), (875, 888, 'DISEASE'), (1082, 1095, 'DISEASE'), (1125, 1138, 'DISEASE'), (1657, 1670, 'DISEASE'), (146, 154, 'STATE'), (1645, 1653, 'STATE'), (1717, 1721, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Sunstar: Typhoid downs 37 in Zambo",
    "timestamp": "April 12, 2007 8:59am",
    "content": "Typhoid fever is now a threat in Zamboanga City, having recently downed at least 37 residents in a village there, Sun-Star Zamboanga reported Thursday. According to the Sun-Star report, most of the patients are living in Campo Islam village, where the houses are closely built to each other. It said at least five residents of Barangay (village) Mariki were also found to be showing symptoms of typhoid fever. City health officer-in-charge Kiddiya Uddin advised residents showing symptoms of typhoid fever to immediately go to city health centers for medical assistance. Uddin said symptoms of typhoid fever including vomiting and severe stomach pain. According to Uddin, the city government has released suspension medicines with iron supplement to be given to the people who might show symptoms of typhoid fever. Earlier, 20 people were hospitalized after they were downed by typhoid fever. Health officials have taken samples of the drinking water for laboratory tests of the community because it might be contaminated and the source of the sickness.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/37964/sunstar-typhoid-downs-37-in-zambo/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(33, 47, 'GPE'), (221, 240, 'GPE'), (327, 352, 'GPE'), (43, 47, 'LOC_TYPE'), (410, 414, 'LOC_TYPE'), (527, 531, 'LOC_TYPE'), (676, 680, 'LOC_TYPE'), (99, 106, 'LOC_TYPE'), (233, 240, 'LOC_TYPE'), (327, 335, 'LOC_TYPE'), (676, 691, 'ORG'), (142, 150, 'DATE'), (81, 83, 'CARDINAL'), (309, 313, 'CARDINAL'), (824, 826, 'CARDINAL'), (0, 13, 'DISEASE'), (395, 408, 'DISEASE'), (492, 505, 'DISEASE'), (594, 607, 'DISEASE'), (800, 813, 'DISEASE'), (878, 891, 'DISEASE'), (23, 29, 'STATE')]"
}
]