[
{
    "title": "Typhoid downs 150 in Samar - DOH",
    "timestamp": "March 18, 2008 9:28am",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines - An outbreak of typhoid cases has downed at least 150 residents in Samar province, even as health authorities are now working to prevent secondary infections there. Eric Tayag, head of the national epidemiology center, said local health workers are now teaching the residents in Alegria village in Zumarraga town on disinfection. “Mahigit 150 na ang nagkasakit, tinuturuan namin ang tao doon mag-disinfection (More than 150 had been taken ill. Our focus is to teach the residents on disinfection),“ Tayag said in an interview on dzBB radio Tuesday. He said the outbreak stemmed from two months of rains, with the surface runoff contaminating the local deep wells from which the residents draw drinking water. Meanwhile, a Chinese Filipino medical team conducted a medical mission in Calamba City in Laguna province Tuesday to treat residents downed by typhoid fever. James Dy, head of the Filipino Chinese Charitable Association that headed the mission, said most of those downed by typhoid were children. “Yung mga malubha dadalhin namin sa Manila (We'll bring the serious cases to Manila),“ he said, referring to his foundation's Chinese General Hospital.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/85276/typhoid-downs-150-in-samar-doh/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 19, 'GPE'), (22, 50, 'STATE'), (71, 74, 'CARDINAL'), (360, 363, 'CARDINAL'), (441, 444, 'CARDINAL'), (88, 102, 'GPE'), (210, 238, 'ORG'), (300, 315, 'GPE'), (319, 333, 'GPE'), (550, 560, 'ORG'), (604, 607, 'CARDINAL'), (804, 816, 'GPE'), (820, 835, 'GPE'), (873, 886, 'DISEASE'), (37, 44, 'DISEASE'), (1004, 1011, 'DISEASE'), (910, 949, 'ORG'), (1063, 1069, 'GPE'), (1104, 1110, 'GPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Typhoid fever downs over 500 in Laguna",
    "timestamp": "March 3, 2008 9:22am",
    "content": "MANILA, Philippines - More than 500 residents in 18 villages in Calamba City in Laguna were hospitalized due to typhoid fever, GMA's Unang Balita reported Monday. The television report said severely affected were villages Pansol and Bucal. Based on the record of Philippine National Red Cross, 504 patients were being treated in nine hospitals in the city as of 10 p.m. Sunday. The PNRC-Laguna chapter said patients downed by typhoid fever started pouring into hospitals February 16. The number of patients doubled last week. “Sa ganitong karaming cases, sa tingin po namin mukhang water ang pinagmulan (ng sakit),“ Dr. Chari Juangco, JP Rizal Memorial Medical Center, told GMA News. At least 157 typhoid patients were being treated at the said hospital which only has a capacity to accommodate 50 patients at a time. The television report said most of the patients at JP Rizal Memorial Medical Center were on the floor due to the hospital's insufficient number of beds. Juangco said they are also having a shortage of medicines and medical supplies. “'Yung IV (intravenous) lines po namin talagang nauubusan po kami, yung suwero, IV fluid, yung ibang medications po namin medyo nagkakaubusan,“ she said. The television report said Department of Health-Region 4 is now conducting test on the water sample from the Calamba Water District.",
    "url": "http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/news/regions/83070/typhoid-fever-downs-over-500-in-laguna/story/",
    "disease": "typhoid",
    "entities": "[(0, 19, 'GPE'), (22, 125, 'CASE'), (127, 130, 'ORG'),(52, 60, 'LOC_TYPE'), (213, 221, 'LOC_TYPE'), (222, 228, 'GPE'), (233, 238, 'GPE'), (263, 292, 'ORG'), (294, 297, 'CARDINAL'), (382, 401, 'ORG'), (484, 514, 'CHANGE'), (635, 667, 'ORG'), (869, 901, 'ORG'), (674, 682, 'ORG'), (684, 696, 'CARDINAL'), (32, 34, 'CARDINAL'), (294, 296, 'CARDINAL'), (795, 797, 'CARDINAL'), (1232, 1261, 'ORG'), (1314, 1336, 'ORG')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases drop in Cordillera",
    "timestamp": "September 10, 2017",
    "content": "THE Department of Health (DOH) in the Cordillera noted a 78-percent decrease in dengue cases in the region. From the 8,311 cases recorded last year, dengue cases went down to 1,852 this year with four deaths compared to 21 in 2016. Kalinga province recorded the highest number of dengue cases with 375 cases followed by Ifugao with 346, Benguet (300), Baguio City (225), Apayao (131) and Mt. Province (34). Baguio City recorded three deaths of the four with one coming from Mt. Province. DOH said males were predominantly affected with 56.7 percent ranging from three to 92 years old. Entomologist Ursula Segundo of DOH-Cordillera said the decrease was supported by the logistics of the Health office to augment needs of local government units using insecticide treated curtains and drum net covers.  With the alarming number of dengue cases in 2016, DOH-Cordillera launched a dengue awareness campaign in every province including Baguio City. Local officials worked on the “action barangay kontra dengue“ which leads to the search and elimination of mosquito breeding sites. Segundo added that source of elimination is the cornerstone of basic dengue prevention adding the DOH are also having interventions for dengue by providing drum net covers in the community. “Karamihan kasi ng breeding site ng lamok ay doon sa drums and in Baguio City last June they launched the Juan Tireless Day kasi gusto nilang alisin iyong mga tires na nagkalat diyan because we would like to eliminate these major breeding sites of aedis mosquitos,“ Segundo explained. Aedes aegypti mosquito is the main vector which transmits the viruses that cause dengue disease. The number of dengue cases peak during the rainy season and may reach to widespread proportion if preventive measures of control are not taken, according to the DOH.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/baguio/local-news/2017/09/11/dengue-cases-drop-cordillera-563335",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0, 48, 'ORG'), (57, 92, 'CHANGE'), (100, 106, 'LOC_TYPE'), (117, 122, 'CARDINAL'), (149, 155, 'DISEASE'), (280, 286, 'DISEASE'), (828, 834, 'DISEASE'), (876, 882, 'DISEASE'), (997, 1003, 'DISEASE'), (1144, 1150, 'DISEASE'), (1211, 1217, 'DISEASE'), (1631, 1637, 'DISEASE'), (1661, 1667, 'DISEASE'), (175, 180, 'CARDINAL'), (196, 200, 'CARDINAL'), (448, 452, 'CARDINAL'), (220, 222, 'CARDINAL'), (232, 248, 'GPE'), (298, 301, 'CARDINAL'), (320, 326, 'GPE'), (332, 335, 'CARDINAL'), (337, 344, 'GPE'), (346, 349, 'CARDINAL'), (352, 363, 'GPE'), (407, 418, 'GPE'), (930, 941, 'GPE'), (1331, 1342, 'GPE'), (365, 368, 'CARDINAL'), (371, 377, 'GPE'), (379, 382, 'CARDINAL'), (388, 400, 'GPE'), (474, 486, 'GPE'), (332, 334, 'CARDINAL'), (428, 433), (562, 567, 'CARDINAL'), (458, 461, 'CARDINAL'), (26, 29, 'ORG'), (488, 491, 'ORG'), (1173, 1176, 'ORG'), (1808, 1811, 'ORG'), (536, 548, 'CARDINAL'), (562, 573, 'CARDINAL'), (616, 630, 'ORG'), (850, 864, 'ORG')]"
},
{
    "title": "Provincial health office: Dengue deaths in NegOcc now 14",
    "timestamp": "August 02, 2017",
    "content": "THE Provincial Health Office (PHO) reported Tuesday, August 1, that that dengues this year in Negros Occidental have reached 14 from January to July this year. The latest death was reported in Barangay Mambulac, Silay City. Deaths were monitored in San Carlos City, with four; Sagay City and Kabankalan City, two each; Escalante City, Victorias City, Bago City, Silay City, Hinigaran and Calatrava, one each. Doctor Ernell Tumimbang, provincial health officer, said that that based on the monitoring of the Dengue Death Review Team, the first four dengue deaths involved patients who acquired dengue for the first time. The Dengue Death Review Team was created to closely study the rise of deaths due to dengue despite that the decrease in the number of cases this year. Tumimbang said they suspect that the victims died of late referral and that the victims may be have been brought to the hospital with severe conditions already.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/bacolod/local-news/2017/08/02/provincial-health-office-dengue-deaths-negocc-now-14-556270",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0, 34, 'ORG'), (53, 61, 'DATE'), (73, 80, 'DISEASE'), (94, 111, 'GPE'), (125, 127, 'CARDINAL'), (128, 148, 'DATE'), (193, 210, 'GPE'), (212, 222, 'GPE'), (362, 372, 'GPE'), (249, 264, 'GPE'), (271, 275, 'CARDINAL'), (543, 547, 'CARDINAL'),(277, 287, 'GPE'), (292, 307, 'GPE'), (309, 312, 'CARDINAL'), (319, 333, 'GPE'), (335, 349, 'GPE'), (351, 360, 'GPE'), (212, 222, 'GPE'), (362, 372, 'GPE'), (374, 383, 'GPE'), (388, 397, 'GPE'), (399, 402, 'CARDINAL'), (507, 531, 'ORG'), (624, 648, 'ORG'), (73, 79, 'DISEASE'), (548, 554, 'DISEASE'), (593, 599, 'DISEASE'), (704, 710, 'DISEASE'), (728, 759, 'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Suspected dengue cases drop by 69% in January to October",
    "timestamp": "October 27, 2017",
    "content": "DENGUE cases in Davao Region dropped significantly to 69 percent, data from the Department of Health Davao showed. From January to October this year, a total of 3,076 cases were reported compared to the same period last year with 10,128 cases. Yasuy Avila, DOH Davao Region Health Education and Promotion Officer, said Friday, October 27, during the Connect press forum at Toryano's Chicken Hauz in SM Lanang Premier that the highest percentage of these cases is in Davao City. For this year Davao City has a total of 1,595 unconfirmed dengue cases; 576 in Davao del Norte; 372 in Compostela Valley; 344 in Davao Oriental; 155 in Davao del Sur; and 34 in Davao Occidental. There were also 23 deaths in the region due to unconfirmed dengue cases. While last year, 4,710 are in Davao City; 1,881 in Davao del Norte; 1,880 in Davao Oriental; 1,206 in Compostela Valley; 360 in Davao del Sur; and 153 in Davao Occidental. A total of 78 deaths were recorded last year. She said unconfirmed cases are those patients who had symptoms of dengue but was not confirmed if they were positive of the illness. “Ito yong mga pasok,(at) reported, hindi pa siya confirm pero pasok siya sa clinical definition ng dengue. But sometimes marami din kasi [factors] as simple as may fever ng two days, may rushes na lumabas pwede na siyang i-clasiffy under dengue though it doesn’t really mean na nagiging positive siya if i-paconfirm na yong blood samples,“ Avila said. She attributed these significant decrease to the continued effort of the health department to reach out to the barangays while empowering barangay officials and capacitating health workers to also go to the grassroots level to raise awareness among communities through their ABKD program or Aksyon Barangay Kontra Dengue (ABKD). The increase last year has also alarmed the communities which triggered them to intensify their campaign at the same time the information, education and communication efforts were escalated to avoid any break out. “If medyo sobrang taas nong case mas nag iintensify mas naaalert yong community so bumababa yong kaso. So pag mababa naman ang kaso nagiging lax na naman ang community despite sa mga programs na binibigay,“ she said.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/davao/local-news/2017/10/27/suspected-dengue-cases-drop-69-january-october-571781",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0, 50, 'CHANGE'), (54, 64, 'CARDINAL'), (161, 166, 'CARDINAL'), (230, 236, 'CARDINAL'), (257, 273, 'ORG'), (327, 337, 'DATE'), (466, 476, 'GPE'), (492, 502, 'GPE'), (776, 786, 'GPE'), (518, 523, 'CARDINAL'), (536, 542, 'DISEASE'), (732, 738, 'DISEASE'), (1030, 1036, 'DISEASE'), (1196, 1202, 'DISEASE'), (1335, 1341, 'DISEASE'), (1763, 1769, 'DISEASE'), (550, 553, 'CARDINAL'), (557, 572, 'GPE'), (797, 812, 'GPE'), (574, 577, 'CARDINAL'), (581, 598, 'GPE'), (848, 865, 'GPE'), (600, 603, 'CARDINAL'), (607, 621, 'GPE'), (823, 837, 'GPE'), (623, 626, 'CARDINAL'), (630, 643, 'GPE'), (874, 887, 'GPE'), (600, 602, 'CARDINAL'), (649, 651, 'CARDINAL'), (655, 671, 'GPE'), (900, 916, 'GPE'), (689, 691, 'CARDINAL'), (22, 28, 'LOC_TYPE'), (706, 712, 'LOC_TYPE'), (763, 768, 'CARDINAL'), (788, 793, 'CARDINAL'), (814, 819, 'CARDINAL'), (839, 844, 'CARDINAL'), (867, 870, 'CARDINAL'), (893, 896, 'CARDINAL'), (929, 931, 'CARDINAL'), (1270, 1273, 'CARDINAL'), (1470, 1490, 'CHANGE'), (1698, 1709, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1822, 1833, 'LOC_TYPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Measles outbreak declared in Davao City",
    "timestamp": "January 22, 2018",
    "content": "DAVAO CITY, Philippines – The local government here declared a measles outbreak as more than 200 people showed signs they were suffering from the highly-contagious infection. Josephine Villafuerte, the city’s chief health officer, said Monday, January 22, that at least 222 people here, not all residents of Davao City, had measles, an infection locally known as tigdas. In pamphlets released by the Department of Health (DOH), tidas is described as a virus that thrives well in the country due to climate change, and that it infects best when temperature levels are low. Symptoms of measles infection include a total-body skin rash, according to the DOH.According to Villafuerte, the figures were a total of people infected between November 2017 up to January of 2018. The declaration of a measles outbreak had to be done, said Villafuerte, to raise the importance of performing imunization operations across the city. “We wanted to avoid the spread of the virus,” she said. Also, it aims to strengthen its efforts to vaccinate children amid a growing reluctance brought by the Dengvaxia scare. DOH XI regional director Abdulla Dumama earlier had to assure the public here that Dengvaxia did not reach the city. The CHO said it is administering immunization and booster of measles vaccine for children between 6 to 59 months. These are done through fixed site, house-to-house, and health center measles immunization, according to the health officer. Last week, there were also some 16 call center workers found positive of the virus. The city has been fighting the spread of measles. In 2014, it became the local government in the region with the most number of measles (apart from dengue) cases in the first three months of 2014, according to the Regional Epidemiology Surveillance Unit of DOH.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/194278-measles-outbreak-declared-in-davao-city",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(0, 23, 'GPE') ,(30, 46, 'ORG'), (1608, 1624, 'ORG'), (63, 79, 'CHANGE'), (83, 96, 'CARDINAL'), (244, 254, 'DATE'), (261, 273, 'CARDINAL'), (308, 318, 'GPE'), (324, 331, 'DISEASE'), (584, 591, 'DISEASE'), (1274, 1281, 'DISEASE'), (1396, 1403, 'DISEASE'), (1576, 1583, 'DISEASE'), (1663, 1670, 'DISEASE'), (363, 369, 'DISEASE'), (400, 426, 'ORG'), (725, 768, 'DATE'), (1096, 1102, 'ORG'), (202, 206, 'LOC_TYPE'), (914, 918, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1207, 1211, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1539, 1543, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1303, 1318, 'CARDINAL'), (1483, 1485, 'CARDINAL'),(1103, 1109, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1632, 1638, 'LOC_TYPE'), (1749, 1755, 'LOC_TYPE'),(1710, 1715, 'CARDINAL'), (651, 654, 'ORG'), (1792, 1795, 'ORG')]"
},
{
    "title": "Davao Region reports 4 deaths in measles outbreak",
    "timestamp": "January 23, 2018",
    "content": "DAVAO CITY, Philippines – The Department of Health (DOH) in Davao Region has appealed to parents to submit their children to government-sponsored measles immunization after it received reports that 4 children had died from the highly-infectious viral disease. Abdullah Dumama, DOH XI director, confirmed the figures on Tuesday, January 23, after Davao City declared a measles outbreak. “Our coverage [of the immunization] is quite low. We’re only hovering at 37% in the whole region,” Dumama told DXRP Radyo ng Bayan. The recorded deaths are from the DOH XI’s list last updated on January 12, according to Dumama. There were 224 cases identified with measles infection, he said, adding that majority of the patients were children. Out of the 224 cases, 119 were not vaccinated, he said. “Many of these were from Davao City, while others were migrants from Marawi,” he said. “Their reasons was that the mother was busy, while others said their children were sick at a time they were due for vaccination, while others just forgot their schedules.” He also pointed out “religious beliefs” as one of the factors the mothers opted not to have their children vaccinated. “We’re asking the public not to turn down these programs because the government is doing its best to eradicate measles,” he appealed over the radio. Davao City's chief health officer said they had to declare an outbreak to raise awareness on the importance of performing immunization operations across the city. The city declared the same outbreak in 2014, with at least 230 people reported to be infected in just 3 months. Locally known as tigdas, the disease is best fought through measles-rubella immnunization, according to DOH. In 2012, the government committed to eliminate the disease in the coutnry, with 3 waves of immunization campaigns conducted in 1998, 2004, and 2007.",
    "url": "https://www.rappler.com/nation/194344-davao-region-deaths-measles-outbreak",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(0, 23, 'GPE'), (30, 56, 'ORG'), (60, 72, 'GPE'), (146, 153, 'DISEASE'), (651, 658, 'DISEASE'), (1276, 1283, 'DISEASE'), (1649, 1656, 'DISEASE'), (198, 199, 'CARDINAL'), (277, 283, 'ORG'), (551, 557, 'ORG'),(328, 338, 'DATE'), (0, 10, 'GPE'), (346, 356, 'GPE'), (812, 822, 'GPE'), (1314, 1324, 'GPE'), (368, 384, 'STATE'), (459, 462, 'CARDINAL'), (476, 482, 'LOC_TYPE'), (497, 516, 'ORG'), (581, 591, 'DATE'), (625, 668, 'CASE'), (742, 745, 'CARDINAL'), (753, 756, 'CARDINAL'), (856, 862, 'GPE'), (1365, 1384, 'STATE'), (1536, 1539, 'CARDINAL'), (337, 338, 'CARDINAL'), (459, 460, 'CARDINAL'), (1579, 1580, 'CARDINAL'), (1778, 1779, 'CARDINAL'), 1693, 1696, 'ORG')]"
}
]