[
{
    "title": "DOH to declare measles outbreak in ARMM",
    "timestamp": "Februar 7, 2018",
    "content": "The Department of Health (DOH) in the Autonomous Region in Muslim Mindanao (ARMM) is set to declare a measles outbreak in the region, an official said Wednesday. Based on government statistics, 14 cases of measles with 6 deaths were recorded in the region from late 2017 to present. The measles cases were all confirmed by serology. Six cases were recorded in Lanao del Sur, while 8 were recorded in Sulu and Maguindanao. “Based on the criteria ng WHO (World Health Organization), isang confirmed case by serology is already considered [an] outbreak dahil mayroon tayong measles elimination for the past years,“ DOH-ARMM Secretary Dr. Kadil Sinolinding Jr. said. For the past years, the data for fully immunized children in ARMM only reached 70%. The health official said this was due to a logistics problem and vaccine availability. “Now, we already initiated mass immunization doon sa mga affected barangays and municipalities and with that, we can be assured na mako-control pa rin natin, but kung hindi kumpleto 'yung immunization ng ating mga anak, may magpositibo pa rin,“ Sinolinding said. DOH-ARMM said it would focus on the prevention of measles cases upon the declaration of the outbreak. Measles is an infectious disease that can cause death among infants as young as 3 months, Sinolinding said. Last month, Davao City declared a measles outbreak after recording 224 suspected measles cases and 4 deaths.",
    "url": "http://news.abs-cbn.com/news/02/07/18/doh-to-declare-measles-outbreak-in-armm",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(4,24,'ORG'),(39,74,'GPE'),(103,109,'DISEASE'),(110,118,'STATE'),(127,132,'LOC_TYPE'),(151,160,'DATE'),(194,195,'CARDINAL'),(196,202,'CASE'),(206,213,'DISEASE'),(219,'CARDINAL'),(250,255,'LOC_TYPE'),(261,281,'DATE'),(288,294,'DISEASE'),(295,300,'CASES'),(333,336,'CARDINAL'),(337,342,'CASES'),(360,373,'GPE'),(381,382,'CARDINAL'),(400,420,'GPE'),(448,478,'ORG'),(487,501,'CASE'),(542,549,'STATE'),(571,578,'DISEASE'),(600,609,'DATE'),(613,620,'ORG'),(664,681,'DATE'),(724,728,'GPE'),(742,745,'PERCENT'),(900,909,'LOC_TYPE'),(914,928,'LOC_TYPE'),(1097,1105,'ORG'),(1148,1155,'DISEASE'),(1156,1160,'CASE'),(1189,1197,'STATE'),(1199,1206,'DISEASE'),(1224,1231,'DISEASE'),(1319,1329,'GPE'),(1342,1357,'STATE'),(1374,1377,'CARDINAL'),(1379,1401,'DISEASE'),(1406,1407,'CARDINAL')]"
},
{
    "title": "Health alert: Measles outbreak declared in Davao City",
    "timestamp": "January 24, 2018",
    "content": "DAVAO CITY — Health officials in the city on Monday declared a measles outbreak after four children died and the number of suspected cases climbed to more than 200. Dr. Josephine Villafuerte, chief of the City Health Office (CHO), however, said only 17 of the suspected cases recorded from November last year to Jan. 12 this year had been confirmed to be measles. Of the confirmed cases, 16 were call center agents who were confined in hospitals last week, she said. Many of those infected with measles, Villafuerte said, were not Davao residents but migrants or transients. Assistant Health Secretary Abdullah Dumama, director of the Department of Health (DOH) in Southern Mindanao region, confirmed the sudden increase in suspected measles cases here, which the DOH said reached 224 cases. He said the rising number of suspected measles cases was a cause for alarm, since deaths had been reported. While the carrier of the measles virus had not been identified, health workers discovered that the low immunization coverage among residents had contributed to the spread of the virus, Dumama said. “Of the 224 cases, we learned that 119 had not been vaccinated,“ Dumama said. He blamed the parents for this health crisis, noting that many of them had cited excuses, like their lack of time, on why they failed to bring their children to health centers for their antimeasles shots. Villafuerte said health workers in the city had vaccinated some 13,000 children, aged 5 months to 5 years, as of Monday as part of the city’s outbreak response immunization operations to prevent the virus from spreading further. She said they also embarked on a massive information campaign, teaching parents how to spot signs of possible infection.",
    "url": "http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/963055/health-alert-measles-outbreak-declared-in-davao-city",
    "disease": "measles",
    "entities": "[(0,10,'GPE'),(37,41,'LOC_TYPE'),(45,51,'DATE'),(63,79,'STATE'),(133,138,'CASE'),(160,162,'CARDINAL'),(200,229,'ORG'),(250,252,'CARIDNAL'),(260,275,'CASE'),(290,329,'DATE'),(355,362,'DISEASE'),(531,536,'GPE'),(635,661,'ORG'),(665,689,'GPE'),(724,747,'CASE'),(764,767,'ORG'),(781,784,'CARDINAL'),(785,790,'CASE'),(804,844,'CHANGE'),(1106,1109,'CARDINAL'),(1110,1115,'CASE'),(1208,1220,'STATE'),(1420,1424,'LOC_TYPE'),(1445,1451,'CARIDNAL'),(1467,1468,'CARDINAL'),(1479,1480,'CARDINAL'),(1494,1500,'DATE'),(1523,1531,'CASE')]"
},	
{
    "title": "DOH: No basis for for declaring dengue outbreak in Cebu",
    "timestamp": "October 13, 2016",
    "content": "Cebu City (CNN Philippines) — Is there really a dengue outbreak in Cebu? The Department of Health (DOH) in Central Visayas sees no basis for declaring an outbreak yet. But on Monday, the Cebu provincial government officially declared a province-wide dengue outbreak. The move was recommended by the provincial health office, which reported that dengue cases have increased by more than 100 percent. Renan Cimafranca, chief of the Regional Epidemiology and Surveillance Unit (RESU), said the provincial health office might have analyzed their data differently. He added they might have other reasons to declare an outbreak. But as far as DOH standards are concerned, the number of cases in Cebu Province does not fall into the outbreak category. The DOH also has not recommended areas of concern to the provincial government. As for Cebu City, the local government declared a state of calamity on Tuesday, following the recommendation of the city health office. With the declaration, the city hall will now have access to calamity funds. Cimafranca, however, said they only recommended declaring an outbreak in four out of the 81 barangays up for review, since these areas are already experiencing “epidemic proportions“ of dengue. These barangays are Guadalupe, Labangon, Lahug, and Barrio Luz. Cimafranca said the DOH cannot prevent both governments from declaring outbreaks in their areas of jurisdiction. He said the purpose of declaring an outbreak is to primarily inform the public about the actual dengue situation in a certain area. More dengue cases RESU data from January to October 8, 2016 shows 17,128 cases with 136 deaths in the provinces of Cebu, Bohol, and Siquijor. No data came from Negros Oriental yet. These are 124 percent higher than the data from 2015. Cebu City, the biggest urban area in the region, listed 2,256 cases including 13 deaths from January 1 to October 8 this year. It only had 1,359 with 11 deaths last year. Blood supply problem? The Cebu provincial health office has maintained its stance recommending a province-wide outbreak of dengue with 5,500 cases listed this year compared to the 2,500 cases last year. Health office chief Rene Catan said they have the authority to declare an outbreak, since the Health Department has already devolved the functions to them. Catan also said that some of the deaths in the province were due to the lack of blood supply. Cebu will look into projects to solve this as part of its anti-dengue measures. But DOH dengue program coordinator Ronald Jarvic Buscato said blood supply problems and dengue deaths have no correlation. He said blood transfusion only occurs in rare cases. He said the deaths are mainly caused by late referrals of patients. Buscato also warned that mosquito misting, usually seen as a preventive measure for dengue, is ineffective and expensive. He said the public should instead practice the search and destroy method, by looking for possible breeding grounds of mosquito carriers, such as stagnant water in containers.",
    "url": "http://cnnphilippines.com/regional/2016/10/13/doh-no-basis-cebu-dengue-outbreak.html",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,9,'GPE'),(11,26,'ORG'),(48,54,DISEASE),(55,63,'STATE'),(67,71,'GPE'),(73,97,'ORG'),(108,122,GPE),(155,162,'STATE'),(175,181,'DATE'),(187,213,'ORG'),(236,244,'LOC_TYPE'),(250,256,'DISEASE'),(257,265,'STATE'),(299,323,'ORG'),(345,351,'DISEASE'),(352,357,'STATE'),(363,372,'CHANGE'),(386,397,'PERCENT'),(431,473,'ORG'),(492,515,'ORG'),(613,621,'STATE'),(637,640,'DOH'),(680,685,'CASE'),(689,702,'GPE'),(726,734,'STATE'),(749,752,'ORG'),(802,823,'ORG'),(832,841,'GPE'),(847,863,'ORG'),(875,892,'STATE'),(897,903,'DATE'),(941,959,'ORG'),(1098,1106,'STATE'),(1129,1138,'LOC_TYPE'),(1223,1229,'DISEASE'),(1237,1246,'LOC_TYPE'),(1251,1260,'GPE'),(1262,1270,'GPE'),(1272,1277,'GPE'),(1283,1293,'GPE'),(1315,1318,'ORG'),(1339,1350,'ORG'),(1366,1375,'STATE'),(1444,1452,'STATE'),(1505,1510,'DISEASE'),(1545,1551,'DISEASE'),(1552,1557,'CASE'),(1558,1562,'ORG'),(1573,1599,'DATE'),(1606,1612,'CARDINAL'),(1613,1618,'CASE'),(1624,1627,'CARDINAL'),(1642,1651,'LOC_TYPE'),(1655,1659,'GPE'),(1661,1666,'GPE'),(1672,1680,'GPE'),(1700,1715,'GPE'),(1731,1773,'CHANGE'),(1775,1784,'GPE'),(1831,1836,'CARDINAL'),(1837,1842,'CASE'),(1853,1855,'CARDINAL'),(1863,1900,'DATE'),(1914,1919,'CARDINAL'),(1925,1927,'CARDINAL'),(1935,1944,'DATE'),(1972,2001,'ORG'),(2057,2065,'STATUS'),(2069,2075,'DISEASE'),(2081,2086,'CARIDNAL'),(2087,2092,'CASE'),(2126,2131,'CARDINAL'),(2132,2137,'CASE'),(2138,2147,'DATE'),(2149,2162,'ORG'),(2223,2231,'STATE'),(2243,2260,'ORG'),(2352,2360,'LOC_TYPE'),(2399,2403,'GPE'),(2483,2486,'ORG'),(2487,2493,'DISEASE'),(2567,2573,'DISEASE'),(2648,2653,'CASE'),(2807,2813,'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases on the rise but under control — DOH",
    "timestamp": "August 11, 2016",
    "content": "Metro Manila (CNN Philippines) — Dengue is on the rise, but the number of deaths is much lower than the “acceptable rate“ set by the World Health Organization, Health Secretary Paulyn Ubial said on Thursday. The Department of Health recorded 70,697 dengue cases from January 1 to July 23 this year — 19.1 percent higher than last year's record. However, the country's fatality rate (the ratio of deaths within a population of people diagnosed with the disease) now stands at 0.33 percent. This is almost 70 percent lower than the WHO's dengue fatality rate of one percent. “It's below the accepted case fatality, so I think we're doing well in the management of identified dengue cases,“ Ubial said. She said although the year-on-year data showed a rise in cases, a week-on-week comparison showed a downward trend. Ubial said it was too early to tell if the downward trend was an effect of the department's dengue vaccination program. But only half of the targeted one million Grade 4 students in Metro Manila, Southern Luzon, and Central Luzon took the vaccine. She said the negative publicity that surrounded the vaccine barred discouraged parents to let their children get vaccinated. The DOH also listed 47 barangays nationwide as dengue “hot zones.“ Four barangays in Metro Manila — three in Quezon City and one in Malabon — were identified as hot zones, while Region 4A registered the most number of cases. With dengue on the rise, the Health secretary urged people to practice the “4S Strategy“ against the disease: Searching and destroying mosquito breeding sites. Self-protection by applying mosquito repellent and covering exposed skin. Seeking early medical consultation. Saying no to indiscriminate fogging",
    "url": "http://cnnphilippines.com/news/2016/08/11/dengue-cases-rising-under-control-DOH.html",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,12,'GPE'),(14,29,'ORG'),('33,39,'DISEASE'),(133,158,'ORG'),(198,206,'DATE'),(212,232,'ORG'),(242,248,'CARDINAL'),(249,255,'DISEASE'),(256,261,'CASE'),(262,297,'DATE'),(300,312,'PERCENT'),(313,319,'CHANGE'),(325,334,'DATE'),(358,365,'LOC_TYPE'),(475,487,'PERCENT'),('504,514,'PERCENT'),(515,520,'CHANGE'),(530,533,'ORG'),(536,542,'DISEASE'),(560,571,'PERCENT'),(598,602,'CASE'),(673,679,'DISEASE'),(680,685,'CASE'),(757,762,'CASE'),(799,807,'CHANGE'),(858,866,'CHANGE'),(907,913,'DISEASE'),(965,976,'CARDINAL'),(997,1009,'GPE'),(1011,1025,'GPE'),(1031,1044,'GPE'),(1192,1195,'ORG'),(1208,1210,'CARIDNAL'),(1211,1220,'LOC_TYPE'),(1235,1241,'DISEASE'),(1243,1252,'STATE'),(1255,1259,'CARDINAL'),(1260,1269,'LOC_TYPE'),(1273,1285,'GPE'),(1288,1293,'CARDINAL'),(1297,1308,'GPE'),(1313,1316,'CARDINAL'),(1320,1327,'GPE'),(1349,1358,'STATE'),(1366,1375,'GPE'),(1406,1411,'CASE'),(1418,1424,'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases in Zamboanga City decrease",
    "timestamp": "October 7, 2015",
    "content": "Zamboanga City (CNN Philippines) — Amid the rise in other provinces and cities, Zamboanga City noted a decrease in the number of dengue cases for the month of September compared to last year. Based on the city’s health records, a total of 138 cases was reported in Zamboanga City for the month of September this year compared to 275 cases reported the same time last year. A decrease in cases was also observed for the past four months compared to last year's figures. There were reportedly 183 cases for June 2015 compared to 543 for June 2014. There were 301 cases for July 2015 compared to 583 for July 2014 and 240 cases for August this year compared to 339 last year.",
    "url": "http://cnnphilippines.com/regional/2015/10/07/Zamboanga-City-dengue-cases-decrease.html",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,14,'GPE'),(16,31,'ORG'),(58,67,'LOC_TYPE'),(72,78,'LOC_TYPE'),(80,94,'GPE'),(103,111,'CHANGE'),(129,135,'DISEASE'),(136,141,'CASE'),(150,168,'DATE'),(181,190,'DATE'),(205,209,'LOC_TYPE'),(239,242,'CARDINAL'),(243,248,'CASE'),(265,279,'GPE'),(288,316,'DATE'),(329,332,'CARDINAL'),(334,338,'CASE'),(362,371,'DATE'),(375,383,'CHANGE'),(387,392,'CASE'),(419,435,'DATE'),(448,457,'DATE'),(491,494,'CARDINAL'),(495,500,'CASE'),(505,514,'DATE'),(527,530,'CARDINAL'),(535,544,DATE'),(557,560,'CARDINAL'),(561,566,'CASE'),(571,580,'DATE'),(593,596,'CARDINAL'),(601,610,'DATE'),(615,618,'CARDINAL'),(619,624,'CASE'),(629,645,'DATE'),(658,661,'CARDINAL'),(662,671,'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases in Metro Manila, Cavite on the rise",
    "timestamp": "September 30, 2015",
    "content": "Metro Manila (CNN Philippines) — Health officials in Metro Manila are preparing for an overflow of dengue patients from Cavite to hospitals in the metropolis. The San Lazaro Hospital in Manila has added dengue to its Code White alert list since the Middle East Respiratory Syndrome scare hit early this year. A Code White alert means all hospital staff are on standby round the clock and that medicines and other supplies have been prepositioned. Dengue admissions in San Lazaro Hospital have more than doubled in August compared to the same month last year. The hospital administration said the number is still much lower, though, compared to the dengue outbreak in 2012. The hospital has 500 beds. One of the patients in the ward is three-year-old Jas Benebaye. She traveled all the way from Cavite as the hospitals there could not admit more patients. Her mother Gloria says she would much rather stay closer to home but was left with no choice. The Philippine National Police General Hospital has also been swamped with dengue cases. It has even opened a dengue express lane for those showing dengue-like symptoms. With its pediatric ward at near capacity, the hospital had to use other wards as well. The Department of Health warns that dengue is a threat during a long dry spell and reminds residents to destroy potential mosquito breeding sites.",
    "url": "http://cnnphilippines.com/news/2015/09/30/Dengue-cases-in-Metro-Manila-Cavite-on-the-rise.html",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,12,'GPE'),(14,29,'ORG'),(53,65,'GPE'),(99,105,'DISEASE'),(120,126,'GPE'),(147,157,'LOC_TYPE'),('147,157,'LOC_TYPE'),(186,192,'GPE'),(203,209,'DISEASE'),(217,233,'STATE'),(249,281,'DISEASE'),(292,307,'DATE'),(311,327,'STATE'),(447,453,'DISEASE'),(503,510,'CHANGE'),(514,520,'DATE'),(537,557,'DATE'),(612,622,'CHANGE'),(648,654,'DISEASE'),(667,671,'DATE'),(690,693,'CARDINAL'),(700,703,'CARDINAL'),(735,740,'CARDINAL'),(794,800,'GPE'),(1024,1030,'DISEASE'),(1031,1036,'CASE'),(1059,1065,'DISEASE'),(1097,1103,'DISEASE'),(1242,1248,'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "More than 400 dengue cases recorded in Laoag City",
    "timestamp": "September 24, 2015",
    "content": "Laoag City (CNN Philippines) — Officials in Laoag City are alarmed at the increasing number of dengue cases in the area. The City Health Office (CHO) said that more than 400 cases have been recorded in the city since January. One of the patients, a six-year-old girl, died after being hospitalized for more than a week. Just last week, at least 39 patients, four of them children from Barangay Talingaan, suspected of having dengue were rushed to the Laoag City General Hospital. Mayor Chevylle Fariñas said she would meet with health officials and coordinators to determine if there was a need to declare an outbreak of the disease. She also instructed barangay officials to intensify anti-dengue campaigns in their areas.",
    "url": "http://cnnphilippines.com/regional/2015/09/24/More-than-400-dengue-cases-recorded-in-Laoag-City.html",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,10,'GPE'),(12,27,'ORG'),(43,54,'GPE'),(95,101,'DISEASE'),(102,107,'CASE'),(125,143,'ORG'),(145,148,'ORG'),(170,173,'CARDINAL'),(174,179,'CASE'),(206,210,'LOC_TYPE'),(217,224,'DATE'),(226,229,'CARDINAL'),(249,252,'CARDINAL'),(312,318,'DATE'),(325,334,'DATE'),(345,347,'CARDINAL'),(358,362,'CARDINAL'),(385,403,'GPE'),(425,431,'DISEASE'),(451,461,'GPE'),(609,617,'STATE'),(654,662,'LOC_TYPE'),(691,697,'DISEASE')]"
}
]