[
{
    "title": "Talisay tops in number of dengue cases",
    "timestamp": "August 10, 2017",
    "content": "TALISAY City reported the highest number of dengue cases among component cities and towns in Cebu Province so far this year, health officials said yesterday. As of Aug. 5, Talisay had 296 dengue cases with nine deaths. Next to Talisay is Consolacion with 260 cases and four deaths, followed by Argao with 187 cases and one death. Talisay City also ranks fourth among towns and component cities in Central Visayas with the most number of dengue cases from January to August this year. Dr. Lino Alanzado, Talisay City health officer, said that a nine-month-old baby girl from Barangay Linao is the latest person to have died due to dengue this week. The report came just as the City Government started giving the anti-dengue vaccine to children in the 22 barangays. In an interview yesterday, Alanzado said they are doing their best to reduce the number of dengue cases and deaths through the help of the city’s Anti-Dengue Task Force. He said that one of the factors that contributed to the increase in the number of cases is the onset of the wet season. Alanzado said they will continue to intensify their efforts to reduce the number of dengue cases in the city. Their programs include information dissemination in all barangays and constant clean-and-green drive around the city. Alanzado also reminded parents to immediately seek medical help if their children are showing signs and suffer from the symptoms of dengue, which includes fever for more than three days.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/cebu/local-news/2017/08/10/talisay-tops-number-dengue-cases-557829",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,12,'GPE'),(34,40,'CASE'),(44,50,'DISEASE'),(51,56,'CASE'),(73,79,'LOC_TYPE'),(84,89,'LOC_TYPE'),(93,106,'GPE'),(114,123,'DATE'),(147,156,'DATE'),(164,170,'DATE'),(172,179,'GPE'),(184,187,'CARDINAL'),(188,194,'DISEASE'),(195,200,'CASE'),(206,210,'CARDINAL'),(227,234,'GPE'),(238,249,'GPE'),(255,258,'CARDINAL'),(259,264,'CASE'),(269,273,'CARDINAL'),(294,299,'GPE'),(305,308,'CARDINAL'),(309,314,'CASE'),(319,322,'CARDINAL'),(330,342,'GPE'),(354,358,'CARDINAL'),(367,372,'LOC_TYPE'),(387,393,'LOC_TYPE'),(397,412,'GPE'),(427,433,'CASE'),(437,443,'DISEASE'),(444,449,'CASE'),(450,482,'DATE'),(473,482,'DATE'),(503,515,'GPE'),(574,588,'GPE'),(630,636,'DISEASE'),(637,646,'DATE'),(716,722,'DISEASE'),(750,752,'CARDINAL'),(753,762,'LOC_TYPE'),(780,789,'DATE'),(834,840,'CHANGE'),(845,851,'CASE'),(855,861,'DISEASE'),(862,867,'CASE'),(903,907,'LOC_TYPE'),(910,932,'ORG'),(915,921,'DISEASE'),(990,998,'CHANGE'),(1006,1012,'CASE'),(1016,1021,'CASE'),(1117,1123,'CHANGE'),(1128,1134,'CASE'),(1138,1144,'DISEASE'),(1145,1150,'CASE'),(1158,1162,'LOC_TYPE'),(1220,1229,'LOC_TYPE'),(1276,1280,'LOC_TYPE'),(1414,1420,'DISEASE')]"
},
{
    "title": "NegOcc tops dengue cases, deaths in W. Visayas",
    "timestamp": "December 12, 2017",
    "content": "NEGROS Occidental, excluding its capital Bacolod City, posted the highest number of both dengue cases and deaths in this region, records of the Department Health (DOH) in Western Visayas showed. Based on the Morbidity Week 46 Report of the agency, there were 3,829 recorded dengue cases in the province since the start of the year. The figure accounts for almost 42 percent of the total 9,164 cases registered in Western Visayas during the period January 1 to November 18. Negros Occidental was followed by Iloilo with 1,088 cases; Aklan, 931; Antique, 680; Capiz, 316; and Guimaras, 37. Bacolod City ranked second with 1,704 cases while Iloilo City registered 380 cases only. The remaining 199 dengue cases were accounted for patients, who are only “visiting” or not really from the region. In terms of deaths, DOH-Western Visayas reported that Negros Occidental has 36, comprising 50 percent of total deaths in this region, at 72. Bacolod City again was in second spot, having 12 deaths. It was followed by Antique with 10; Iloilo Province, seven; Aklan, four; and Iloilo City, three. The provinces of Capiz and Guimaras recorded no deaths, the reports further showed. Dr. Reynilyn Reyes, head of the family, health and nutrition cluster of DOH-Western Visayas, Monday told SunStar Bacolod that higher dengue cases and deaths in Negros Occidental manifests the need for the province to implement stronger counter measures. She said that since dengue is a vector-borne disease, possibly there are many virus-carrier mosquitoes in the province. “It could be attributed to both environmental and host factors, including the vulnerability of patients,” Reyes said, adding that higher cases possibly resulted from “more” number of vector. The province maybe has potential habitats for mosquitoes especially Aedes Aegypti, posing higher risk of dengue virus infection to the public. It is good to have a strong vector-control program, the DOH-Western Visayas official said, adding that “this includes preventing the possible development of breeding places for mosquitoes mainly through maintaining cleanliness and sanitation on surroundings.” Negros Occidental has a case fatality rate (CFR) and attack rate of 0.94 percent and 149.19, respectively. Attack rate refers to the number of cases occurring over the total population times 100,000. This means that with the higher the attack rate, more cases occurred, Reyes said, adding that attack rate is proportionate with the population. For instance, Bacolod City has higher attack rate of 299.19 compared to that of Negros Occidental “because even though it has lower dengue cases than the province, its population is smaller.” High attack rates were also noted in the provinces of Aklan, 156.60; Antique, 114.14; Iloilo City, 81.78; and Iloilo Province, 54.77. Capiz and Guimaras registered an attack rate of only 40.66 and 20.84, respectively. Comparing this year’s figures to the same period in 2016, DOH-6 noted a 64 percent drop in the total number of dengue cases in Western Visayas. From January 1 to November 18 last year, the region had 25,461 dengue cases. In terms of deaths, there was also higher number of cases during the same period last year, 85. For Negros Occidental alone, the DOH-Western Visayas noted a decrease of 35 percent with last year’s recorded dengue cases in the province reaching 5,890. More death cases were also reported in the province the year before, 46. Also based on the same morbidity week, Bacolod City also posted a decrease of 16 percent, having previous cases of 2,025. “We continue to urge our local health offices to initiate the implementation of counter measures in their respective communities,” Reyes said The DOH-Western Visayas official also appealed to the public to actively take part in the fight against the deadly virus.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/bacolod/local-news/2017/12/12/negocc-tops-dengue-cases-deaths-w-visayas-579410",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,17,'GPE'),(41,53,'GPE'),(78,80,'CASE'),(89,95,'DISEASE'),(96,101,'CASE'),(121,127,'LOC_TYPE'),(163,166,'ORG'),(171,186,'GPE'),(223,225,'CARDINAL'),(259,264,'CARDINAL'),(274,280,'DISEASE'),(281,286,'CASE'),(294,302,'LOC_TYPE'),(313,330,'DATE'),(363,373,'PERCENT'),(387,392,'CARDINAL'),(393,398,'CASE'),(413,428,'GPE'),(447,456,'DATE'),(460,471,'DATE'),(473,490,'GPE'),(507,513,'GPE'),(519,524,'CARDINAL'),(525,530,'CASE'),(532,537,'GPE'),(539,542,'CARDINAL'),(544,551,'GPE'),(553,556,'CARDINAL'),(558,563,'GPE'),(565,568,'CARDINAL'),(574,582,'GPE'),(584,586,'CARDINAL'),(588,600,'GPE'),(620,625,'CARDINAL'),(626,631,'CASE'),(638,644,'GPE'),(661,664,'CARDINAL'),(665,670,'CASE'),(691,694,'CARDINAL'),(695,701,'DISEASE'),(702,707,'CASE'),(784,790,'LOC_TYPE'),(812,831,'ORG'),(816,831,'GPE'),(846,863,'GPE'),(868,870,'CARDINAL'),(883,893,'PERCENT'),(918,924,'LOC_TYPE'),(929,931,'CARDINAL'),(933,945,'GPE'),(979,981,'CARDINAL'),(1009,1016,'GPE'),(1022,1024,'CARDINAL'),(1026,1032,'GPE'),(1033,1041,'LOC_TYPE'),(1043,1048,'CARDINAL'),(1050,1055,'GPE'),(1057,1061,'CARDINAL'),(1067,1073,'GPE'),(1080,1085,'CARDINAL'),(1091,1099,'LOC_TYPE'),(1104,1109,'GPE'),(1114,1122,'GPE'),(1243,1262,'ORG'),(1264,1270,'DATE'),(1304,1310,'DISEASE'),(1311,1316,'CASE'),(1331,1348,'GPE'),(1376,1384,'LOC_TYPE'),(1445,1451,'DISEASE'),(1535,1543,'LOC_TYPE'),(1682,1687,'CASE'),(1718,1724,'CASE'),(1740,1748,'LOC_TYPE'),(1841,1847,'DISEASE'),(1935,1954,'ORG'),(1939,1954,'GPE'),(2139,2156,'GPE'),(2207,2219,'PERCENT'),(2224,2230,'CARDINAL'),(2272,2278,'CASE'),(2282,2287,'CASE'),(2330,2337,'CARDINAL'),(2393,2398,'CASE'),(2497,2509,'GPE'),(2536,2542,'CARDINAL'),(2563,2580,'GPE'),(2615,2621,'DISEASE'),(2622,2627,'CASE'),(2637,2645,'LOC_TYPE'),(2716,2724,'LOC_TYPE'),(2729,2734,'GPE'),(2736,2742,'CARDINAL'),(2744,2751,'GPE'),(2753,2759,'CARDINAL'),(2761,2767,'GPE'),(2774,2779,'CARDINAL'),(2802,2807,'CARDINAL'),(2785,2791,'GPE'),(2792,2800,'LOC_TYPE'),(2809,2814,'GPE'),(2819,2827,'GPE'),(2862,2867,'CARDINAL'),(2872,2877,'CARDINAL'),(2903,2912,'DATE'),(2945,2949,'DATE'),(2951,2954,'ORG'),(2965,2975,'PERCENT'),(2994,3000,'CASE'),(3004,3010,'DISEASE'),(3020,3035,'GPE'),(3042,3051,'DATE'),(3055,3066,'DATE'),(3067,3076,'DATE'),(3082,3088,'LOC_TYPE'),(3093,3099,'CARDINAL'),(3096,3098,'CARDINAL'),(3100,3106,'DISEASE'),(3156,3162,'CASE'),(3195,3204,'DATE'),(3206,3208,'CARDINAL'),(3214,3231,'GPE'),(3243,3262,'ORG'),(3247,3262,'GPE'),(3271,3279,'CHANGE'),(3283,3293,'PERCENT'),(3299,3308,'DATE'),(3320,3326,'DISEASE'),(3340,3348,'LOC_TYPE'),(3358,3363,'CARDINAL'),(3408,3416,'LOC_TYPE'),(3417,3432,'DATE'),(3434,3436,'CARDINAL'),(3477,3489,'GPE'),(3504,3512,'CHANGE'),(3516,3526,'PERCENT'),(3553,3558,'CARDINAL'),(3706,3725,'ORG'),(3710,3725,'GPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Philippines' dengue cases near 36,000",
    "timestamp": "June 15, 2017",
    "content": "THE number of dengue fever cases in the country has grown to nearly 36,000 in the first five months of this year, but lower than the same period last year, Health Secretary Paulyn Ubial said Thursday. In a statement for the commemoration of Asean Dengue Day, Ubial said that from January 1 to May 20 the DOH has recorded 35,973 dengue cases. The number, she said, is actually 31.8 percent lower compared to the 52,780 cases recorded during the same time period last year. “There is a decreasing trend of reported dengue cases to the Epidemiology Bureau,“ said Ubial. The DOH Epidemiology Bureau has reported 207 dengue deaths so far. Majority of the dengue cases were in Central Visayas (15.5 percent), Central Luzon (13 percent), National Capital Region (12.2 percent), Calabarzon (11.4 percent) and Soccsksargen (11.1 percent). The report also showed that most (21.5 percent) of the cases belongs to the five to nine years old age group. Meanwhile, the health chief clarified that expanded dengue immunization program in Cebu will be community-based, and not school-based like those in Metro Manila, Calabarzon, and Central Luzon. “The vaccination will be done in health centers but still the same target age group, which are Grade 4 public school pupils aged nine years old,“ said the DOH head. She explained that the change in venue was prompted by the absence of a formal agreement with the Department of Education (DepEd) for the program's expansion in Cebu. “I think it's because of the training, and of the lack of preparation, and we respect that,“ said Ubial. The health department earlier announced that the dengue vaccination program will be expanded to Cebu. This means that the program will no longer just be limited anymore to Metro Manila, Central Luzon, and Calabarzon. This was after the dengue immunization program in the three regions left some 500,000 unused doses. Ubial said the unused dosages will the only ones to be used and that they will not increase the supply any further. “We are not making any additional procurement for this. We are just trying to use the remaining vaccines, which will expire by August 2018,“ said Ubial.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/manila/local-news/2017/06/15/philippines-dengue-cases-near-36000-547588",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(4,10,'CASE'),(14,20,'DISEASE'),(27,32,'CASE'),(40,47,'LOC_TYPE'),(52,57,'CHANGE'),(68,74,'CARDINAL'),(82,112,'DATE'),(118,123,'CHANGE'),(145,154,'DATE'),(191,199,'DATE')(247,253,'DISEASE'),(328,334,'DISEASE'),(335,340,'CASE'),(346,352,'CASE'),(389,394,'CHANGE'),(418,423,'CASE'),(461,470,'DATE'),(513,519,'DISEASE'),(520,525,'CASE'),(612,618,'DISEASE'),(650,656,'DISEASE'),(657,662,'CASE'),(885,890,'CASE'),(992,998,'DISEASE'),(1619,1625,'DISEASE'),(1806,1812,'DISEASE'),(280,289,'DATE'),(293,299,'DATE'),(304,307,'ORG'),(571,574,'ORG'),(1288,1291,'ORG'),(321,327,'CARDINAL'),(376,388,'PERCENT'),(608,611,'CARDINAL'),(671,686,'GPE'),(688,700,'PERCENT'),(703,716,'GPE'),(1118,1131,'GPE'),(1756,1769,'GPE'),(718,728,'PERCENT'),(731,754,'GPE'),(756,768,'PERCENT'),(771,781,'GPE'),(1102,1112,'GPE'),(1775,1785,'GPE'),(783,795,'PERCENT'),(801,813,'GPE'),(815,827,'PERCENT'),(864,876,'PERCENT'),(1088,1100,'GPE'),(1742,1754,'GPE'),(1421,1426,'ORG'),(1023,1027,'GPE'),(1459,1463,'GPE'),(1666,1670,'GPE'),(1865,1872,'CARDINAL'),(1970,1978,'CHANGE'),(2130,2141,'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases in Zamboanga rise",
    "timestamp": "June 22, 2017",
    "content": "THE Zamboanga City Government through the City Health Office is conducting on Saturday, June 24, a citywide cleanup drive in a bid to lessen the cases of dengue fever. The City Health Office recorded an increase in dengue cases for the month of April and May this year compared to the same months last year. City Health Officer Rodelin Agbulos said they recorded 130 cases in April and 188 dengue cases in May this year. The dengue cases in April and May the previous year were 97 and 127, respectively. Agbulos said his office also recorded five deaths cause by dengue since January, this year. He advised the residents to continue the practice of the “4S” strategy to lessen the cases of dengue in the city. The 4S strategy includes: search and destroy; self-protection measures; seek early consultation; and, say yes to fogging only when there is an impending outbreak. “If we will not do something about the prevention and control of dengue, we expect an outbreak coming in on July, August, or September,” Agbulos said. Dengue fever is a viral disease usually affecting infant and young children. Aedes aegypti mosquitoes, which lay eggs on clear and stagnant water, are the spreader of the disease. The signs and symptoms of dengue fever included: sudden high fever; joints and muscle pains; skin rashes; nose bleeding; vomiting of coffee colored mattered; and, dark colored stool.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/zamboanga/local-news/2017/06/22/dengue-cases-zamboanga-rise-548914",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(4,29,'ORG'),(78,95,'DATE'),(154,166,'DISEASE'),(1024,1036,'DISEASE'),(1230,1242,'DISEASE'),(203,211,'CHANGE'),(215,221,'DISEASE'),(390,396,'DISEASE'),(425,431,'DISEASE'),(563,569,'DISEASE'),(690,696,'DISEASE'),(938,944,'DISEASE'),(145,150,'CASE'),(222,227,'CASE'),(367,372,'CASE'),(397,402,'CASE'),(432,437,'CASE'),(681,686,'CASE'),(245,250,'DATE'),(376,381,'DATE'),(441,446,'DATE'),(255,258,'DATE'),(406,409,'DATE'),(451,454,'DATE'),(264,268,'DATE'),(302,306,'DATE'),(415,419,'DATE'),(468,472,'DATE'),(590,594,'DATE'),(363,366,'CARDINAL'),(386,389,'CARDINAL'),(478,480,'CARDINAL'),(485,488,'CARDINAL'),(542,546,'CARDINAL'),(259,268,'DATE'),(410,419,'DATE'),(585,594,'DATE'),(704,708,'LOC_TYPE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases in Central Luzon down by 50%",
    "timestamp": "December 13, 2017",
    "content": "CITY OF SAN FERNANDO – Dengue cases in Central Luzon went down by almost 50 percent this year compared to last year, the Department of Health Central Luzon region said. DOH Central Luzon regional director Leonita Gorgolon said 2,006 cases of dengue were recorded from January to July this year, more than half of the 4,302 cases recorded in the same period in 2016. This period is considered the peak months for dengue cases due to the rainy season. Gorgolon said the numbers though could not be attributed to the implementation of the Dengvaxia vaccination program of the government wherein 205,000 grade nine and over children from Central Luzon were vaccinated. “We do not have enough data para sabihin na dahil ito sa vaccine na ininject namin sa mga bata. Nakikita lang talaga namin na bumaba ito dahil siguro wala rin naman gaanong tag-ulan this year (to say that this is due to the Dengvaxia vaccine. We only see that the (dengue) cases dropped and this is possible because there was no occurrence of rain this year),” she said.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/pampanga/local-news/2017/12/13/dengue-cases-central-luzon-down-50-579652",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,20,'GPE'),(23,29,'DISEASE'),(242,248,'DISEASE'),(412,418,'DISEASE'),(930,936,'DISEASE'),(30,35,'CASE'),(233,238,'CASE'),(323,328,'CASE'),(419,424,'CASE'),(938,943,'CASE'),(39,52,'GPE'),(142,155,'GPE'),(173,186,'GPE'),(634,647,'GPE'),(73,83,'PERCENT'),(169,172,'ORG'),(227,232,'CARDINAL'),(268,275,'DATE'),(279,283,'DATE'),(84,93,'DATE'),(284,293,'DATE'),(847,856,'DATE'),(1013,1022,'DATE'),(317,322,'CARDINAL'),(360,364,'DATE'),(592,599,'CARDINAL'),(944,951,'CHANGE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Dengue cases in Davao City drop",
    "timestamp": "June 15, 2017",
    "content": "DENGUE cases in Davao City this year dropped to 677 from 1,376 cases in the same period last year as the City Health Office (CHO) intensified its anti-dengue campaign in dengue-prone barangays since January. CHO Chief Josephine Villafuerte said the comparison of the data is based on the January to May dengue status report made by their office last week. The decrease of dengue patients, Villafuerte said, connotes the effectiveness of their campaign that started last January which included the Indoor Residual Spraying method, an application of long-acting chemical insecticides on the walls and roofs of all houses and domestic animal shelters in a given area, fogging method and cleaning of breeding sites. “The dengue-prone areas in the city remained the same as last year - Buhangin, Talomo, and Toril,“ Villafuerte said. Villafuerte said they have also piloted the formation of a Dengue Taskforce in Barangay Maa on Wednesday, June 14. She said the task force will regularly monitor all houses inside the community and see if there are possible breeding sites to immediately clean the area and report to CHO if a fogging and IRS is needed. She added that they will be implementing this throughout the city after an evaluation is done. “Prevention and control of dengue is in your hands. Take the initiative to destroy the breeding sites in your house and to constantly clean your surroundings,“ Villafuerte said.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/davao/local-news/2017/06/15/dengue-cases-davao-city-drop-547595",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(0,6,'DISEASE'),(151,157,'DISEASE'),(170,176,'DISEASE'),(303,309,'DISEASE'),(372,378,'DISEASE'),(717,723,'DISEASE'),(888,894,'DISEASE'),(1270,1276,'DISEASE'),(7,12,'CASE'),(63,68,'CASE'),(16,26,'GPE'),(37,44,'CHANGE'),(48,51,'CARDINAL'),(57,62,'CARDINAL'),(88,97,'DATE'),(769,778,'DATE'),(125,128,'ORG'),(208,211,'ORG'),(1112,1115,'ORG'),(183,192,'LOC_TYPE'),(199,206,'DATE'),(288,295,'DATE'),(470,477,'DATE'),(299,302,'DATE'),(345,354,'DATE'),(360,368,'CHANGE'),(659,663,'LOC_TYPE'),(730,734,'LOC_TYPE'),(1093,1097,'LOC_TYPE'),(105,109,'LOC_TYPE'),(743,747,'LOC_TYPE'),(1209,1213,'LOC_TYPE'),(924,942,'DATE')]"
},
{
    "title": "Baguio records 875% decrease in dengue cases",
    "timestamp": "June 26, 2017",
    "content": "THE BAGUIO City Health Services Office (BCHSO) reported a huge decrease in the incidence of dengue from January to June of 2017. Dr. Rowena Galpo, Baguio City Health Services Office chief, reported 64 cases of dengue from different barangays were recorded during the period which is an 875.34-percent decrease compared to the 703 cases recorded for the same period last year. Galpo attributed the huge decrease to the participation and involvement of the different sectors of the community, including the City Government. The health official said awareness of the community on the prevention of dengue contributed much, aside from the continuing program being undertaken by health officials to inform the public about the diseases and how to prevent it. This is aside from the local government’s role in institutionalizing the dengue awareness campaign. In December 2016, the City Council approved Ordinance 66 or the local anti-dengue act which provides for the prevention and control measures to mitigate dengue, and which requires all residents to strengthen the fight against it. The ordinance was passed to continually and substantially reduce the occurrence of dengue cases in the city through integrated vector management and implementation of prevention and control measures as well as to strengthen the fight against the disease. The city ordinance defines the mandatory role of household and business owners, schools and institutions, hospitals, church organizations, private and government offices and other work places. It also mandates the creation of the Baguio anti-dengue committee, the barangay anti-dengue committee as well as the guidelines and the fines and penalties for violators.",
    "url": "http://www.sunstar.com.ph/baguio/local-news/2017/06/26/baguio-records-875-decrease-dengue-cases-549583",
    "disease": "dengue",
    "entities": "[(4,46,'ORG'),(63,71,'CHANGE'),(301,309,'CHANGE'),(402,410,'CHANGE'),(79,88,'CASE'),(92,98,'DISEASE'),(210,216,'DISEASE'),(595,601,'DISEASE'),(827,833,'DISEASE'),(929,935,'DISEASE'),(1007,1013,'DISEASE'),(1167,1173,'DISEASE'),(1581,1587,'DISEASE'),(1617,1623,'DISEASE'),(104,111,'DATE'),(115,119,'DATE'),(123,127,'DATE'),(198,200,'CARDINAL'),(201,206,'CASE'),(330,335,'CASE'),(1174,1179,'CASE'),(232,241,'LOC_TYPE'),(286,300,'PERCENT'),(326,329,'CARDINAL'),(480,489,'LOC_TYPE'),(564,573,'LOC_TYPE'),(857,870,'DATE'),(147,153,'GPE'),(1569,1575,'GPE'),(154,158,'LOC_TYPE'),(505,509,'LOC_TYPE'),(876,880,'LOC_TYPE'),(1187,1181,'LOC_TYPE'),(1343,1347,'LOC_TYPE'),(1142,1148,'CHANGE')]"
}
]